<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Murrels tvvo books of cookerie and carving</title>
            <title>Murrels two books of cookerie and carving.</title>
            <author>Murrell, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 110 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51636</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220259</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831681</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831681</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36146</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51636)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36146)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2051:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Murrels tvvo books of cookerie and carving</title>
                  <title>Murrels two books of cookerie and carving.</title>
                  <author>Murrell, John, 17th cent.</author>
                  <author>Murell, John, 17th century. New book of cookerie. aut</author>
                  <author>Murrell, John, 17th cent. Second book of cookerie. aut</author>
                  <author>Murrell, John, 17th cent. New book of carving and serving. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The fifth time printed, with new additons.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[6], 188, [14] p., [3] plates.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M. F[lesher] for Iohn Marriot, and are to be sold at his shop in St Dunstans Churchyard in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>A2r is a separate title page, without imprint, reading: A nevv book of cookerie. Wherein is set forth a most perfect direction to furnish an extraordinary, or ordinary feast either in summer or winter. ..</note>
                  <note>F5r is a separate title page, with imprint: Printed for Iohn Marriot .. 1641. Title page reads: The second book of cookerie. VVherein is set forth the newest and most commendable fashion of dressing, boyling, sowcing, or roasting, all manner either flesh, fish, or any kinde of fowle. ..</note>
                  <note>K6r is a separate title page, with same imprint as the general title page, reading: A nevv book of carving and sevving [sic].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cookery --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Cookery (Meat) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Carving (Meat, etc.) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>MVRRELS TWO BOOKES OF COOKERIE AND CARVING.</p>
                  <p>The fifth time printed, with new Additions.</p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Marriot,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Dunſtans Churchyard in Fleetſtreet. 1641.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="list_of_illustrations">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Is morſige Iteden kuys worden / ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>chueren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e de panne van achteren.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:3"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <lg>
                           <head>LA CUISINIERE</head>
                           <l>Tous les ans nouvelle Cuisine</l>
                           <l>Car tous les ans changenl les goûts;</l>
                           <l>Ettous les Jours nouveaux ragouts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </l>
                           <l>Soyès done Chimiste Justine.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:4"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:5"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:5"/>
                  <p>A NEVV BOOK OF COOKERIE.</p>
                  <p>Wherein is ſet forth a moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect direction to furniſh an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, or ordinary-feaſt, either in <hi>Summer or Winter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo a Bill of Fare for Fiſh-dayes, Faſting-daies, Ember-weekes, or Lent.</p>
                  <p>And likewiſe the moſt commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble faſhion of Dreſsing, or Sowcing, either Fleſh, Fiſh, or Fowle: for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Gellies, and other Made-diſhes for ſervice, to beautifie either Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans or Gentlemans Table.</p>
                  <p>Together with the beſt and neweſt Art <hi>of Carving and Sewing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All ſet forth according to the now new <hi>Engliſh and French faſhion:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By IOHN MVRRELL.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:6"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:6"/>
                  <head>TO THE VERTVOVS and well accompliſhed Gentlewoman M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
                     <hi>Martha Hayes</hi> (Daughter to the honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Thomas Hayes</hi> Knight, late Lord Maior of the City of <hi>London:</hi>) health and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F this <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman,) many ſmall <hi>Books</hi> and <hi>Pamphlets</hi> have heretofore beene publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the moſt of which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe have inſtructed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther how to marre then make good Meate: but this (in
<pb facs="tcp:36146:7"/>credit of my knowledge, and ſtrict obſervation in Travell) is experimentally ſuch as it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to bee in the Title Page thereof. Whereof I can ſay bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this, and this it will perform for the ſayer, That it gives each Meat his right for the manner o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dreſſing; Each diſh his due, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the order of ſerving: and both good proofe of my deſire to pleaſe and profit in the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing. So, referring it to you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worthy peruſall, and my ſelfe to your favourable opinion, I eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> remaine.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>London,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>Iuly,</hi> 20 1630</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Yours, no leſſe humbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> then truly devote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="book">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36146:7"/>
                  <head>The firſt Booke of Cookery.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y reaſon of the generall ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of moſt men in this practiſe of Catering. I haue ſet downe here a perfect di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection how to ſet forth an extraordinary Dyet for the Summer ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when theſe things mentioned may eaſily be had. It ſerueth alſo for a Direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a Bill of fare: and alſo for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect direction for the ſeruing of dinner or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, twenty Diſhes to your firſt Meſſe, and as many to the ſecond Courſe to the ſame Meſſe, and ten to the third Courſe: ſo that in all you haue fifty diſhes to your Meſſe. For the boords end you may leaue out ſome of the coſtlieſt diſhes: if you haue ten or twelue for the boords end it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. If you cannot come by all theſe things named, then you may place ſome other thing at your diſcretion in the place, ſo that it be not groſſe meate, for groſſe meat diſgraceth the Feaſt.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36146:8"/>
                  <p>Alſo, another Direction for another ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice for the Winter ſeaſon, of twenty Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes to the firſt Meſſe, and as many to the ſecond Courſe to the ſame meſſe: ſo that in al there be forty Diſhes to the meſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be contrary to the other ſeruice of the Summer ſeaſon. And you may take of theſe meates half ſo many to the boords end, and it will be ſufficient both for the firſt and the ſecond: but if your perſons be of equall dignitie, then ſerue your firſt Meſſe, and the boords end, all as one alike equally.</p>
                  <p>A third Direction for a common ordinary Seruice of ten or twelue diſhes to a meſſe, to your firſt Meſſe, and as many to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Courſe to the ſame Meſſe, ſo that in all there will bee twenty diſhes to your Meſſe: but to your boords end ſixe or eight, according as your boord will hold. If any of theſe meates named be wanting, then you may place ſome other that you haue ready at hand.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Directions ſerue both for a Bill of fare, and to ſerue out your meat in good order: it is alſo a direction to young practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners which vnderſtand not theſe buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
                  <div type="bill_of_service">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36146:8"/>
                     <head>A Bill of ſervice for an extraordinary Feaſt for Summer ſeaſon, 50. diſhes to a Meſſe.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1</hi> A Grand Sallet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2</hi> A boyld Capon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3</hi> A boyld Pike.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4</hi> A diſh of boyld Pea-chickens, or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triges, or young Turky chicks.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5</hi> A boyld Breame.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6</hi> A diſh of young Wild-ducks.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7</hi> A diſh of boyld Quailes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>8</hi> A Florentine of Pufpaſte.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>9</hi> A forc'd boild meat.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>10</hi> A hanſh of Veniſon roaſted.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>18</hi> A Lombar Pye.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>12</hi> A Swan.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>13</hi> A Fawne or Kid, with a Pudding in his belly, or for want of a Fawne you may take a Pigge and fley it.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>14</hi> A Paſty of Veniſon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>15</hi> A Buſtard.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>26</hi> A Chicken Pye.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>17</hi> A Pheaſant or Powtes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>18</hi> A Potato Pye.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>19</hi> A Couple of Caponets.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>20</hi> A ſet Cuſtard.</item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36146:9"/>
                     <list>
                        <head>The ſecond Courſe.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1</hi> A Quarter of a Kid.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2</hi> A boyld Carpe.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3</hi> A Heron or Bitter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4</hi> A Congers head broyled, or Trouts.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5</hi> A Hartichoake pie.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6</hi> A diſh of Ruffs or Godwits.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7</hi> A cold bak'd meate.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>8</hi> A ſowſt pigge.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>9</hi> A Gull.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>10</hi> A cold bak'd meat.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>11</hi> A ſowſt pike, Breame, or Carp.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>12</hi> A diſh of partriges.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>13</hi> An Orengado pye.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>14</hi> A diſh of Quailes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>15</hi> A cold bak'd meate.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>16</hi> A freſh Salmon, pearch or Mullet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>17</hi> A Quodling Tart, Cherry, or Gooſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery Tart.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>18</hi> A dryed Neates-tongue.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>19</hi> A Iole of Sturgeon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>20</hi> A ſucket Tart of pufpaſte.</item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36146:9"/>
                     <list>
                        <head>The third Courſe for the ſame Meſſe.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1</hi> A Diſh of Pewets.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2</hi> A Diſh of Pearches.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3</hi> A diſh of gréen Peaſe, if they be dainty.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4</hi> Diſh of Dotrels.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5</hi> A diſh of Hartichoakes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6</hi> A diſh of buttered Crabs.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7</hi> A diſh of Prawnes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>8</hi> A diſh of Lobſtars.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>9</hi> A diſh of Anchoues.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>10</hi> A diſh of pickled Oyſters.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Another direction for a Bill of fare for Winter ſeaſon, and alſo ſerveth to ſet forth your meat in order.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1</hi> A Shield or Collar of Brawne.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2</hi> A Sallet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3</hi> A boyled Capon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4</hi> A boyld Gurnet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5</hi> A boyld Mallard.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6</hi> A forſt boyld meate.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7</hi> A roaſted Neats tongue with a pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in it.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>8</hi> A made diſh of puſpaſte.</item>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:36146:10"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>9</hi> A Shoulder of Mutton with Oliues, and Capers.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>10</hi> A Chine of Béefe.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>11</hi> A diſh of Chewets of Veale.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>12</hi> A Swan or Gooſe.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>13</hi> An Oliue-Pie.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>14</hi> A Pigge.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>15</hi> A Loyne of Veale or a Legge of Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>16</hi> A Larke or a Sparrow-pye.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>17</hi> A Turkey.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>18</hi> A Paſtie of Veniſon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>19</hi> A Capon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>20</hi> A Cuſtard.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>The ſecond courſe for the ſame meſſe.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1</hi> A Young Lamb or Kid.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2</hi> A couple of Rabbets.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3</hi> A Kickſhaw fryde or bak'd.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4</hi> A roaſted Mallard.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5</hi> A brace of Partriges.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6</hi> A Chicken-Pye.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7</hi> A brace of Woodcocks.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>8</hi> A couple of Teales.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>9</hi> A cold bak'd meate.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>10</hi> A diſh of Plouers.</item>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36146:10"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>11</hi> A diſh of Snites.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>12</hi> A cold bak'd meat.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>13</hi> A diſh of Larkes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>14</hi> A Quince, or Warden-Pye.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>15</hi> A bride Neates-tongue.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>16</hi> An Oyſter-Pye,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>17</hi> A diſh of Puffes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>18</hi> A Iole of Sturgion.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>19</hi> A laid Tart of Pufpaſte and ſucket.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>20</hi> A diſh of pickled Oyſters.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>The firſt Courſe for a ſmall common Service of Meate, to direct them which are unperfect, to bring them to further knowledge of greater Service.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1</hi> A Boyld Capon or Chicken.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2</hi> A Legge of Lambe farc'd of the French faſhion, or neates tongue.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3</hi> A boyld Mallard or Rabbet.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4</hi> A diſh of boild Oliues of Veale, or Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops and Egges.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5</hi> A piece of roaſt Béefe.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6</hi> A diſh of Chewets of Veal, or Mutton-pyes, if it be Winter, but if it bee ſummer an Oliue-pye.</item>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36146:11"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7</hi> A legge of Mutton roaſted whole, or a Loyne of Veale, or both.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>8</hi> A pigge.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>9</hi> A Swan, Gooſe, or Turkey.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>10</hi> A paſty of Veniſon, or forequarter of Mutton, or a fat rumpe of Béefe.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>11</hi> A Capon, pheaſant, or Hearne.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>15</hi> A Cuſtard.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>A ſecond Courſe to the ſame dyet.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1</hi> A Quarter of Lambe.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2</hi> A couple of Rabbets.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3</hi> A Maliard, Teale, or Widgin.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4</hi> A brace of partriges or Woodcocks,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5</hi> A Chicken or pigeon-pie.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6</hi> A diſh of plouers or Snites.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7</hi> A couple of Chickens.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>8</hi> A Warden or Quince-pie,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>9</hi> A ſowſt pig or Capon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>10</hi> A Cherrie or a Gooſeberrie Tart, or a Quarter-Tart of pippins.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>11</hi> A diſh of ſome kinde of ſowſt-fiſh.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>12</hi> Lobſtars or pickled Oyſters.</item>
                     </list>
                     <div type="part">
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36146:11"/>
                        <head>A Table of Direction for a Bill of fare for fiſh-daies, and Faſting dayes, Ember-weekes, or Lent.</head>
                        <list>
                           <head>The firſt Courſe for the ſame dyet.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1</hi> A Diſh of Butter.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2</hi> Rice milke.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3</hi> Buttered Egges.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4</hi> Stew'd Oyſters.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5</hi> A boyled Rochet or Gurnet.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>6</hi> A boyld Sallet of Hearbes, or of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>7</hi> A boyld pike.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>8</hi> Buttered Loaues.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>9</hi> Cheuets of Ling or Stockfiſh.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>10</hi> Another Sallet.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>11</hi> Stew'd Trouts or Smelts.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>12</hi> A diſh of butterd ſtockfiſh.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>13</hi> Salt Eele, or white-herring.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>14</hi> A Iole of Ling.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>15</hi> A Skirret-pye.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>16</hi> Buttered Flounders or plaice.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>17</hi> An Eele or Carpe-pye.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>18</hi> Haddocke, Freſh-Cod, or Whiting.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>19</hi> Salt Salmon.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>20</hi> A Cuſtard.</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36146:12"/>
                        <list>
                           <head>The ſecond courſe for this dyet.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1</hi> A Boyld Carpe.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2</hi> Spitcheockes of Eeles.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3</hi> Fride Stockfiſh.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4</hi> Boyld Eeles.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5</hi> Bakte Puffes.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>6</hi> A roaſted Eele.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>7</hi> Buttered Parſnips.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>8</hi> Fride Oyſters.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>9</hi> Blancht Manchet in a Fryingpan.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>10</hi> A fride Rochet.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>11</hi> An Oyſter-pye.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>12</hi> Fride Smelts.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>13</hi> A Pippin-pye.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>14</hi> Fride Flounders.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>15</hi> Butterd Crabs.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>16</hi> Fride Skirrets.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>17</hi> A Tart of Spinage or of Carrets.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>18</hi> Conger.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>19</hi> Lobſtar or Prawnes.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>20</hi> Pickled Oyſters.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>If your Meſſe be halfe ſo much for the boords end, it will bée enough both for the firſt and ſecond courſe.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="boiled_meats">
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:36146:12"/>
                        <head>To boyle a Capon Larded with Lemmons, on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Cald your Capon, and take a little duſty Oatmeale to make it boyle white. Then take two or three ladlefuls of Mutton broth, a fagot of ſweet Hearbs, two or three Dates, cut in long peeces, a few parboyld Currans, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle whole Pepper, a Peece of whole Mace, and one Nutmeg. Thicken it with Almonds. Seaſon it with Verjuyce, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and a little ſweet Butter. Then take vp your Capon, and larde it very thicke with a preſerved Lemmon. Then lay your Capon in a deep Meat-diſh for boyled meates, and powre the broth vpon it. Garniſh your diſh with Suckets and preſerued Barberries.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To ſowce a Pigge.</head>
                        <p>SCald a large Pigge, cut off his head and ſlit him in the middeſt, and take
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36146:13"/>out his bones, and waſh him in two or thrée warme waters. Then collar him vp like brawne, and ſow the collars in a faire cloath. Then boyle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very tender in the faire water, then take them vp and throw them in faire water and ſalt vntill they be cold, for that will make the skinne white. Then take a pottle of the ſame water that the Pigge was boyled in, and a Pottle of White-wine, a race of Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſliced, a couple of Nutmegs quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, a ſpoonfull of whole Pepper, five or ſix Bay-leaues: ſéethe all this together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when it is cold, put your Pigge into the ſowce-drinke, ſo you may keep it halfe a yeare, but ſpend the head.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To ſowce Oyſters.</head>
                        <p>TAke out the meat of the greateſt Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: ſaue the liquor that commeth from them; and ſtraine it into an earthen Pipkin: put into it half a pinte of white-Wine, and half a pinte of White-Wine Vinegar: put in ſome whole Pepper, and ſliced Ginger. Boyle all theſe together with two or thrée Cloaues, when it hath boyled a little, put in your Oyſters, &amp; let them boyle two or thrée walmes, but not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36146:13"/>too much. Then take them vp, and let the ſirrup ſtand vntill it be cald: then put in your Oyſters, and ſo you may kéep them all the yeare.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To ſowce Pike, Carpe, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>me.</head>
                        <p>DRaw your Fiſh, but ſcale it not: ſaue the Liver and the refuſe of it, ſlit the ſaid refuſe, and waſh it. Then take a pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of faire water, and a quart of White-Wine, and a faggot of ſweet hearbes: ſo ſoon as you ſee your Wine boyle, throwin your Fiſh with the ſcales on, and when you ſee your Fiſh boyle, poure in a little Vinegar, and it wil make your Fiſh criſp. Then take vp your Fiſh, and put it in a Tray. Then put into the liquor ſome whole pepper, a little whole Ginger, and when it is boyled together well with a little Salt, and cold, put in your Fiſh into an earthen panne: when you ſerue it in, ſerue Gelly in Sawcers, with a little fine Ginger about the Sawcers ſides, and Fennell on your Fiſh.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:36146:14"/>
                        <head>To boyle Flounders or Gudgeons on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>BOyle a pinte of White-Wine, and a pinte of faire Water, a few ſweet Hearbes, tops of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>, ſweet Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joram, winter Sauo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ps of Roſemary, a peece of whole Mace, a little Parſly pickt ſmall: when all is boyled well together, put in your Fiſh, and ſcum it well. Then put in a little cruſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet, a quarter of a pound of ſwéet But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Seaſon it with Pepper, and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juyce, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle a Gurnet on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>DRaw your Gurnet, &amp; waſh it clean, boyle it in water and ſalt, with a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got of ſwéet Hearbs: then take it up, and powre vpon it Verjuyce, Nutmeg, But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; Pepper: thicken it with the yolkes of two new layd Egges. All this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing powred vpon your Fiſh, garniſh your diſh with preſerued Barberries, or a ſliced Orange.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:36146:14"/>
                        <head>To boyle a Legge of Mutton on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>CVt out all the meat at the Butt end, leauing the bone ſtill in. Mince it ſmall with Beefe Suit, and Marrow. Then take ſweet Creame, yolks of Egs, a few Raiſins of the Sunne, two or thrée Dates minced, a little grated Bread. Seaſon it with Pepper, Salt, and Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megge: then worke it ſtiffe, like a Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and cram it in againe. Then ſtue it in a Pot with a Marrow bone, and a knuckle of Veale: ſerue the Legge by it ſelfe, and your knuckle in ſtued broth, &amp; your Marrow-bones vpon Bruys, with Carrets, and Pepper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To haſh a Legge of Mutton on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>PArboile your Legge, and take it vp &amp; pare off ſome thin ſlices &amp; prick your Legge through, and let out the grauie on the ſlices: then bruiſe ſweet Hearbs with the back of a Ladle, and put in a peece of ſweet Butter: Seaſon it with Verjuyce &amp; Pepper: and when your Mutton is boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, pour it on it, &amp; ſerve it ſo to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:36146:15"/>
                        <head>To roaſt a legge of Mutton, on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>PAre all the skinne as thin as you can Lard it with ſweet Lard, and ſticke about it a dozen Cloues: when it is half roaſted, cut off three or foure thin pieces &amp; mince it ſmall with a few ſweet hearb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> and a little beaten Ginger: put in a ladle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full of Claret-wine, a piece of ſweet But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, two or three ſpoonfuls of verjuyce, little Pepper, a few parboyld Capers when all this is boyled together, chop th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> yolk of an hard Egge into it. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dridg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> your Legge, and ſerue it vpon ſawce.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To roaſt a Neates tongue, on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>CHop ſweet hearbes fine, with a piec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of a raw Apple, ſeaſon it with Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Ginger, and the yolk of a new la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> Egge chopt ſmall to mingle amongſt it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> then ſtuffe it well with that farcing, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſo roaſt it. The ſawce for it is Verjuyce Butter, and the juyce of a Lemmon, &amp; little Nutmegge. Let the tongue lye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> the ſawce when it goeth to the Table
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36146:15"/>Garniſh your Diſh as you thinke fitteſt, or as you are furniſht.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle Pigeons with Rice on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>FIt them to boyle, and put into their bellies ſweet Hearbs, <hi>viz.</hi> Parſley, tops of yong Tyme: &amp; then put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a Pipkin, with as much Mutton broth as will couer them, a piece of whole Mace, a little whole Pepper: boyle all theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vntill your Pigeons bee tender. Then take them off the fire, and ſcum of the fat cleane from the broth, with a ſpoone, for otherwiſe it will make it to taſte ranke. Put in a piece of ſweet But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: ſeaſon it with Verjuyce, Nutmeg, and a little Sugar, thicken it with Ryce boyled in ſweet Creame. Garniſh your Diſh with preſerued Barberies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret roots, being boyled with Verjuyce &amp; Butter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle a Rabbet with Hearbs on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>FIt your Rabbet for the boyling, and ſeethe it with a little Mutton broth, White-wine and a piece of whole Mace:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36146:16"/>then take Lettuce, Spinage, Parſley, Winter Sauory, ſweet Marjoram: all theſe being pickt, and waſht clean, bruiſe them with the backe of a Ladle (for the bruiſing of the hearbs wil make the broth looke very pleaſantly gréene.) Thicken it with a cruſt of manchet, being ſtéeped in ſome of the broth, and a little ſweet. Butter therein. Seaſon it with Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juyce, and Pepper, and ſerue it to the Table upon Sippets. Garniſh your diſh with Barberries.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle Chickens in white broth.</head>
                        <p>TRuſſe your Chickens fit to boyle, as was before ſhewed in the Rabbets, cut two or three Dates in ſmall peeces: take a péece of whole Mace: thicken your broth with Almonds: Seaſon it with Verjuyce, and a little Pepper. Garniſh your diſh ſides with ſweet Sucket and ſugar, after you haue ſeaſoned your broth. In like ſort you may boyle a Capon, but then you muſt put Marrow into your White broth. If you diſlike Mutton-broth, then boyle it by it ſelfe in faire wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter till it turne as white as a Curd. But
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36146:16"/>the French men follow the other way, &amp; it is the better.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle a Teale or Wigeon on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle either of theſe Fowles, and throw them in a Pale of faire water (for that taketh away the ranckneſſe of the fleſh.) Then roaſt them halfe, &amp; take them off the fire, &amp; put ſweet Hearbs in the bellies of them: lace them downe the breaſt, and ſtick them with two or three whole Cloues in the breſt with your knif in euery one of them ſo many. Then put them in a Pipkin, with two or three ladle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of ſtrong Mutton broth, a peece of whole Mace, two or three little Onyons minſt ſmall. Thicken it with a toaſt of houſhold bread: put in a péece of ſwéet but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as big as a Walnut: Seaſon it with Pepper and Verjuyce.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To ſmoore an old Coney Ducke, or Mallard on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle any of theſe &amp; halfe roaſt it, lanch them downe the breaſt with your knife, and ſticke them with two or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36146:17"/>thrée Cloues. Then put them into a pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin with halfe a pound of ſweet Butter, a little White-wine, Verjuyce, a péece of whole Mace, a little beaten Ginger, and Pepper. Then mince two Onyons very ſmall, with a péece of an Apple, ſo let them boyle leiſurely, cloſe couered, the ſpace of two houres, turning them now &amp; then. Serue them in vpon Sippets.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Another way to boyle Chickens, or Pigeons with Gooſeberryes or Grapes.</head>
                        <p>BOyle them with Mutton-Broth, and White-wine, a péece of whole Mace, put into the bellies of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſwéet Hearbs: when they be tender, thicken it with a péece of Manchet and two hard eg yolks ſtrained with ſome of the ſame broth. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put ſome of the ſame broth into a boyld-meat diſh, with Verjuyce, Butter, and Sugar, and ſo boyle your Grapes or Gooſeberries in the diſh cloſe couered, till they be tender, &amp; poure it on the breaſt of your diſh.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:36146:17"/>
                        <head>To boyle a Chine of Mutton or Veale, in ſharp broth, on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>COuer your meate with faire water and a little White-wine, a peece of whole Mace, a Nutmeg quartered, a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Hearbs cleane pickt, and bruiſed with the back of a Ladle, young Lettice, Spinage, Parſley, tops of young Tyme: when all is boyled well together, thicken it with a cruſt of Manchet, and the yolke of a hard Eg, ſteeped in ſome of the ſame broth, and draw it through a ſtrainer, and thicken your broth with it. Seaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it with a little Verjuyce and Pepper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle Larks or Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes.</head>
                        <p>TRuſſe them fit to boyle, and put them into a Pipkin, with a Ladlefull of Mutton-broth, a peece of whole Mace, a quarter of a Nutmegge, a fagot of ſweet Hearbs, and a little young Parſley pickt cleane and ſhort: put your Parſley looſe into your broth: ſeaſon it with Verjuyce, Pepper and Sugar. Thicken it with the yolkes of two new laid Egges hard, &amp; a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36146:18"/>peece of Manchet, ſtrained with ſome of the ſame broth, till they be tender. Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh your diſh as you will.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="baked_meats">
                     <head>Baked-meates.</head>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A made diſh of Coney Livers.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Arboyle thrée or foure of them, and then chop them fine with ſwéet Hearbes, the yolks of two hard Egs, Seaſon it with Cinamon, Dinger, and Nutmeg, and Pepper: put in a few parboyld Currans, and a little mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted butter, and ſo make it vp into little paſtyes, frye them in a Fryingpan, ſhaue on Sugar, and ſerue them to the boord.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A made diſh of Sweet-bread.</head>
                        <p>BOyle, or roaſt your Sweet-bread, and put into it a few parboyld Currans, a minſt Date, the yolkes of two new laid Egges, a peece of Manchet grated fine,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36146:18"/>Seaſon it with a little pepper, Salt, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, and Sugar, wring in the juyce of an Drange or Lemmon, and put it between two ſhéets of Puf-paſte, or any other good paſte: and either bake it, or fry it, whether you pleaſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A made diſh of Sheepes tongues.</head>
                        <p>BOyle them tender, and ſlice them in thin ſlices: then ſeaſon them with Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Ginger, and a little Pepper, and put them into a Coffin of fine Paſte, with ſweet Butter, and a few ſwéet Hearbes chopt fine. Bake them in an Duen. Then take a little Nutmeg, Vinegar, Butter, Sugar, the yolke of a new layd Egge, one ſpoonfull of Sacke, &amp; the juyce of a Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: boyl all theſe together on a chafing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh of Coales, and put it into your Pye: ſhog it well together, and ſerue it to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Florentine of a Cony, the wing of a Capon, or the Kidney of Veale.</head>
                        <p>MInce any of theſe with ſweet hearbs, parboyld Currans, a Date or two minſt ſmall, a peece of a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Drange or Lemmon, minſt as ſmall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36146:19"/>as your Date. Seaſon it with Ginger, Cinamon, Nutmeg, &amp; Sugar: then take the yolkes of two new laid Egges, a ſpoonfull of ſweet Creame, a peece of a ſhort Cake grated and marrow cut in ſhort peeces. Bake this in a diſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two leaues of puf-paſte, put a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Roſe-water to it before you cloſe your paſte. When it is baked, ſhaue on Sugar.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Fridayes Pye, without either Fleſh or Fiſh.</head>
                        <p>WAſh greene Beets clean, picke out the middle ſtring, and chop them ſmall with two or three well reliſht ripe Apples. Seaſon it with Pepper, Salt, and Ginger: then take a good handfull of Raiſins of the Sunne, and put them all in a Coffin of fine Paſte, with a peece of ſweet Butter, and ſo bake it: but before you ſerue it in, cut it vp, and wring in the juyce of an Drange and Sugar.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Chewet of Stockfiſh.</head>
                        <p>BOyle watered Stockfiſh, and make it fit to be eaten: when it is cold take the whiteſt of the fiſh and mince it ſmall: put in parboyld Currans, Ralſins of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36146:19"/>Sunne, Seaſon it with Nutmeg, Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Salt, and a peece of ſweet Butter. Bake it, but before you ſerue it in, cut it vp, and wring in the juyce of an Drange.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Quarter-Tart of Pippins.</head>
                        <p>QUarter them and lay them between two ſheets of Paſte: put in a peece of whole Cinamon, two or three bruiſed Cloues, a little ſliced Ginger, Drengado, or only the yellow outſide of the Drange, a bit of ſweet Butter about the bigneſſe of a Egge, good ſtore of Sugar: ſprinkle on a little Roſe water. Then cloſe your Tart, and bake it: Ice it before it goe to the boord, ſerve it hot. This Tart you may make of any puf-paſte, or ſhort paſte that will not hold the raiſing. If you bake in any of theſe kindes of paſtes, then you muſt firſt boyle your Pippins in Claret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine and Sugar, or elſe your Apples will be hard when your Cruſt will be burnt &amp; dryed away. Beſides, the wine giueth them a pleaſant Colour, and a good taſte alſo. Though you boyle your Pippins tender, take heed you breake not the quarters, but bake them whole.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:36146:20"/>
                        <head>A Gooſeberry Tart.</head>
                        <p>PIck the ſtalkes of your Gooſeberries, and the pips in the tops: put them in good Paſte, with a little gréene Ginger fliced in ſlices: caſt on good ſtore of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Roſewater, and ſo cloſe them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Cherry Pye.</head>
                        <p>BRuiſe a pound of Cherries, and ſtamp them, and boyle the ſirrup with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar. Then take the ſtones out of two pound: bake them in a ſet Coffin: Ice them, and ſerve them hot in to the boord.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make an Oyſter Pye.</head>
                        <p>SAue the liquor of your largeſt Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, ſeaſon them with Pepper and Ginger, and put them into a Coffin: put in a minſt Dnyon, a few Currans, and a good péece of Butter. Then poure in your ſirrup and cloſe it. When it is bak't, cut vp the Pye, and put in aſpoonefull of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar and melted Butter: ſhake it well together, and ſet it again into the Duen a little while: then take it out, &amp; ſerue it in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:36146:20"/>
                        <head>A made diſh of Muſckels and Cockles.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle them and take out the meat, and waſh them very cleane in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they were boyled in, &amp; a little white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine: mince them ſmal with two or thrée yolkes of new-laid Egges. Seaſon it with Pepper, Salt, and a little Nutmeg: then wring in the juyce of an Drange, and put them betwéene two ſhéetes of Paſte, Cake it, Ice it, and vſe it: you may alſo fry them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake Neates tongues to be eaten hot.</head>
                        <p>BOyle it tender, and pill off the skin, take the fleſh out at the Butt-end: mince it ſmall with Oxe-ſuet, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. Seaſon it with Pepper, Salt, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megge, parboyld Currans, and a minced Date cut in péeces. Take the yolkes of two new-laid Egges, and a ſpoonefull of ſwéet Creame, worke all together with a ſiluer ſpoone in a Diſh, with a little pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of a dryed Drange-pill: ſprinckle a little Verjuyce ouer it, and caſt on ſome Sugar. Then thruſt it in againe as hard as you can exam it. Bake it on a diſh
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36146:21"/>in the Duen: baſte it with ſwéet Butter, that it may not bake dry on the outſide: when it is to be eaten, ſawce it with Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar and Butter, Nutmeg, Sugar &amp; the juyce of an Drange.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A delicate Chewet.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle a péece of a Leg of Veale, and being cold, mince it with Béefe ſuet, and Marrow, and an Apple, or acouple of Wardens: when you haue minſt it fine, put a few parboyled Currans, ſixe Dates minſt, a péece of preſerued Drange-pill minſt, Marrow cut in little ſquare péeces: Seaſon all this with Pepper, Salt, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, and a little Sugar: then put it into your Coffins, and ſo bake it. Before you, cloſe your Pye, ſprinckle on a little Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, and when they are baked ſhaue on a little Sugar, and ſo ſerue it to the table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make an Umble Pye, or for want of Umbles to doe it with a Lambes head and Purtnance.</head>
                        <p>BOyle your meat reaſonable tender, take the fleſh from the bone, &amp; mince it ſmall with Béefe-ſuet and Marrow
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36146:21"/>with the Liuer, Lights, and Heart, a few ſwéet Hearbes and Currans. Seaſon it with Pepper, Salt, and Nutmeg:bake it in a Coffin raiſed like an Vmble pye, and it will eat ſo like unto Vmbles, as that you ſhall hardly by taſte diſcerne it from right Umbles.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Calves Chaldron.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle it, and coole it, and pick out the Kernels, and cut it in ſmall peeces: then ſeaſon it with Pepper, Salt, &amp; Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg: put in a few ſwéet Hearbs chopt, a péece of ſwéet butter, ſprinckle it with uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juyce, and ſo cloſe it. When you ſerue it in, put to it a little of a cawdle, made with Nutmeg, Vinegar, Butter, Sugar, and the yolks of two new laid Egs, a ſpoone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Sack, and the juyce of an Orange.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Carpe.</head>
                        <p>SCald, waſh and draw a ſayre large Carpe: ſeaſon it with Pepper, Salt, and Nutmeg, and put it in a Coffin with good ſtore of ſwéet Butter: caſt on great Raiſins of the Sunne, the juyce of two Oranges, put your Butter uppermoſt, to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36146:22"/>kéepe the reſt moiſt: ſprinckle on a little Vinegar before you cloſe it, and ſo bake it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Tench with a Pudding in her belly.</head>
                        <p>LEt your fiſh blood in the Taile, then ſcald it, and ſcoure it: waſh it cleane, and dry it with a doth. Then take gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Bread, ſwéet Creame, the yolkes of two or thrée new-laid Egges, a few par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyld Currans, a few ſwéet Hearbs chopt fine. Seaſon it with Nutmeg and Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and make it into a ſtiffe pudding, and put it into your Tenches belly. Seaſon your fiſh on the outſide with a little Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Salt, and Nutmegge, and put him in a déepe Coffin with a péece of ſwéet But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſo cloſe your Pye, and bake it. Then take it out of the Ouen, and open it, and caſt in a péece of preſerued O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range minſt. Then take Vinegar, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, Butter, Sugar, and the yolke of a new-laid Egge, and boyle it on a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingdiſh of Coales, alwaies ſtirring it to keepe it from curding. Then poure it into your Pye, ſhogge it well together, and ſerue it in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:36146:22"/>
                        <head>To bake Eeles.</head>
                        <p>CUt your Eeles about the length of your finger: ſeaſon them with Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Salt, and Ginger, and ſo put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Coffin, with a good peece of ſweet Butter. Put into your Pye great Raiſins of the Sun, and an Onyon minſt ſmall, &amp; ſo cloſe it and bake it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake Chickens with Grapes.</head>
                        <p>TRuſſe and ſcald your Chickens, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon them well with pepper, ſalt, and Nutmeg: and put them into your Pye, with a good peece of Butter; bake it &amp; cut it vp, and put vpon the breaſt of your Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, Grapes, boild in Uerjuyce, Butter, Nutmeg, and Sugar, with the juyce of an Orange.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Steake pye with a French pudding in the pye.</head>
                        <p>SEaſon your Steakes with Pepper, Salt, and Nutmeg: and let it ſtand in a tray an houre: Then take a peece of the leaneſt of a Legge of Mutton, and mince it ſmall with Oxe-ſuet, and a few
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36146:23"/>ſwéet Hearbs, tops of young Tyme, a branch of Pennyroyal, two or three leaues of red Sage, grated Bread, yolks of Egs, ſweet Cream, Raiſins of the Sunne, work all together like a Pudding with your hand ſtiffe, and roule it round like bals, and put them in your Steakes in a deep Coffin, with a good peece of ſweet butter, ſprinckle a little Uerjuyce on it, and bake it: then cut it vp, and roule Sage: leaues in Butter, and frye them, &amp; ſtick them vpright in your wals, &amp; ſerue your Pye without a couer, with the juyce of an Orange or Lemmon.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make a good Quince Pye.</head>
                        <p>PAre them, and coare them (the beſt of the Quinces is next unto the skinne, therefore pare it as thinne as is poſſible) ſtuffe them with Sugar, then with as much other Sugar as they weigh, put them with peeces of ſliced ginger in a Coffin, ſprinckle on a little Roſe-water before you cloſe your Pye. Bake it, and let it ſtand long a ſoaking in the ouen, Ice it, and ſerue it in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:36146:23"/>
                        <head>To make a Pippin Pye.</head>
                        <p>TAke their weight in Sugar, &amp; ſtick a whole Cloue in euery peece of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and put in peeces of whole Cinamon, then put in all your Sugar, with a ſlice or two of whole Ginger: ſprinckle Roſe-water on them before you cloſe your Pye: bake them and ſerue them in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Pigge.</head>
                        <p>SCald it, and ſlit it in the middeſt, flay it, and take out the bones. Seaſon it with Pepper, Salt, Cloues, Mace, and Nutmeg: chop ſweet hearbs fine with the hard yolkes of two or three new layd Egges, and parboyld Currans. Then lay one halfe of your Pigge into your pye, and hearbs on it: then put on the other halfe with more hearbes aloft vpon it, and a good peece of ſweet Butter aloft vpon all. It is a good diſh both hot and cold.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake Fallow Deer in the beſt manner.</head>
                        <p>BAke it firſt in his owne blood, onely wipe it clean, but waſh it not, bone it
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36146:24"/>and skin it, and ſeaſon it with Pepper &amp; Salt. Then bake it in fine Paſte after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, either puft-paſte or ſhort-paſte.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Red Deere.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle it, and dreſſe it, and let it lye all night in Red Wine, and Vinegar: then Larde it thicke, and ſeaſon it with Pepper, ſalt, Cloues, Mace, Nutmeg, and Ginger. Bake it in a deep Coffin of Rye paſte, with ſtore of Butter: let it ſoake well. Leaue a vent-hole in your Pye, and when you draw it out of the Quen, put in melted Butter, Vinegar, Nutmeg, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and a little Sugar: ſhake it very well together, and put it into the Quen again, &amp; let it ſtand three or foure houres at the leaſt, to ſoake thorowly: when your Quen is cold: take it out, and ſtop the hole with Butter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a wilde Boare.</head>
                        <p>TAke the buttocke of a Brawne, and the fillets: parboyle it, and mince it ſmall, and ſtampe it in a Morter till it come like paſte all in a lumpe. Then lard
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36146:24"/>it, and vſe it like the Red Deere. The fillets alſo of béefe for a need will ſerue very well.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Swan.</head>
                        <p>SCald it, and take out the bones: then parboyle it and ſeaſon it well with Pepper, Salt, and Ginger. Then Lard it, and put it in a deep Coffin of Rye-paſte, with ſtore of Butter. Let it ſoake well: when you take it out of the Quen, put in more Butter moulten at the vent-hole.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Turkey or a Capon.</head>
                        <p>BOne the Turkey, but not the Capon: parboyle them, and ſticke cloues in their breaſts: Lard them and ſeaſon them well with Pepper and Salt, &amp; put them in a deep Coffin with the breaſt downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and ſtore of Butter: and when it is bak't, poure in more Butter, and when it is cold, ſtop the vent hole with more butter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Hare on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle two Hares, and take the fleſh from the bone, and mince it ſmall,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36146:25"/>and beat it in a Morter into a lumpy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: then ſowce it in Wine and Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, as you would doe red Deere, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it alſo. Lap all this pulp about the Chine of one Hare, ſo it wil ſeem but one: Lard it well, and put it into a Coffin, with ſtore of butter, and ſo bake it. Then take it out of the Ouen, and put into it a little melted Butter, Nutmeg, Ginger and Sugar, and ſet it into the Ouen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to ſoake: when it is cold ſtop the hole with Butter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a wild Gooſe or Mallard.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle them, and breake the breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone of a large Gooſe, or take it quite out, and all the other bones alſo, but not out of a Mallard. Seaſon them and lard them and put them into deepe Coffins, with ſtore of Butter; when you draw them out of the Ouen, put in more, and doe as before is ſhewed.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Curlew or Hearneſhaw.</head>
                        <p>TRuſſe them, and parboyle them, but vpon one ſide. Seaſon them with Pepper, Salt, and Ginger. Put them in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36146:25"/>deep Coffins, with ſtore of Butter, &amp; let the heads hang out for a ſhow.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake Woodcocks, or Black-birds.</head>
                        <p>TRuſſe, parboyle, &amp; ſeaſon them with Pepper and Salt: your Woodcocke may be larded: doe as in other.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake Larkes or Sparrowes.</head>
                        <p>SErue them as before was ſhewed in the Woodcocks and Blacke-birds.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Fritters on the Court-faſhion.</head>
                        <p>TAke the Curds of a Sack poſſet, the yolkes of ſixe new-laid Egges, and the whites of two of them, fine flower, &amp; make thicke batter: cut a Pome water in ſmall peeces: ſeaſon it with Nutmeg and a little Pepper, put in a little ſtrong Ale, and warme milke: mingle all together, and put them into Lard, neither too hot nor too cold. If your batter ſwim, it is in good temper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:36146:26"/>
                        <head>To make Pancakes ſo criſpe, that you may ſet them upright.</head>
                        <p>MAke a dozen or a ſcore of them in a little frying-pan, no bigger then a Sawce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, and then boyle them in Lard, &amp; they wil look as yellow as gold, beſide the taſte will be very good.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Sallet of Roſe-buds and Cloue Gillyflowers.</head>
                        <p>PIck Roſe-buds, and put them into an earthen Pipkin, with White-wine vinegar and Sugar: ſo may you vſe Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlips, Violets, or Roſe-mary-flowers.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To keepe green Cucumbers all the yeare.</head>
                        <p>CVt the Cucumbers in peeces, boyle them in ſpring-water, Sugar, and Dill, a walme or two. Take them vp and let your pickle ſtand vntill it be cold.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To keepe Broome Capers.</head>
                        <p>BOyle the greateſt &amp; hardeſt buds of the Broome in Wine Vinegar and Bay-ſalt, ſcum it cleane: when it is cold, you may put in raw ones alſo, each by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36146:26"/>themſelues: put in a peele of Lead on the raw ones, for all that ſwim will be black, and the other that are preſſed downe, as greene as any Leek. The boyld ones wil change colour.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Purſlaine ſtalkes.</head>
                        <p>GAther them at the full growth, but not too old: parboyle them, and keepe them in White-wine Vinegar and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make Caper-rowlers of Radiſh cods.</head>
                        <p>TAke them when they be hard, &amp; not ouer much open: boyle them tender in fair water, boyle White-wine Vinegar and bay-ſalt together, and keep them in it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Divers Sallets boyled.</head>
                        <p>PArboile Spinage, &amp; chop it fine, with the edges of two hard Trenchers vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a boord, or the backs of two Choppin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kniues: then ſet them on a Chafindiſh of Coales with Butter and Vinegar. Seaſon it with Cinamon, Ginger, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and a few parboyld Currans. Then
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36146:27"/>cut hard Egges into quarters to garniſh it withall, and ſerue it upon Sippets. So may you ſerue Burrage. Bugloſſe, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diff, Suckory, Coleflowers, Sorrell, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigold-leaues, Water-creſſes, Leekes boyled, Onyons, Sporragus, Rocket, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexanders, Parboyle them and ſeaſon them all alike: whether it be with Oyle and Vinegar, or Butter and Vinegar, Cinamon, Ginger, Sugar, and Butter: Egges are neceſſary, or at leaſt very good for all boyld Sallets.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Buds of Hoppes.</head>
                        <p>SEethe them with a little of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der ſtalks in faire water, and put them in a diſh ouer coales with Butter, &amp; ſo ſerue them to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Sallet of Mallowes.</head>
                        <p>STrip off the leaues from the tender ſtalkes ſauing the tops: let them lye in water, and ſeethe them tender, and put them in a diſh ouer coales, with Butter and Vinegar: let them ſtand a while: then put in grated bread and Sugar betweene euery lay.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:36146:27"/>
                        <head>A Sallet of Burdock rootes.</head>
                        <p>CVt off the outward rinde, and lay them in water a good houre at the leaſt: when you haue done, ſeeth them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they be tender: then ſet them on coales with Butter and Vinegar; &amp; ſo let them ſtand a pretty while: then put in grated Bread and Sugar betwixt euery lay, and ſerue them in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make blancht Manchet in a Fryingpan.</head>
                        <p>TAke halfe a doſen of Egges, halfe a pinte of ſweet Cream, a penny Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet grated, a Nutmegge grated, two ſpoonefuls of Roſe-water, two ounces of Sugar, worke all ſtiffe like a Pudding: then frye it like a Tanſey in a very little Fryingpan that it may be thicke: frye it brown and turne it out upon a plate. Cut it in quarters, &amp; ſerue it like a Pudding: ſcrape on Sugar.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="puddings">
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:36146:28"/>
                     <head>Puddings.</head>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A fierced Pudding.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ince a Legge of Mutton with ſweet Hearbes: ſearce grated Bread tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough a Collinder, mince Dates, Currans, Raiſins of the Sunne being ſtoned, a little Oren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado cut finely, or a preſerued Lemmon, a little Coriander-ſeedes, Nutmeg, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and pepper: mingle all together with milke and Egges, raw, wrought together like Paſte: wrap the meat in a cawle of Mutton or of Veale, &amp; ſo you may either boyle or bake them. If you bake them, beat the yolk of an Egge with Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſugar, and Cinamon. And when it is almoſt bak't, draw it out, and ſtick it with Cinamon and Roſemary.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:36146:28"/>
                        <head>A pudding of Veale.</head>
                        <p>MInce raw Veal very fine, cut ſome Lard, like Diamonds: mince ſwéet Marjozam, Pennyroyal, Camomill, win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Sauory, Nutmeg, Pepper, Ginger, and Salt made hot, the gut of a fat Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Hog: cut it about an inch long: work it together with ſtore of Cinamon &amp; Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Barberies, ſliced Figs, blancht Almonds, half a pound of Beef ſuet, moſt finely minſt: put this into your ſhort skins: ſet them a boyling in a Pipkin of Claret-wine, with large Mace, a ſliced Lemmon, and Barberies in knots, or Grapes: this is a delicate Pudding.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Fregeſey of Egges.</head>
                        <p>BEat a dozen of Egges with Creame, Sugar, Nutmeg, Mace, Roſe-water, and a Pome water cut ouerth wart in ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: put them into the Frying-pan with ſwéet Butter, &amp; the apples firſt: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they bée almoſt enough, take<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> them vp, and cleanſe your Pan: put in ſwéet Butter, and make it hot: put in halfe the Egges:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36146:29"/>and Cream at one time: ſtir it with a ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, or ſuch a thing. Take it out, &amp; put it in a diſh, put in the reſt of the Egs and Cream like the former, and then put in your apples round about the batter. Then caſt on the other ſide on the top of it, and keep it from burning with ſweet Butter. When it is fryed on both ſides enough, wring on the juyce of an Orange and ſerue it in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Cambridg Pudding.</head>
                        <p>SEarce grated bread thorow a cullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, mince it with Flower, minſt Dates, Currans, Nutmeg, Cinamon and Pepper, minſt Suet, new milk warme, fine Sugar and Egs: take away ſome of their whites, worke all together. Take halfe the Pudding on the one ſide, &amp; the other on the other ſide, and make it round like a loafe. Then take Butter, and put it in the midſt of the Pudding, and the other halfe aloft. Let your liquor boyle, &amp; throw your pudding in, being tyed in a fair cloth: when it is boyled enough, cut it in the middeſt, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:36146:29"/>
                        <head>A Swan or Gooſe Pudding.</head>
                        <p>STirre the blood of a Swan, or Gooſe, ſtéepe fine Oatmeale in Milke, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, Pepper, ſwéet Hearbs, minſt Suet: mingle all together with roſe-water, Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pils minſt fine, Coriander ſéeds, a little quantity thereof. And this is a rule both for grated bread pudding or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pudding that is made in a Swanne or Gooſe necke.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Liveridge or Hogges Pudding.</head>
                        <p>BOile a Hogs Liuer well, let it be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly cold, then grate it like Bread: grate Bread, take new Milke, the fat of a Hogge minſt fine, put it to the bread, and the Liuer, the more the better, diuideit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two parts. Take ſtore of dry hearbes, that are very well dryed, mince them fine, put the hearbs into one part, with Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, Mace, Pepper, Anniſ-ſéeds, Roſe-water, Cream, and Egs, waſh the skins, and then fill them vp, &amp; let them boile e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. To the other ſort put Barberies, ſliced Dates, Currans, new Milke and Egges, worke them as the other.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:36146:30"/>
                        <head>A Chiveridge pudding.</head>
                        <p>LAy the fatteſt-guts of your Hogge in fair water and Salt, to ſcowre them. Take the longeſt and the fatteſt gut, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne at the middeſt of the Gut, and ſtuff it with Nutmeg, Sugar, Ginger, Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and ſliced Dates, boyle it and ſerue it to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Ryce pudding.</head>
                        <p>STéepe it in faire water all night: then boyle it in new milke, and draine out the Milke through a Cullinder: mince Beefe-ſuet handſomely, but not too ſmal, and put it in the Rice, and parboild Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, yolkes of new laid Egges, Nutmeg, Cinamon, Sugar and Barberies: mingle all together: waſh your ſcoured guts, and ſtuffe them with the aforeſaid pulp: par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyle them, and let them coole.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Florentine of Veale.</head>
                        <p>MInce cold Veale fine, take grated Bread, Currans, Dates, Sugar, Nutmeg, Pepper, two or three Egs, and Roſe-water: mingle all well together,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:36146:30"/>and put it on a Chafingdiſh of coales, ſtir them till they be warme, and then put ſome between two ſheets of puft-paſte, and bake it, put the reſt vpon ſlices of a white loafe and frye it in a frying-panne, waſht before with the yolk of an Egge: ſerue it with Cinamon and Ginger, at the ſecond courſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A marrow toaſt.</head>
                        <p>MInce cold parboyld Veale, and ſuet very fine, and ſweet hearbs, each by themſelues, and then mingle them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Sugar, Nutmeg, Cinamon, Roſe-water, grated Bread, the yolkes of two or three new-laid Egges: open the minſt meat, and couer it with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. Then put your toaſt into the Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin with the vppermoſt of ſome ſtrong broth: let it boyle with large Mace, a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got of ſweet hearbes, ſcum them paſſing cleane, &amp; let them boyle almoſt dry. Then take Potato-rootes boyled, or Cheſtnuts, Skirrootes, or Almonds boyled in White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine, &amp; for want of Wine you may take Verjuyce and Sugar.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:36146:31"/>
                        <head>Another in a Frying-pan.</head>
                        <p>TAke the marrow whole out of the bone as néer as you can: ten Oyſters is a fit proportion for that marrow, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parboyled and bearded, and cut in ſmall péeces. Put in a little yong Tyme, Pennyroyall, and parſly minſt fine: work all together like batter. Then rowle your Marrow within that, and ſeaſon it with Pepper, Salt, and Nutmeg. Then make it in little Paſtyes with fine Paſte: ſome like Peaſcods: fry them, ſhaue on Sugar, and ſerue them in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Pudding ſtewed between two Diſhes.</head>
                        <p>TAke the yolkes of thrée Egges, and the white of one, halfe a dozen ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of ſweet Cream, a Nutmeg grated, a few Cloaues and Mace, a quarter of a pound of Beefe ſuet minſt ſmall, a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pound of Currans, temper it like a Pudding with grated Bread, and a ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Roſe-water. Then take a Kell of Veale, cut it in ſquare peeces like Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, lay three ſpoonfuls of the batter vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one ſide, then rowle it vp in the cawle:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36146:31"/>pin on one ſide ouer the other with two ſmall prickes, and tie each end with a thread. You may put two, or three, or foure of them in a diſh, then take halfe a pinte of ſtrong Mutton broth, and halfe a dozen ſpoonfuls of Vinegar, three or four blades of large Mace, and an ounce of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar. Make this broth to boyle vpon a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>findiſh of Coales, and then put in your Pudding: when it boiles, couer it with an other diſh, &amp; let it ſtue a quarter of an houre longer. Turne them for burning, then take vp your Pudding, and lay it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sippets, and poure the broth vpon the top. Garniſh your diſh with the coar of a Lemmon, and Barberies: ſerue them hot, either at dinner or Supper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make French puffes with greene Hearbes.</head>
                        <p>TAke Spinage, Parſly, Endife, a ſprig or two of Sauory: mince them very fine: ſeaſon them with Nutmeg, Ginger, and Sugar. Wet them with Egges, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quantity of the Hearbes, more or leſſe. Then take the Coare of a Lemmon, cut it in round ſlices very thin: put to euery ſlice of your Lemmon one
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36146:32"/>ſpoonfull of this ſtuffe. Then frye it with ſweet Lard in a Frying-pan, as you fry Egs, and ſerue them with ſippits or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, ſprinckle them either with White-wine or Sack, or any other Wine, ſauing Rheniſh wine Serue them either at Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or Supper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Dropt Raiſins.</head>
                        <p>TAke the faireſt Reaſins of the Sun, ſlit them on one ſide: lay them open, as round and as broad as you can. Then take the aforeſaid Hearbes minſt and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, and lay betwixt two Raiſins as many as you can cloſe betwixt them. Take halfe a ſpoonfull of the aforeſaid ſtuffe that you fryed your Lemmons with: fry them brown.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Fond pudding.</head>
                        <p>TAke either Mutton, Veale, or Lamb, roaſt or raw, but raw is better. Mince it fine with Beef-ſuet: take Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, Parſley, Marigold, Endiffe, a ſprig of Tyme, and a ſprigge of Sauory: chop them fine, and ſeaſon them with Nutmeg, Sugar, minſt Dates: take Currans and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36146:32"/>grated Bread, the yolks of three or foure new laid Egges, a ſpoonefull or two of Roſe water, as much vejuyce: work the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp like Birds. Beaſts, Fiſhes, Peares, or what you will. Fry them, or bake them, &amp; ſerue them upon ſippits, with verjuyce or White-wine, Butter, and Sugar: ſerue them either at Dinner or Supper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make puffes on the Engliſh faſhion.</head>
                        <p>TAke new milk Curds, preſſe out the Whay clean, take the yolks of three Egges, and the white of one, fine Wheat-flower, and mingle amongſt your Curds: Seaſon it with Nutmegge, Sugar, and Roſewater, mingle all together. But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a faire white Papet, lay a ſpoonefull at once vpon it: ſet them into a warme Ouen, not ouer hot, when you ſee them riſe as high as a halfe-penny loafe, then take Roſe-water and Butter, and indale them ouer: ſcrape on Sugar, &amp; ſet them in the Ouen againe vntill they be dryed at the tops like Ice. Then take them out, and ſerue them vpon a plate, either at Dinner or Supper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:36146:33"/>
                        <head>To make a Pudding in a Frying-panne.</head>
                        <p>TAke foure Egges, two ſpoonfulls of Roſe-water, Nutmeg grated, Sugar, grated Bread, the quantity of a penney Loafe, a pound of Beefe-ſuet minſt fine: work them as ſtiffe as a Pudding with your hand, &amp; put it in a Frying-pan with ſweet Butter, fry it brown, cut it in quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſerue it hot, either at Dinner or Supper. If it be on a faſting-day leaue out the Suet and Currans, and put in two or three Pomewaters, minſt ſmal, or any other ſoft Apple that hath a good reliſh.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make Apple-puffes.</head>
                        <p>TAke a Pomewater, or any other Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that is not hard, or harſh in taſte: mince it ſmall with a dozen or twenty Raiſins of the Sunne: wet the Apples in two Egges, beat them all together with the backe of a knife or a ſpoone. Seaſon them with Nutmegge, Roſe-water, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and Ginger: drop them into a Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-pan with a ſpoone, fry them like Egs,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36146:33"/>wring on the juyce of an Orange or Lemmon, and ſerue them in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make Kick-ſhawes.</head>
                        <p>TAke the Kidney of a Veal, or Lamb, or if you haue neither of both, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the eare of Mutton, take the fat and all, boyle it, and mince it fine: ſeaſon it with Nutmeg, Pepper, and Salt. Then take two or three Egges, a ſpoonfull of Roſe-water, two or three ſpoonfuls of Sacke, as much grated Bread as will worke them like lithe-paſte. Then flower your moulds, and fil them with that paſte: then roule a thin ſheete of paſte, wet it and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ouer: fry them, and turne them into ſmall diſhes, and keepe them warm in the Ouen, ſerue them at dinner, or ſupper. If you will bake them, then you may turne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the diſh raw, out of your moulds, and Ice them with Roſe-water &amp; Sugar, and ſet them in the Ouen, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your pyes are halfe bak't.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:36146:34"/>
                        <head>To make ſome Kick-ſhawes in paſte, to fry or bake, in what forme you pleaſe.</head>
                        <p>MAke ſome ſhort Puft-paſte, roule it thinne, if you haue any moulds you may work it vpon your moulds, with the pulp of Pippins, ſeaſoned with Cinamon, Ginger, Sugar, and Roſe-water, cloſe them vp, and bake them, or fry them: or you may fill them with Gooſeberries, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with Sugar, Cinamon, Ginger, and Nutmeg: rowle them vp in yolkes of Egges, and it will kéepe your Marrow, being boyled, from melting away, or you may fil them with Curds, boyled vp with whites of Egges and Creame, and it will be a tender Curd: but you muſt ſeaſon the Curde with parboyld Currans, thrée or foure ſliced Dates put into it, or ſixe bits of Marrow, as bigge as half a Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut: put in ſome ſmall peeces of Almond-paſte, Sugar, Roſe-water, and Nutmeg. And this will ſerue for any of theſe Rick-ſhawes, either to bake, or for a Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentine in Puft-paſte: any of theſe you may fry or bake, for Dinner or Supper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:36146:34"/>
                        <head>To make an Italian pudding.</head>
                        <p>TAke a penny whiteloafe, pare off the cruſt, and cut it in ſquare péeces like vnto great Dyce, mince a pound of Béef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuet ſmall: take halfe a pound of Raiſins of the Sunne, ſtone them, and mingle them together, and ſeaſon them with Sugar, Roſe-water &amp; Nutmeg, wet theſe things in foure Egs, and ſtir them very tenderly for breaking the Bread: then put it in a diſh, &amp; prick in thrée or four péeces of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and ſome ſliced Dates: put it into an Ouen hot enough for a Chewet: if your Ouen be too hot, it will burne: if too cold, it will be heauy. When it is baked, ſcrape on Sugar and ſerue it hot at Dinner, but not at Supper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:36146:35"/>
                        <head>To boyle a Racke of Veale on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>CVt it into Steakes, cut a Carret or Turnip in peeces like Diamonds, &amp; put them into a Pipkin with a pinte of White-wine, Parſly bound in a Fagot, a little Roſemary, and large Mace, and a ſtick of Cinamon: pare a Lemmon, or O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range, and take a little groſſe pepper, half a pound of Butter: boyle all together vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they be enough: when you haue done, put in a littie Sugar &amp; Verjuyce, garniſh your diſh as you liſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To fearce a Legge of Lamb on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>TAke the fleſh out of the in-ſide, and leaue the skin whole, mince it fine with ſuet: take grated Bread, minſt O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range pil, ſliced nutmeg, Coriander-ſéeds, Barberies pickt, a little Pepper: worke all together with yolkes of Egs, like a Pudding, and put it in againe. If you want a cawle of Mutton to cloſe it with, then take the yolk of an Egge, and ſmear
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:36146:35"/>it all ouer, &amp; it will hold it faſt. Then put it in a diſh raw, and ſet it vpright, and put a little Butter into the diſh, &amp; ſet the diſh into the Ouen: put to the aforeſaid things, Sugar, Currans, and ſliced Dates, Salt and Verjuyce. When it goeth to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſtrow it with yolks and parſly, either of them minſt by it ſelfe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To haſh Deere; Sheepe, or Calves tongues, on the French faſhion.</head>
                        <p>BOyle, Blanch, and Larde them, ſticke them with Cloues and Roſemary &amp; put them on a Spit, vntill they be halfe roaſted. Then put them into a Pipkin with Claret-wine, Cinamon, Ginger, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, ſliced Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, a few Carrawayſéeds, and large Mace. Boyle all together and ſerue them in with fryed toaſts.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="English_cooking">
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:36146:36"/>
                     <head>Engliſh Cookery.</head>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle a Capon.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake ſtrong broth of marrow bones, or any other ſtrong broth, put the Marrow into a pipkin with ſalt: boil your Capon in the Pipkin, and ſcum it clean, before you be ready to take it off put in your Salt. Take a pinfe of White-wine in a pipkin, for one Capon; if you haue more, you muſt haue more wine: half a pound of Sugar, a quarter of a pound of Dates ſliced, Potatoes boyled and blancht, large Mace, Nutmeg ſliced: if you want Potatoes, take Endiffe, &amp; for want of both boyle Skirrets, and blanch them: boile all together, with a quarter of a pinte of Verjuyce, &amp; the yolks of Egs, ſtrain it and ſtirre it about, and put it to the Capon with ſtrong broth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:36146:36"/>
                        <head>To garniſh your Diſhes.</head>
                        <p>GArniſh your Diſhes round about with fine Sugar: take Orengado dipt among Biskets: take Carawayes. Take a Pomegranat and garniſh the ſide of your diſh with it: take Currans and Prunes, and wrap them in fine Sugar, having beene firſt boyled tender in faire water: Take a Lemmon and ſlice it, and put it on your diſh, and large Mace ſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped or boyled, or preſerued Barberries. Any of theſe are fit to garniſh your Diſh: take your Capon out of the broth, and put it into a diſh with ſippets, &amp; of theſe gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes round about it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle a Capon ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>her way.</head>
                        <p>BOyle a Knuckle of Veale vntill it make ſtrong broth: then take your Capon, &amp; boyle it in faire water and Salt, and when it is almoſt boyld, take it &amp; put it in a Pipkin, and ſtrain your broth in to the Capon: Then waſh and ſcrape Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſley, and Fennell rootes cleane, pith them, and ſlice them along: boil them in a skillet of water, and when they are halfe boyled take them from the fire, and put them
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:36146:37"/>in a ſtrainer and then in a clean Pipkin. Then take a little Roſewater, and a quarter of a pound of fine Sugar, vntil it be as cleare as glaſſe: then take a little large Mace, a faggot of ſwéet Hearbes, a minſt Lemmon, the pill taken off. Boyle a few Raiſins of the Sunne with it, but firſt take out your Capon and ſtraine the broth: put the Capon into a Diſh very finely garniſht: then put the broth to the Capon: then take Parſley rootes, and lay them on the top of the Capon with your minſt and ſliced Lemmon, your Raiſins of the Sunne, and your large Mace. Garniſh your diſh, as before is ſhewed.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle a Capon in Rice.</head>
                        <p>BOyle a Capon in Salt &amp; water, and if you like it, you may put into a ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> cloath, a handfull of Oatmeale: then take a quarter of a pound of Rice, and ſteepe it in faire water, and ſo halfe boyle it then ſtrain the Rice through a Cullinder then boyle the Rice in a Pipkin, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> quart of Milke: put in half an ounce o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> large Mace, half a pound of Sugar: boyle it well but not ouer-thick, put in a little Roſe-water: blanch halfe a pound of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:36146:37"/>and beate them in a morter with a little Creame and Roſe-water: beate them fine, and ſtraine them into a Pipkin by it ſelfe. Then take vp your Capon, and ſet your Almonds a little againſt the fire; garniſh your diſhes as you think fit and ſay in your Capon, and put your Rice handſomely vpon the Capon, and then the broth vpon the Rice.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle a Capon with Oyſters and picked Lemmons.</head>
                        <p>BOyle the Capon halfe enough, with faire water &amp; Salt: then ſtraine ſome of the broth into a quart of Reniſh-wine: then put in a few ſwéet hearbes, minſt with a pickled Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon or Orange, put all into the Pipkin, and let them boyl toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Then take the Oyſters, pick and beard them, and parboyle them: then put them out of the broth into a Cullinder, &amp; then put them into a Pipkin. Then take a few Raiſins of the Sun: if you loue the juyce of an Onyon, firſt boyl ſome Ony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by themſelues, and ſtraine them, and then put them into the Pipkin, and ſerue in with what garniſh you pleaſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:36146:38"/>
                        <head>To boyle a Capon with Pippins.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle it as before, then put two Marrow-bones into a Pipkin, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put the marrow of two or thrée bones into a Pipkin, with a quart of White-Wine, a little ſliced Nutmeg, half a ſcore of Dates. When you haue ſo done, put in a quarter of a pound of Sugar, then pare your Pippins, and cut them into quarters, and put them into a Pipkin, and couer them with a little Roſe-water and Sugar, and boyle them. Then take (if you haue it) ſippets of Bisket, and for want thereof take other Bread: then boyle ſeuen or eight Egges hard, take out the yolkes and put them in a ſtrainer. Then take a little Verjuyce, and ſtrong broth where the Capon is boyling, ſtrain it, and put it in a Pipkin, and ſtirre all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Pippins and Muſcadine: let the Maſcadine bée put on when the Pippins are cold.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:36146:38"/>
                        <head>To boyle Chickens in White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broth.</head>
                        <p>TRuſſe and parboyl them very white: then put them with ſwéet Hearbes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Pipkin with Mace, péeces of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, chop a little Parſley but courſe, and ſtraine the yolkes of foure or fine Egges, with a little verjuyce, which muſt be put in when they are ready to be taken from the fire. Garniſh your diſh.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle Chickens in ſoope.</head>
                        <p>BOyle them vntill they bee enough, boyle Hartichokes very well, and blauch them. Then put your Chickens into a Pipkin with ſtrong broth. Cut your Hartichokes, and put them into a pipkin with a few ſliced Dates: waſh a few Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins of the Sun, and a few Currans clean, put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a pipkin: then take <hi>Cola-Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> and waſh it clean, and parboyle it very well. When you take them from the fire, blaunch them very cleane, &amp; put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a pipkin: then take ſome of your Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichokes left, and a little white Bread,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:36146:39"/>laid in ſtéep with a little broth and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juyce, halfe a dozen yolks of hard Egges, and a little ſtrong broth and Verjuyce, a quarter of a pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Sugar, put it into the Pipkin, and ſtir all together, with a good quantity of Butter: then mince the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Marigolds, and boyl them with the reſt: ſtum the broth clean and then it will looke very cleare: with this boyling you may boyl Capon, Pigeon, Rabbet, Lark, &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle the common way.</head>
                        <p>TRuſſe and parboyle them, and put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a Pipkin with ſtrong broth: then take Parſley, Endiffe, Spinage, a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got of ſwéet Hearbs. Bruiſe your parſley and Endiffe, and put them into a Pipkin and two or thrée ribs of Mutton, &amp; if you haue any Potatoes, or Skirrets, put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in with Marigold Flowers, and let them boyl well together: then ſlice one Carret<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and caſt it in, &amp; ſerue it with a few large Mace, and a little Verjuyce. Take the yolkes of halfe a dozen Egs, mince them by themſelues fine, and the parboyld Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſley by it ſelf; then mingle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a few
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:36146:39"/>Barberries: caſt all theſe things on the toppe of the Chickens, after you haue put them in the Diſh: ſo alſo may you do with a Knuckle of Veale.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle Chickens with Lettice the beſt way.</head>
                        <p>CUt euery Chicken in foure quarters after the parboyling of them, and put them into a Pipkin with two or thrée Swéet-breads of Veale: or if you cannot ſo readily come by ſo many, then take the Vdder of a Veale, &amp; parboyl it very well: Cut it in peeces, and put it into the Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, with a ſliced Lemmon. Then take Lettice, cut them and waſh them cleane; and bruiſe them with the back of a Ladle, and put them into the pipkin: then take a good deale of ſwéet Butter, about the quantity of halfe a pound halfe a pinte of Sack, a quarter of a pinte of white-wine, Mace, a ſliced Date, a Nuimeg: you may put in thrée or foure Dates ſliced, if you haue ſo many. Let all theſe boyle toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ouer the fire with Marigold-flowers and ſwéet Hearbes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:36146:40"/>
                        <head>To boyle a Rabbet.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle your Rabbet well, and cut it in péeces: then take ſtrong broth, and a Fagot of Hearbs, a little Parſley, ſwéet Marjoram, thrée or foure yolkes of Egs, ſtrained with a little white Bread, and put all in a Pipkin with Mace, Cloues, and a little Verjuyce to make them haue a taſte.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle a Rabbet with Grapes or Gooſeberries.</head>
                        <p>TRuſſe your Rabbet whole, and boyl it with ſtrong broth, vntill it be ready: Then take a pinte of White-wine, a good handfull of Spinage chopt in péeces, the yolkes of Egges cut in quarters, &amp; a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle large Mace. Let all boyle together with a Fagot of ſweet Hearbs, &amp; a good peece of Butter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle a Rabbet with Claret-wine.</head>
                        <p>VSe it as before is ſhewed, ſlice Ony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and a Carret, root, a few Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, and a Fagot of Hearbes, minſt Parſley, Barberries pickt, large Mace,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:36146:40"/>Nutmeg, and Ginger: throw them all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pipkin. Boyl it with half a pound of Butter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle a wilde Duck.</head>
                        <p>TRuſſe and parboyle it, and then halfe roaſt it: then carue it, and ſaue the grauy: take ſtore of Onyons. Parſly, ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Ginger and Pepper: put the grauy into the Pipkin with waſht Currans, large Mace, Barberries, a quart of Claret-Wine: let all boyle well together, ſcumme it cleane, put in Butter and Sugar.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle a tame-Duck, or Widgin.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle your Fowl well, take ſtrong Mutton broth, a handfull of Parſley, chop them fine with an Onyon, and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, pickt Endiffe waſht: throw all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pipkin with a Turnip cut in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and parboyld, vntill the rankneſſe bee gone: then put in a little White-wine, or Verjuyce, half a pound of Butter: boyle all together, and ſtirre it, and ſerue it with the Turnip, large Mace, Pepper and a little Sugar.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:36146:41"/>
                        <head>To boyle Pigeons.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle your Pigeons with Parſley in their bellies, and Butter: put them in a Pipkin with ſtrong broth, about a quart thereof, a ribbe of Mutton, large Mace, a little groſſe Pepper, beaten Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, a little Ginger and Sugar, a few Raiſins of the Sunne, a few Currans, Barberries in bunches, halfe a pinte of white-wine, boyle all together with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Bread ſtéeped in broth, to colour it: ſtraine it with ſome of the broth, and put it into the pipkin: let them boyle till they be enough, and ſo ſerue them in. This broth may ſerue to boyle Woodcockes, or Partridges in, with this difference, take ſome of the broth out of the Pigeon, and put in a minſt Onyon. Let all boyle vntil it be enough.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle Pigeons with Capers or Sampyre.</head>
                        <p>PVt them into a Pipkin, with a pinte or more of white-wine, a little ſtrong broth, a ribbe or two of Veale, waſh off the ſaltneſſe of your Capers or Sampyre; blaunch halfe a pound of Almonds, put them in cold water, cut them longwiſe &amp;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:36146:41"/>put them into the Pipkin with Raiſins of the Sunne. Take large Mace, a little ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Ginger, a ſliced Nutmeg; let them all boyle together with a Fagot of Hearbs, Throw into them thrée or foure yolks of Egs whole, and a péece of Butter, then put in the Sampyre or Capers. This boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling will ſerue well for Rabbets.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle Saweeges.</head>
                        <p>PVt them into a quart of Claret wine, large Mace, Barberries, Cinamon, a handfull of ſwéet hearbes. Garniſh this Diſh with Cinamon, Ginger, and fine Sugar.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To boyle Gooſe-Giblets, or Swannes giblets.</head>
                        <p>PIcke and parboyle them cleane, and put to them ſome ſtrong broth, with Onyons, Currans, and Parſley, &amp; let all boyle together with large Mace, and Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; boyle them well with a Faggot of ſwéet Hearbes, and then put in Verjuyce and Butter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:36146:42"/>
                        <head>Giblets with Hearbs and Rootes.</head>
                        <p>PIcke and parboyl them, and put them in a quart of Claret-wine into a Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, halfe an ounce of Sugar, a good quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Barberries, Spinage, and a Fagot of ſweet Hearbs, boyld Turnips, and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets ſliced, and put them into the Pipkin, and boyle them well together: then take ſtrong broth, Verjuyce, and the yolks of two or three newlayd Egs: ſtrain them, and put them into the Pipkin.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To ſmoore a Racke or Ribbes of Mutton.</head>
                        <p>CVt your Mutton in peeces, &amp; ſplit it with the back of a Cliuer, and ſo put it into a diſh, and a peece of ſweet Butter, and put it into the bottome of your diſh: then take a Fagot of ſweet Hearbs, and groſſe Pepper: ſtue them in a couered diſh with a little Salt: turne them now and then, and when they are enough, put them in a cleane Diſh with ſippets. The diſh is beſt garniſhed with Barberries, and Pepper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:36146:42"/>
                        <head>For the fillets of a Veale, ſmoored in a Frying-panne.</head>
                        <p>CVt them as for Oliues; hacke them with the backe of a knife; then cut Lard fine, and lard them, then put them in a Frying-pan with ſtrong Beere, or Ale, and fry them ſomewhat browne; then put them into a pinte of Claret-wine, and boyle them with a little Cinamon, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Ginger.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Diſh of Steakes of Mutton, ſmoored in a Frying-panne.</head>
                        <p>TAke your Legge of Mutton cut into Steakes, &amp; put it into a Frying-pan, with a pinte of White-Wine, ſmoore them ſomewhat browne: then put them into a Pipkin; Cut a Lemmon in ſlices, and throw it in; then take a good quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Butter &amp; hold it ouer the fire; when it is ready to fry put in a handful of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſley, and when it is fryed, put it into the Pipkin and boyle all together. This Diſh would be garniſhed with Cinamon, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and ſliced Lemmons.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:36146:43"/>
                        <head>To ſmoore a Chicken.</head>
                        <p>CVt it in ſmall péeces, and fry it with ſweet Butter; take Sacke, or white-Wine, Parſly, an Onyon chopt ſmall, a peece of whole Mace, and a little groſſe Pepper; put in a little Sugar, Veriuyce, and Butter. Then take a good handfull of Clary, and picke off the ſtalkes, then make fine batter with the yolkes of two or three new-laid Egges, &amp; fine flowre, two or three ſpoonfuls of ſweet Creame and a little Nutmegge, and ſo fry it in a Frying-pan with ſweet Butter; ſerue your Chickens with the fryed Clary on them. Garniſh your diſh with Barberies.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To fry Muſſels, Perywinckles, or Oyſters, to ſerve with a Duck, or ſingle by themſelves.</head>
                        <p>BOyle theſe ſhell Fiſhes; then flowre and fry them; then put them into a Pipkin, with a pinte of Claret-Wine, Cinamon, Sugar, and Pepper. Take your Ducke boyled or roaſted, and put them into two ſeuerall Pipkins, if one be boyled, and the other roaſted, and a little
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:36146:43"/>Sugar, large Mace and fryed toaſts, ſtuck round about it with Butter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To marble Smelts, Soales, Flounders, Plaice, &amp;c.</head>
                        <p>FRy Sallet Oyle in a Frying-pan, or Chafer, wipe your Fiſh, and when the Oyle is hot, put in ſo much Fiſh as the Oyle will couer, and when it waſts you muſt ſupply it. Then fry Bay-leaues, where the Fiſh hath been fryed in whole peeces; put Claret-Wine into an earthen Panne, put the fryed leaues into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Panne, and let ſome of them lie aloft; ſlice an ounce of Nutmeg, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two, as much Ginger, and large Mace, a few cloues &amp; Wine-Vinegar; put your marble Fiſh into the liquor, ſo as the Bay, leaues and ſpices couer it, as well as it that lyeth vnder. And vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſerue it with the Bay-leaues, and the ſpices of the liquor.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To congar Eeles in Colar like Brawne.</head>
                        <p>CVt them open with the skin on, and take the bone clean out, large Mace, groſſe Pepper, ſome fine ſweet Hearbes,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:36146:44"/>chop vnder your Kniſe. Then ſtrow the Hearbes and the Spices all along the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of your Eele, and rowle it like a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Brawne: ſo may you doe with Tenches, boyled in faire water, White Wine, and a quantity of Salt, ſo put in ſome ſliced Ginger, Nutmeg, and Pepper in graine. When it is well boyled put it into an earthen Panne, couered with the owne liquor, and a little White-Wine Vinegar.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To ſowce a Pigge in collars.</head>
                        <p>CHine your Pigge in two parts: take out all the bones, lay it in a Keeler of water all night. The next day ſcrape off all the filth from the backe, and wipe it very dry: then caſt Pepper on it, a little large Mace, and Ginger, with a Bay-leaf or two, euen as you would doe a collar of Brawne, and let your panne boyle before you put it in: keep it with ſcumming vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it be halfe boyled, then take out a Ladlefull or two, and put it in a Pan by it ſelf, put into this boyling ſome Rheniſh or Claret-wine, ſliced Nutmegge-groſſe Pepper, ſliced Ginger. Let it ſtand vntill
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:36146:44"/>it be almoſt cold, and then diſh it with Bay-leaues.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To ſowce a Breaſt of Veal.</head>
                        <p>BOne your breaſt, and lay it in faire water, vntill the blood be gone. Then take it, and dry it, and take all kinde of ſwéet hearbes, Nutmeg beaten, Cinamon beaten, Ginger beaten, but not too fine, Callender, pared Lemmon-pill cut in fine péeces: mingle all together, ſpread your Veale, and caſt it on the inſide, and then rowle it like a collar of Brawne, binde it cloſe. Let your liquor boyl, and put inyour Veale. So you may uſe racks unbound, and Breaſts vnbound. Let it be ſcumm'd very cleane: then put in a Fagot of ſwéet hear bes, and keep it couered, for that will make it white: when it is almoſt boyled, throw in ſliced Nutmeg, large Mace, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Ginger, a Lemmon or two ſliced.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To haſt a ſhoulder of Mutton or a Legge of Lambe.</head>
                        <p>TAke your meat off the Spit, and haſh it into a Pewter Diſh: put inſome Rheniſh-Wine, Raiſins of the Sunne,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:36146:45"/>ſliced Lemmon, raw Oyſters: put them all together into a pipkin, and ſtir them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If you want Oyſters, and Raiſins, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> take two Oyſters whole, put them into the meate. If you want Wine, take ſtrong broth, Verjuyce, &amp; Sugar. Throw a few Barberries into the Diſh, and ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> it on toaſts or ſippets.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Legge of Lambe fearſt with Hearbes.</head>
                        <p>SErue it as before ſhewed, with ſwéet Hearbes, and grated Bread, Biskit ſeedes, a few Coriander-ſeedes, Lemmon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pills minſt fine, Nutmegge ſliced, ſliced Dates, a little groſſe pepper, Capers waſht cleane: put all together wth ſix or ſeuen yolks of new-laid Egges, hard roa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſted, and whole, &amp; put them in your ſtuffe and work them with Sugar, Roſewater and Verjuyce, and the Marrow of a bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> or two, Salt, and pepper, put all together into the Skin: Carrawayes and Oreng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> do are fitteſt garniſh for your Diſh.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:36146:45"/>
                        <head>To ſmoore Calves feet.</head>
                        <p>BOyle and blanch them, and lay them in faire water, and Salt, and when they are cold, cut them in the middeſt, and take out the blackneſſe, and put them in a Diſh with ſweet Butter, Mince parſley, Onyons, and tops of time, Currans, large Mace, pepper, with a little Wine. Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar. Let all ſtue together vntill they be ready: put in a few Barberries, chopt parſley fine, two or three yolks hard, and minſt by themſelues, Roſe-water, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and when you ſerue it, ſtrow it with parſloy and hard Egges.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Another way.</head>
                        <p>BLaunch them as before, put them in a Diſh with faire water and Butter, chop Lettice, and Spinage, with the back of your Knife: and put them in a Diſh: let them boyle with large Mace, ſliced Lemmon, a few Grapes, or a ſtewed Cucumber ſliced. Let all boyle well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with pepper: ſtraine into a Diſh the yolkes of Egges, Verjuyce, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar: ſtraine them together when they go to the Table, This boyling will ſerue for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:36146:46"/>Neates-féet, Shéepes. Trotters, or Hogs féet: ſerue them hot at Supper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To haſt Neates tongues.</head>
                        <p>BOyle them, and blaunch them, and ſlice them in péeces, put them into a Pipkin with Raiſins of the Sunne, large Mace, Dates ſliced, a few blauncht Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, and Claret-wine, boyle all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with halfe a pound of ſwéet Butter, Verjuyce and Sugar. Straine a Ladle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Liquor, with the yolkes of about halfe a dozen Egges.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>The ſame with Cheſtnuts.</head>
                        <p>SErue your fongue, as before: put it in a Pipkin with blauncht Cheſt-nute<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtrong broth, a Fagot of Hearbes, large Mace, waſht Endiffe, a little Pepper, a few Cloues, and whole Cinamon. Boyle all to gether with Butter, ſeaſon them with Salt onely, garniſh your Diſh as youll ſt.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="jellies">
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:36146:46"/>
                     <head>Certaine Gellies.</head>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Chriſtall Gelly.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake a Knuckle of Veale, &amp; a paire or two of Calues<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>féete, take out the fat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the Cleaſe, waſh them in two or thrée warm waters, and let them be al night in an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then pot or panne, in faire water. The next day boyle them very tender in faire Spring-Water, from a gallon to three pintes: then let the liquor ſtand vntil it be cold in a earthen Baſon, pare away the top and bottome, and put to it a little Roſe-water, ſeaſon it with double refined ſugar, then put to it half a dozen ſpoonfuls of Oyle of Cinamon, and as many of Oyl of Ginger, and halfe ſo much Oyle of Nutmeg, a graine of Muske tyed in a little Lawn: when all this is boyled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:36146:47"/>put it into a Siluer or earthen Diſh, and ſo let it ſtand vntill it be throughly cold, and then either ſerue it in ſlices, or otherwiſe if you pleaſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make Gelly of Pippins, of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Amber.</head>
                        <p>TAke eight faire pippins, take out the coares, boyle them in a quart of Spring-water, from a quart vnto a pinte: put in a quarter of a pinte of Roſe-water, a pound of fine Sugar, and boyle it vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, vntill it come to the colour of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: you may know when it is enough by letting a drop fall on a peece of Glaſſe, &amp; if it ſtand it is enough: then let it runne into an earthen or ſiluer Baſon vpon a Chafindiſh of Coales, and while it is warme, fill your Boxes or Printing-moulds with a ſpoone, and let it ſtand, and when it is cold you may turne it out of your mould, and it will be printed on the vpper ſide.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="81" facs="tcp:36146:47"/>
                        <head>To make Gelly of Pippins, as orient red as Rubie.</head>
                        <p>TAke eight faire pippins, take out the coares, boyl them in a quart of ſpring-water, and a pound of fine Sugar, boyle it ſtill couered cloſe vntill it be red, and in all other the operations you muſt doe as in the Amber coloured-Gellies, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring alwaies that your Boxe or moulds bée laid in water before you vſe them thrée or foure houres, and the Gellie will not cleaue unto them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make white Leach of Almonds.</head>
                        <p>TAke halfe a pound of Iordan Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, lay them in cold water, the next day blanch them, and beat them in a ſtone Morter, put in ſome Damaske-roſe-water into the beating of them: and when they be beaten very fine, draw them through a ſtrainer, with a quart of ſwéet-milke, from the Cow: ſet it vpon a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing-diſh of Coales, with a péece of Iſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:36146:48"/>a péece of whole Mace, one Nutmeg quartered, a graine of Muske fyed in a faire cloute and hung upon a threed in it: And when you ſee it grow ſomething thicke, take it off the fire, and take out your whole ſpices, and let it run thorow a ſtrainer, into a broad deep Diſh. And when it is cold, you may ſlice it, &amp; ſo ſerue it in. If you pleaſe you may caſt ſome of it into colours, as Yellow, Greene, Red: your yellow muſt bee Safron, or the bloſſomes of white Roſes: the Green, muſt be the juyce of Greene Wheat: and your Red you muſt make with Turnſoll: thus you may haue Leach of foure ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall colours.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:48"/>
                  <p>THE SECOND BOOKE OF Cookerie.</p>
                  <p>Wherein is ſet forth the neweſt and moſt commendable Faſhion of Dreſſing, Boyling, Sowcing, or Roaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, all manner either Fleſh, Fiſh, or any kind of Fowle.</p>
                  <p>Together with an exact order of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Kickſhawes, or made-diſhes of any faſhion, fit to beautifie either No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemans or Gentlemans table.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All ſet forth according to the now new Engliſh and French faſhion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BY IOHN MVRRELL</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſixth Impreſsion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Iohn Marriot,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Saint Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans Church-yard. 1641.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:49"/>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:36146:49"/>
                  <head>To the Right worſhipfull the Lady <hi>Browne,</hi> Wife to the right Worſhipfull S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Iohn Brown,</hi> Knight, health and happineſſe.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My moſt Honourable Lady:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE laſt Book of this kind which I publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed (the laſt yeare) having under your name found ſo good welcome at their hands into which it chanced, (ſith it mended their fare with their owne food) hath now (for their further wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare in the like manner) called out this Second part, as a ſecond ſervice to ſatisfie their more dainty deſire: In which ſervices, ſuch Novelties as <hi>Time, Art,</hi> and <hi>Diligence</hi> (the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecters of each <hi>Faculty</hi>) doe daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, may be ſeene and practiſed, to
<pb facs="tcp:36146:50"/>give all contentment to the curiouſt palate. And this I take to be no ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full curioſity, but it is rather a ſin to marre good meate with ill handling; and ſo the old proverbe verified; <hi>God ſends Meat, but the Devill Cookes:</hi> what it is, <hi>(Good Madam)</hi> is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with the Author, yours, though he ſhew it others; that ſo the world may be thankfull to you for good meate well dreſt though at their own coſt: And let me loſe my credit with you and the world too, if it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their expectation, ſo as they cooke it by this booke. To the tryall whereof I referre them: recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it and my ſelfe, to your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips wonted favour, reſting in all humble ſervice</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Ladyſhips IOHN MVRRELL.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="2" type="book">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:36146:50"/>
                  <head>THE SECOND Booke of Cookery.</head>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle a Capon larded with Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons on the French faſhion.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake a fat young Capon, and three or foure peeces of a neck or chine of Mutton, &amp; put them together in a pot or Pipkin vntill your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon bee tender: boyle them with as much faire water as will couer them, then take a pinte of the broth out from them, and put it in another Pipkin: put in ſix blades of whole Mace, as many Dates broken in quarters, and eight lumpes of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: then take two Hartichoake bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes, cut them in ſquare peeces or quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:36146:51"/>if you haue no Hartichoakes, then take potatoes, and as much ſugar as will ſwéeten it, boyle them on the fire, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Marrow be boyled, then take the yolkes of fiue or ſire Egs, halfe a pinte of Sacke or Muſcadine, wring in the juyce of two or thrée Lemmons, a little Sugar, a little Amber-gréece, a little Roſewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Salt, ſtrain them thorow a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis ſtrainer, and put them into a pipkin to your Marrow, brew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together with your Ladle, that they curdle not. Garniſh the Diſh with wet Suckets and preſerued Barberries, your Sippets muſt be dyet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread: then take vp your Capon, and take a preſerued Lemmon cut in long ſlices, draw thoſe ſlices thorow the breaſt of the Capon thicke, lay the Capon into your garniſht Diſh, and pour your broth hot on the top of the Capon: Lay on it Sucket and preſerued Barberries, ſcrape on fine Sugar, then ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle Chickens.</head>
                     <p>BOyle your Chickens in a Skillet or green pipkin, with as much faire wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as will couer them, put to two or thrée whole Maces, and put into them a good
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:36146:51"/>péece of Butter, and a little ſalt, according to the quantity of your broth, one handful of pickt Parſley, two or thrée ſprigs of Time and Winter: Sauory ſtript, bruiſe them together, &amp; put them into your pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin to the Chickens, and when the Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens bée almoſt boyled put in a handfull of Gooſeberries or cluſters, of Grapes gréene, or Lemmon payred &amp; cut in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or Barberies off the frée or out of the pickle: take any of theſe fruits, garniſh your diſh fitting for your Chickens, ſerue them in vpon hot ſippets, lay the Liuers &amp; the Gizzards with the fruit on the Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, ſcrape on fine ſugar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>Another way to boyle Chickens, or a Capon in white-broth.</head>
                     <p>TAke and boyle in a pot or pipkin two or thrée ſmall Chickens, take two or three blades of whole Mace, as many quartered Dates, three or foure lumps of Marrow, a little Salt, a little Sugar, the yolkes of two or thrée Egges, a quarter of a pinte of Sacke, ſtraine your Egges, and Sacke thorow a Canuis ſtrainer, and put them into the Chickens, brew it with
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:36146:52"/>your Ladle for curdling: ſlice a Lemmon rinde, but firſt taſte it, that it be not bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if it be, pare it, and garniſh your Diſh with Lemmons and hard Egs quartered then poure the broth vpon ſippets, &amp; lay in the Chickens, ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it hot.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>Another way to boyle Chickens, for one that is ſicke, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke ſleepe.</head>
                     <p>PUt two or three ſmall Chickens into a green Pipkin, with as much faire water as will couer them, ſcumme them and put into them the top or bottome of an vnchipt Manchet, two or three blades of Mace, one handfull of Raiſins of the Sun, the ſtones pickt out, as much ſweet Butter as a walnut, parboyl three or four hard Lettices in Lettice water in a Skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, cut them in quarters, put them to your Chickens, wring in the juyce of a Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, let him drinke the broth, and eat the Lettice with the Chickens: If the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent be bound in the body, put not in the Butter vntill the Chickens be boyled.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:36146:52"/>
                     <head>Another way to boyle them on Sorrell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſops, for him that hath a weake ſtomacke.</head>
                     <p>BOyle them in as much faire water as will couer them, with pickt Parſley and ſwéet Butter ſtopt in their Bellies: put into the broth, Parſley, Winter-ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norie and Tyme pickt and ſtript, a blade or two of Mace; one handfull of gréene Sorrell, ſtampt in a wooden Diſh, or ſtone morter: put halfe your broth into the Sorrell from the Chickens, wring in the juyce thorow a Canuas ſtrainer into a pewter Diſh, put in as much Butter as a walnut, a little Sugar, then ſet it on a chafingdiſh of coales, then take a deep Diſh, ſlice in ſome Manchet, couer the bottome of the diſh with them, poure the other halfe of the broth from your Chick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens vpon the Sippets, and lay the Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens on them, then take your Sorrell ſawce, &amp; pour it on the Chickens, ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle Partridges.</head>
                     <p>PUt two or thrée Partridges into a pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin with as much water as will couer
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:36146:53"/>them, then take thrée or foure blades of Mace, one Nutmeg quartered, fiue or ſix whole Cloues, a péece of ſweet Butter, two or thrée Manchet toaſts toſted brown ſoak them in a little Sacke or Muſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, ſtraine it thorow a Canuas ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with a little of the broth, then put them into the Pipkin, to the Partridges, boyls your Partridges very ſoftly, often turning them vntill your broth bee halfe boyled away, then put in a little Salt and a little ſweet Butter: when your broth is boyled, garniſh your diſh with a ſliced Lemmon, the yolk of an hard Egge minſt ſmall, then lay on ſmall heapes betweene the ſlices of the Lemmon, then lay your Partridges in your garniſht diſh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, and pour your broth hot vpon them, lay vpon the breaſt of your Partridge round ſlices of a Lemmon pared, mince ſmall, and ſtrew on the yolke of a hard Egge: pricke all ouer the breaſt of your partriges fiue or ſix wing-feathers, ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it hot. In like manner you may boyle young Pheſants, or young Turkies, or Peachickens, or Woodcocks, or Quailes, or Larkes, or Sparrowes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:36146:53"/>
                     <head>To boyle a Legge of Mutton on the French faſhion.</head>
                     <p>TAke a faire Legge of Mutton, and a piece of ſuet of the kidney cut in long ſlices as bigge as ones finger, then thruſt your knife into the fleſh of your Legge down as deep as your finger is long, and thruſt into euery hole a ſlice of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Kidney Suet, but take heed that one peece touch not another: boyl your Legge well, but not too much, then put halfe a pinte of the broth into a Skillet or pipkin and put to it three or four blades of whole Mace, halfe a handfull of Currans and Salt, boyle them vntill the broth be halfe boyled away: then take it off the fire, and ſtraight before the broth hath done boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, put in a peece of ſweet Butter, a good handfull of French Capers, and a Lemmon cut in ſquare peeces like Dice, with the rinde on, and a little Sacke, and the yolks of two hard Egges minſt. Lay your Legge of Mutton with the faireſt ſide vpward upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſippets within your gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed diſh: hauing all theſe things in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to put into your aforeſaid broth when it comes boyling off the fire, then
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:36146:54"/>poure it on your Legge of Mutton hot, ſo ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To farce a Legge of Mutton.</head>
                     <p>CVt out all the fleſh at the Butte end, from a faire Legge of Mutton, but take héed you cut not the vttermoſt skin, mince the fleſh ſmal that you haue cut out euen as it were for pies, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mince among your meate foure pound of dubbing ſuet, ſo you may make of it fiue or ſixe ſmall pies, and yet there may be left enough to fill your Legge againe, but before you put it into your Pyes, ſeaſon it with a little white Salt, and a little Sugar, Cloues, Mace, and Nutmegges: thrée or foure ſpoonefuls of Roſe-water, halfe an handfull of Carraway-ſeed, couered with Sugar, two pound of Currans, one of Raiſins of the Sun without their ſtones, ſixe Dates minſt, ſtirre all theſe betwixt your hands and fill your Pies, bake them in a moderate Quen, for they will endure no great heat, and will be baked in an houre; then take the reſt of the meat that is left, and worke it with an Egge, and put it into your Legge of Mutton,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:36146:54"/>where your meate came out. This lets you vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, you muſt leaue out of your Pies as much as will fill your Legge of Mutton, then prick vp your Legge with a pricke at the end where you put your meat in: then ſet it in an Quen in an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then panne or Diſh, or if you pleaſe you may put it on the ſpit and roaſt it: if you doe ſo, then ſet a diſh vnder it and ſaue the grauy, and if you take the thickeſt of the grauy that is in the bottome of the Diſh, put a little White-Wine, and Vinegar, a few Barberries, and the yolke of an hard Egge minſt: if you haue no Barberries, then take Capers; lay your Legge on ſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, and garniſh your Diſh with ſliced Lemmons &amp; Barberries, or Capers, pour your ſawce hot on, and ſcrape on Sugar, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To farce a Legge of Lambe.</head>
                     <p>CVt out all the meate, as before in the Mutton, and mince it with halfe a pound of beefe Suet very ſmall, then the two handfulls of Parſley picked cleane, halfe a handfull of Winter-Sauory and Time picked very clean, and mince them very ſmall: then ſeaſon your aforeſaid
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:36146:55"/>Lambe with halfe the hearbes, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Cloues and Mace, a little Sugar and white Salt, a little Salt will be enough: then put in a handfull of Currans, and worke it vp with an Egge: then put half your meat into your Legg of Lambe, and prick vp the end with a prick, and worke the reſt of your meate into little round cakes, as broad as a ſhilling: put your Leg of Lambe into the pot, with as much Mutton broth as wil couer it, if you haue it not, then take faire water, and put in a little Cloues and Mace, &amp; the other halfe of the Hearbes, and the meat that you did make in little cakes, and let it boyle with often turning it round, vntill it be boyled vnto a pinte: then put in three or foure ſpoonefuls of Vinegar, and then take vp your Legge of Lambe, and put it into a boyld meat Diſh vpon ſippets: and pour your broth and your round peeces of the meat on the top of the Lamb: then ſcrape on fine Sugar, &amp; ſerue it hot to the table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To ſtew Trouts.</head>
                     <p>PVt three or four Trouts in a pewter diſh, and a quarter of a pinte of white-Wine,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:36146:55"/>or of Sacke, with a péece of ſwéet Butter, as bigge as an Egge, a little whole Mace, a handfull of Parſley, a little Sauory and Tyme, mince all together, and put them into the Trouts: if you haue no Wine, take faire water, and one ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Vinegar, and a little Sugar, and let theſe ſtew a quarter of an houre, then mince the yolk of an hard Eg, and ſtrew your Trouts with it, poure the broth and Hearbes all ouer them, ſcrape on fine Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To make a farſt Pudding.</head>
                     <p>MInce Mutton, Veale, or Lambe, with béefe Suet, a handfull of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſley, a little Winter-Sauory and Tyme: ſeaſon your meate with a little Cloues and Mace, Salt and Sugar, worke it vp like birds or little bals, or like Lemmons, put them in a pewter diſh, put to them a little-Mutton or freſh Beefe broth, as much as will couer them, put into the broth a little Mace, Winter-Sauory, Parſley and Tyme, ſhred ſmall together: it muſt bée put in when the broth is halfe ſtewed, and ſo it will make it gréen.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:36146:56"/>Garniſh your diſh with a ſliced Lemmon or Barberries: Lay Sippets about your Diſh, and lay your Birds or Bals on the ſippets, then put a ſpoonefull of Sugar, &amp; two of Vinegar: poure your broth on them, ſcrape on fine Sugar, and ſerue it in to the Table hot.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle a Pike.</head>
                     <p>TVrne a Pike round with his taile to his mouth, couer it with fayre water in a panne or in a kettle, and with it alſo caſt in a good handfull of white Salt, a handfull of Roſemary, Time, ſweet Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joram and Winter-Sauory: when your water boyles put in your Pike, and make it boyle vntill it ſwimme, and then it is boyled enough: then take a little White-Wine and Verjuyce, about the quantity of half a pinte, a few Prunes, a little large Mace Sugar, Currans, ſweet Butter, as much as an Egge: Let all theſe boyle to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vntill your Currans be ſoft: then take vp your Pike and lay it vpon ſippets &amp; if you will you may take off the ſcales, but the beſt is to let them alone: Lay all ouer your Pike parboyld Parſley, and pickled Barberries, then take the yolkes
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:36146:56"/>of two new-layd Egges, ſtraine them with a little White-Wine or Verjuyce, and put them into your broth vpon the Pike, ſcrape on fine Sugar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To farce a Legge of Mutton on the French faſhion.</head>
                     <p>CVt out all the meate of a faire Legge of Mutton, at the butte end, mince it with halfe a pound of Beefe-ſuet, take a handfull of Parſley, ſix ſprigges of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Sauory, and as many of Time, mince all together very ſmall, and put it into your meate: then ſeaſon your meat with Cloues, Mace, Salt, Sugar, and a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Currans: worke vp your meate and Hearbes with a couple of Egges, and put it into the skinne of the Legge of Mutton where you cut it out: prick it vp cloſe with a long pricke, then take the reſt of your meate, and work one halfe of it into little cakes, as broad as a ſhilling, let the other halfe be in little crums like minſt meat: then couer your Legge of Mutton in faire water, in a Pot or Pipkin, and put your round peeces of meat, and all your looſe meat in, then take
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:36146:57"/>ſixe blades of whole Mace, ſix Dates quartered, a handfull of French Capers, halfe a handfull of Currans, and two ſpoonfulls of ſugar, a little beaten Cloaues and Mace, boyle all theſe together ſoftly, ouer a moderate fire, oftentimes turning your Mutton that it burne neither to the pots-ſide nor bottome, and when it is boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the quantity of a pinte and a halfe, then garniſh your Diſh with Capers and a ſliced Lemmon, then mince the yolk of an Egge as ſmall as Dice, you muſt take the Lemmon rinde and all, but if it be bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it will marre the taſte of the meate, therefore pare off the yellow outſide: then lay your Legge of Mutton in Sippets on your Garniſht Diſh, and put into your broth a little Sacke or Muſcadine, or White-Wine: if you haue none of all theſe, then take a little Vinegar and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, the quantity of the fourth part of a pinte, poure your broth on the toppe of your Legge of Mutton, then caſt on it your aforeſaid minſt Lemmon &amp; yolks of Egges, hauing them ready againſt your Mutton be boyled, then ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it in hot: you may lay about it and vpon it garniſhing of puft-paſte, if you
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:36146:57"/>haue it not ready, then a Lemmon will ſerue as well.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle a Carpe or a Breame.</head>
                     <p>COuer your Carpe or Breame with faire water, in a Skillet or pan vpon the fire, put in a handfull of white-Salt, a handfull of Roſemary, Tyme and ſwéete Marjoram, put in a pinte of White-wine Vinegar, or a quart of White-wine or Claret, and make it boyle: then take a faire Carpe or Breame quicke, take out the guts, and waſh your filth cleane, tie it vp cloſe in a cloth, that the ſcales fall not off with boyling: then put it into the boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling liquor, let it boyle vntill it ſwimme, then take a pinte of Claret Wine, and foure races of the whiteſt Ginger ſliced, ſixe blades of whole Mace, a good péece of ſwéet Butter, and a handfull of Sugar, let it boyl vntill it taſte of the ſpices: then take vp your Carpe, or your Bream, and lay it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſippets in a Diſh broad enough for your fiſh, and put into your Wine and ſpices another peece of ſwéet Butter, when it hath done boyling, (for then it will not be ſo oylie,) then powre it on the toppe of your fiſh, then ſtrew on good ſtore
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:36146:58"/>of beaten Ginger vpon the Fiſh, being ſo boyled as is before ſhewed: ſcrape on fine Sugar, and ſerue it hot: but in any wiſe take héed you break not the ſcales of your Fiſh.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle a wild-Ducke, Widgin, or a Teale, on the French faſhion.</head>
                     <p>DReſſe your Fowle, truſſe vp the Legges vpon the backe, put it vpon a Spit, with a quick fire, half roaſt it, and ſet a diſh vnder it to ſaue the grauy, baſte it once with ſwéet Butter, but no oftner: when you thinke it halfe roaſted, take it vp and lay it in the Diſh wherein you ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the grauy, launch it downe the breaſt with your knife, and cut vp the wings broad like a Shoulder of Mutton: then take a handfull of Parſley, fiue or ſixe ſprigges of ſauory, and as much Time, and a handfull of Raiſins of the Sunne without their kernels or ſtones, mince all together ſmall, then put your Ducke or other fowle afore named into a Pipkin, with as much as halfe a pinte of ſtrong Mutton broth, or freſh Béefe broth: put in a quarter of a pinte of Sacke or White-wine, then put in halfe your Hearbes, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:36146:58"/>Raiſins and grauy of your Ducke into the Pipkin vnto your Ducke, put in ſix blades of whole Mace, a little Sugar, a graine or two of Salt, let your Ducke boyle, oft turning it, untill it be halfe boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led away: in the meane while, take the other halfe of the Hearbes, and Raiſins, mingle them with the white of an Egge, and fry them with a little ſuet in a pan, in round Cakes like Figges, frye them thorowly and they will be gréen, but burn them not. Then diſh vp your Duck vpon Sippets, and powre your broth vpon the toppe, &amp; lay on your round Sippets vpon the breaſt of your Duck, ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>Another way to boyle ſmall Carpes or Breames.</head>
                     <p>SCrape your Fiſh, and put it in a skillet or Pipkin, and halfe a Pinte of faire water and as much White-wine, take the milches and refuſe of your Fiſh, waſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cleane, and put them again into your fiſh: then put in fiue or ſixe blades of whole Mace, a handful of Parſley clean pickt, a little Sauory, and as much Time ſtript, a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:36146:59"/>good péece of ſwéet Butter, a little Sugar: put all theſe into your fiſh, and let it boyle vntill it be halfe boyled away, then put in a handfull of Gooſeberries or Grapes in cluſters, or if you haue neither of both, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take Barberries, or a ſliced Lemmon, and ſtraine the yolkes of thrée Egs with a little Vinegar or White-wine, put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your broth to thicken it: then Diſh vp your fiſh with any garniſhing that you haue, and lay in your fiſh, and powre the broth vpon it, ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>Another way to boyle a Legge of Mutton or Lambe.</head>
                     <p>CVt a péece of Kidney ſuet in ſquare peeces of the bigneſſe and length of your finger, &amp; then thruſt your knife in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſix or ſeuen places of the meat, and put your peeces into the holes: boyle your Mutton or Lambe, often turning it, but take heed you ouerboyle it not: then boyle a good handfull of Parſley tender, mince it ſmall with your Knife, then warme a quarter of a pinte of white-Wine Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar with a Chafindiſh of Coales, with a peece of ſweet Butter as bigge as an
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:36146:59"/>Egge, and put in a few cluſters of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, boyled or pickled: then Diſh vp your meat vpon ſippets, poure this ſauce vpon it, and ſerue it hot.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle Eeles.</head>
                     <p>FLey and waſh your Eeles, and cut them in peeces about a handfull long, couer them in a pot or Pipkin with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, put to them a little Pepper, and Mace beaten, and ſixe Onyons in thin ſlices, a little grated bread, three or foure ſpoone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Ale-yeaſt, a good peece of ſweete Butter, a handfull of Parſley, a little-Winter-Sauory, and as much Tyme, ſhred them ſmall, and put them in, and boyle them moderately halfe an houre: as ſoone as they beginne to boyle, put in a handful of Currans well waſht and pickt, and when it is boyled, put in a little Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar or Verjuyce, and another peece of ſweet Butter, and a little Salt; then lay them vpon ſippets, and ſerue them hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle a Rabbet.</head>
                     <p>FLey and waſh your Rabbet, ſlit the hinder legs on both ſides of the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:36146:60"/>turne them forward and truſſe it, pricke them cloſe to the body of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, and ſet the head right vp, with a prick right downe in the neck, then put it into a pot or Skillet, that you may turne it in and couer it with faire water, and make it to boyle: then ſeaſon it with a little whole Mace, ſwéet Butter and Salt, and a few Currans, a handfull of Parſley, a little Winter Sauory and Time, bruiſed with the back of a Ladle: then ſcrape a raw Carret, then take the yolkes of two hard Egges, a toaſt of manchet, ſtraine it with a little Verjuyce thorow a ſtrainer, and put all theſe into it, both to ſeaſon it and to thicken it then let it boyle leiſurely with often turning it, vntill your broth be halfe boyled away: then put in a little ſwéet Butter, a little Sugar, and a little more Verjuyce, and then diſh it vpon ſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, and powre your broth vpon it, ſcrape on Sugar and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle Lamprels.</head>
                     <p>WAſh your Lamprels, but take not out the Guts, cut them in péeces about an inch long, &amp; put into the pot or poſnet twice ſo much water as wil
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:36146:60"/>couer them, ſeaſon it with Pepper and Salt, thicken it with a few Onyons, &amp; a little grated bread, and a little Ale-yeſt, then ſhred a handfull of Parſley, a little winter-Sauory and Tyme ſmall, let all boyle vntill the broth be half boyled away: then put in a good péece of ſwéet butter, &amp; let them boyle a little more, then ſerue it either in diſhes or in porengers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle a Necke, or a Loine, or a Chine of Mutton, or to boyle a Necke, or Legge, a Fillet, or a Knuckle of Veale, or to boyle a Legge, or Loine of Lambe.</head>
                     <p>CVt any of theſe meates in ſo big pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as that two or thrée of them may ſerue in a Diſh, and put them into a Pot, with ſo much water as will couer them: If you haue one necke of Mutton or Veal, then you may take two handfuls of Parſley, and ten ſprigs of Winter-Sauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; as much of Tyme: then put into theſe Hearbs twelue reaſonable great Onyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but if they be ſmall, then take the more, grate in halfe a penny loafe, put into
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:36146:61"/>theſe an ounce of Cloaues and Mace, two or thrée cornes of Pepper, all your ſpices being beaten ſmall, put in the quantity of one ounce of Sugar, and ſixe ſpoone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls of Ale-yeſt, and a little Salt: put all theſe into your meate when it begins to boyle: then let it boyle moderately vntill it be halfe boyled away, often ſtirring it that it burne not, then put in fiue or ſixe ſpéenefulls of Vinegar: then you may Diſh it in as many Diſhes as you ſée fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, according to the occaſions: ſerue it in to the boord hot.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To ſtew Smelts or Flounders.</head>
                     <p>PVt your Smelts or Flounders in a déep diſh, put to them a quarter of a pinte of Vinegar or white-wine, as much Butter as two Egges, put in a little great Pepper, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> handfull of Parſley, ſixe ſprigs of Winter-Sauory and as much of Tyme, ſhred them, &amp; mince them ſmall in the yolkes of two hard Egges: put in all theſe when you put in your fiſh, and let them ſtew, now &amp; then turning them and your fiſh, and when you ſée them ſtewed, diſh them vpon ſippets, and lay on
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:36146:61"/>them bunches of pickled barberries, ſcrape on Sugar, &amp; ſerue them hot to the table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle Pigeons on the French faſhion.</head>
                     <p>TRuſſe your Pigeons ready to be boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, couer them with water, take two or thrée blades of whole Mace, a handfull of French Capers, a few Raiſins of the Sunne, ſhred ſmall three or foure Dates, broken into quarters, a good péece of ſwéet Butter, and a little Sugar, let them boyl halfe away, then put in the yolk of a hard Eg minſt, a little ſweet Butter, three or foure ſpoonfuls of Vinegar, as your taſte ſhall direct you, more or leſſe: garniſh your diſh with ſome of your aforeſaid Egges, and take out ſome of your Capers out of your broth, lay them vpon ſippets, ſcrape on Sugar, &amp; ſerue them hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>Another way to boyle a Pike.</head>
                     <p>TAke out the riuet out of your Pike, and waſh it, and cut it in peeces all of a length, three peeces are enough, then take the middle peece and ſlit it down the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:36146:62"/>back into two péeces, then couer it in the pan or kettle with fair water, and boyl it with a handfull of white Salt and ſweet Hearbs, but put not in your fiſh vntil the water boyl, and then let it ſwimme before you take it vp, for it is not enough til the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: then take it vp, &amp; lay it vpon ſippets with the head and taile, and cut ends both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the middle of the Diſh, then lay your middle péeces on each ſide one, with the ſcales vpward: if it be a ſmal Pike you may take off the ſcales: but if it be a great one, then let them alone, for they keepe your fiſh very white: boyl a good handfull of Parſley tender, and mince it fine, &amp; put it into a Pipkin with a quarter of a pinte of Vinegar, and as much ſweet Butter as an Egge, eight or nine cluſters of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyld Barberies, a little Sugar to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſharpneſſe of your vinegar, poure it vpon your diſh of fiſh hot, but let it not boyle: ſcrape on Sugar, &amp;c. You may gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh this diſh with boyld Parſley, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries, and mince alſo the yolke of an Egge and ſtrew on it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:36146:62"/>
                     <head>To boyle Olives of Veale.</head>
                     <p>CVt a fillet of Veale in thin ſlices, as broad as your hand, and then beate them with the backe of your chopping Knife, then take two handfuls of Parſley, and halfe a handfull of Roſemary and Tyme, picke them and ſhred them ſmall, put to them a handfull of Currans, the yolks of two or three hard Egges minſt, a little Sugar: work all theſe with a raw Egge: ſeaſon your peeces of Veale with Mace, Pepper, Ginger, and Salt: then put your farcing hearbes vpon your thin pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Veale, and rowle them vp as big as an Egge, and prick them with a ſmall pricke, and keepe them cloſe, then couer them in a Pipkin with faire water, with a handfull of French Capers, and a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Currans: and the other half of your hearbs: vnderſtand that you muſt put but half your hearbs to your Oliues: then put in a little Pepper, Mace beaten, a little Sugar: boyl all theſe together, with often turning them that they burn not, and put in a good peece of ſweet Butter, Vinegar, and Sugar: diſh it vpon ſippets and ſerue it to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:36146:63"/>
                     <head>To boyle a Mullet, or a Pike with Oyſters.</head>
                     <p>TAke a faire Mullet or Pike, truſſe it round, and ſet it on a kettle of water, and throw into it a handfull of Salt, and a handfull of ſweet Hearbes, and make your water boyle: then tye your Mullet or Pike in a faire cloth, and put it into your boyling liquour, and put it in a pinte of White-Wine Vinegar, and let your fiſh boyle leiſurely vntill it ſwimme: take the riuet and a pinte of great oyſters, and as much Vinegar as their grauy, thrée or foure blades of Mace, a little groſſe Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: boyle all theſe in a Pipkin by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, vntil your Oyſters be boyled, then ſtraine the yolkes of two or thrée Egges with halfe a pinte of Sacke, or White-wine, put in a little Sugar, and another péece of Butter, then put in your Wine and Egges: then diſh vp your fiſh vpon ſippets and powre your broth vpon it: ſcrape on fine Sugar, and ſerue it hot, &amp;c. With this broth you may ſtew a Capon, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you muſt take roaſted Cheſ-nuts, being roaſted very tender, but not burnt, and ſtéep them in Sacke or Claret-wine,
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:36146:63"/>&amp; put them into your Oyſters: then diſh vp your Capon vpon ſippets, and your broth vpon it: ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it in hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle a tame Ducke.</head>
                     <p>COuer your Ducke with faire water in a Pipkin, put in fiue or ſix blades of Mace, a handful of Raiſins of the Sun, fiue or ſixe ſliced Onyons, a good peece of ſweet Butter: when your Ducke is half boyled, put in thrée or four péeces of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, let them boyle vntill your broth bée half boyled away, then put in a little Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar: garniſh your Diſh with parboyld Onyons, and Raiſins of the Sunne. Lay your Duck vpon ſippets in your garniſht Diſh, and poure your broth and Onyons vpon the toppe of your Duck: ſcrape on Sugar and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle a raſhar of Mutton, or of cold Lambe.</head>
                     <p>SLice cold Mutton or Lamb into thin ſlices, and put it into a pewter or ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Diſh, and put to it halfe a pinte of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:36146:64"/>Claret-Wine, a blade or two of Mace, a Nutmeg ſliced in round ſlices, and a little Sugar, a little Butter: ſtew your Mutton vntill it be thorow hot, and lay your raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vpon ſippets.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>To boyle a Knuckle of Veale, or a necke of Mutton.</head>
                     <p>CVt your Knuckle or neck into péeces, boyle it in a gallon of faire water, put in ſeuen or eight blades of Mace, as many peeces of whole Cinamon &amp; Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs, ten whole Cloues, a pound of Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins of the Sunne, the ſtones pickt out, a pound of Currans, half a pound of French Barley cleane waſht, put in all this after that your meat beginneth to ſeeth, and is ſcummed. If you boyle a knuckle of veale then you were beſt, if you haue it, to boyle a Marrow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bone with it: but if you boyl a necke of Mutton you need not: boyle all this vntill it come to a pottle, then put in Salt by diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as your taſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> all direct you, put in halfe a pinte of Claret-Wine, and if it be not ſweet enough, you may put in Sugar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſippet it, and ſerue it, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:36146:64"/>
                     <head>To ſtew the ribs of a necke of Veale in ſteakes.</head>
                     <p>PVt fiue or ſix ribs of a neck of Veale into a pewter Diſh, pricke into euery rib two or three Cloues, put to it halfe a pinte of Mutton or Beefe broth, foure or fiue blades of whole Mace, half a handfull of Currans, three or foure Dates broke in quarters, a little Saffron tide vp in a cloth, a peece of ſweet Butter as big as an Egge: ſtew theſe halfe away, cloſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, turning them often: then put in a little Verjuyce, and lay your ſteaks vpon ſippets, powre your broth on them, ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue them hot to the table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="baked_meats_and_kickshaws">
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:36146:65"/>
                     <head>Bakte Meates, and Kick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhawes.</head>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make a grand Sallet.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake buds of al kind of good Hearbs and a handfull of French Capers, ſeuen or eight Dates cut in long ſlices, a handful of Raiſins of the Sun, the ſtones be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pickt out, a handfull of Almonds blancht, a handfull of Currans, fiue or ſix figs ſliced, a preſerued Orenge cut in ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: mingle al theſe together with a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Sugar, then take a faire Diſh fit for a ſhoulder of Mutton, ſet a ſtandard of paſte in the midſt of it, put your aforeſaid Sallet about this ſtandard, ſet vpon your Sallet foure half Lemmons, with the flat ends downward, right ouer againſt one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, halfe way betwixt your ſtandard,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:36146:65"/>and the diſhes ſide, pricke in euery one of theſe Lemmons a branch of Roſemary and hang vpon the Roſemary preſerued Cherries, or Cherries freſh from the frée: ſet foure halfe Egges, being roaſted hard, betwéene your Lemmons, the flat ends downward, prick vpon your Egges ſliced Dates and Almonds: then you may lay another garniſh betwéene the brim of the Diſh and the Sallet, of quarters of hard Eggs and round ſlices of Lemmons: then you may garniſh vp the brim of the Diſh with a preſerued Orenge, in long ſlices, &amp; betwixt euery ſlice of orenge, a little heap of French Capers. If you haue not a ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard to ſerue in: then take halfe a Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and a faire branch of Roſemary.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To ſowce a Pigge.</head>
                        <p>CVt off the head of a fair large Pig, and rowle him vp in ſmal collars like Brawne: boyle it in a kettle of faire wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, twice ſo much as will couer him, put in a handfull of ſwéet hearbes, and a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of white Salt, ſeauen or eight blades of whole Mace, two or three Nutmegs cut in quarters, three or foure races of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:36146:66"/>Ginger ſliced, halfe a pinte of white-wine Vinegar or more: let theſe boyle vntill your Pigge be very tender, as you may eaſily know by your owne diſcretion: then take your Pig vp with a ſcummer, and lay it vpon a plate vntill it be cold, then boyle your broth again vntil it come to a Gelly, ſtrain it through a Gelly bag into a diſh, then take your collars of Pig and pare off the top and the bottome, but ridge them as you doe Brawne, and cut off the skinne round about: ſet three of them in a diſh fitting for them, but let not the one peece touch the other, then put your Gelly warm vpon them, euen vntil they be couered, and ſo let them ſtand vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they be cold, this diſh may well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the Table three or foure times: the garniſhing may be thereunto what you thinke fit or what you haue ready.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make Puſpaſte.</head>
                        <p>TAke a quart of floure, a pound and a halfe of ſweet Butter, worke halfe a pound of the Butter into the floure drie, betwixt your hands: then breake into the floure foure Egges, and as much faire water as will wet it, to make it reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:36146:66"/>light paſte, then worke it into a péece of a foot long, ſtrew a little floure on the table, that it hang not to, then take it by the end, and beat it wel about the board vntill it ſtretch long, and then double it, and taking both ends in your hand, beate it again, and doe ſo fiue or ſix times, then worke it vp and rowl it abroad, and then take the other pound of Butter, and cut it in thin ſlices, &amp; ſpred it all ouer the one halfe of your Paſte, with your thumbe, then turne the other halfe ouer your but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered ſide, and turne in the ſides round about vnderneath, then cruſh it downe with a Rolling-pin, and ſo worke it fiue or ſixe times with your Butter, then you may rowle it broad, &amp; cut it in foure quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and if it be not thin enough rowle it thinner in round péeces about the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your little finger: then take a Diſh as broad as your péece of Paſte, &amp; ſtrew on a little floure on the diſh, then lay on one péece of paſte, &amp; you may put into it péeces of Marrow &amp; Hartichoak bottomes or Potato, or Eringus roots: but you muſt rowl your lumpes of Marrow in the yolkes of raw Egs, and ſeaſon them with Cinamon, Sugar, Ginger, &amp; a very little
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:36146:67"/>Salt: lay this vpon your Paſte, then lay your other ſheet vpon that diſh, and cloſe it round about the brim of your diſh with your thumbe: then cut off your round with a Knife cloſe by the brim of the diſh, then you may cut it croſſe the brim of the diſh like virginall keyes, and turne them croſſe ouer one another: then bake them in an Ouen, as hot as for ſmall Pyes. In this manner you may make Florentines of Rice, with yolkes of Egges, boyled with Creame: Boyle the yolkes of ſixe Egges with halfe a pinte of Cream, keep it with very much ſtirring, that it burne not, and it will turne thicke, like Curds, but it will be yeilow: then you may ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it with Sugar, Cinamon, and a little Nutmeg, three or foure ſliced Dates, put into it three or foure peeces of Almond paſte, fiue or ſixe lumps of Marrow, ſtirre them vp together, and put them into the Florentine, then bake it in an Ouen, as hot as for Pies. If you haue Rice, boyle it tender in Milke, and a blade or two of Mace, boyle it vntill the Milke be boyled away, then ſeaſon it with a little Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, Cinamon, and Sugar, two or three raw Egges, a little Salt, a little Roſe-water,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:36146:67"/>a handfull of Currans, three or foure ſliced Dates: you may put this in your diſh, betwixt two ſheets of puft paſt, and bake it as before. If you haue none of theſe, then you may take quarters of Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins, or Peares, the coares taken out, and boyled tender in Claret: Wine, then put them into the Paſte, or for want of theſe, you may take Gooſeberries, Cherries, or Damſons, or Apricockes, without the ſtones, or Prunes: when you ſée your paſt riſe vp white in the Ouen, and begin to turne yellow, then take it forth and waſh it wiſh Roſe, water and Butter, ſcrape on fine ſugar, and ſet it into the Ouen again, about a quarter of an houre: then draw it forth, and ſerue it in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To roaſt a Legge of Mutton, or a Cowes Udder.</head>
                        <p>THruſt your Knife into the Legge of Mutton, at the butte end, the length of your finger, then take a peece of Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ſuet, and cut it in long ſlices &amp; thruſt into euery hole of the Legge one of thoſe peeces: pricke on the outſide whole Cloaues: then roaſt your Legge tender, take a hard Lettice, a handfull of Parſley,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:36146:68"/>and boyle them tender, then beate them with the back of your Chopping-knife a croſſe, vntill they be as ſoft as the pulp of an apple: then take a péece of ſwéet Butter as bigge as an Egge, and a quarter of a pinte of Vinegar, and a ſpoonefull of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Sugar: heat this vpon the fire, and ſerue it in vnto the Table hot, with your meate. Though this be excellent ſawce, yet if you like it not, then you may make a Gallantine thus. Take a little Claret-Wine, and a péece of ſweet Butter, grated bread, a little beaten Cinamon, and Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, a little Sugar, two or thrée cloues, a branch of Roſemary: ſet all theſe on the fire vntill they boyle, and then put it in to the Legge, or Vdder, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make an Olive Pie to be eaten hot.</head>
                        <p>CVt the fleſh of a Legge of Veal into ſlices, as broad as your hand, &amp; beat it a croſſe with the backe of a chopping-Knife: then take two handfuls of Parſly, ſeuen or eight ſprigs of Winter-Sauory, as many of Tyme: ſtrip theſe ſmall, and let there be no ſtalkes in them, then ſhred
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:36146:68"/>them and put vnto them the yolkes of three or foure hard Egges minſt ſmall: ſeaſon your meat with Ginger, Nutmeg, Salt, and Sugar: put to your Hearbes a little Sugar, and a handfull of Currans: lay your hearbes vpon your ſlices of Veale beaten and ſeaſoned: then rowle euery péece into an Oliue of the bigneſſe of an Eg, and lay them into a Coffin fit for your meat, and ſtrew on them the reſt of your hearbes, and a few Currans, thrée or four ſliced Dates, thrée or foure blades of whole Mace, a little Sugar, put in halfe a pound of ſweet Butter, cut in ſlices, cloſe vp the Pie, and bake it in an Ouen, as hot as for Manchet: halfe an houre before you ſerue it to the boord, put in a little white-wine or Vinegar, waſh ouer your Pie with a little Roſe-water and Butter, and ſtrew vpon it hard Sugar and floure bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten together: if any place grow preſently drie, wet it againe with Roſe-water and Butter, and ſet it into the Ouen againe, and within a quarter of an hour it will be criſp like yce: then draw it forth, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="124" facs="tcp:36146:69"/>
                        <head>To roaſt a ſhoulder of Mutton to ſerve for either Dinner or Supper.</head>
                        <p>ROaſt it with a quick fire that the fat may drop away, and when you think it halfe roaſted, ſet a Diſh vnder it, and flaſh it with a Knife a croſſe, as you doe Porke, but you muſt cut it downe to the bone on both the ſides, let al the grauy run into the diſh, baſte it no more after you haue cut it, put vnto the grauy halfe a pinte of White-wine Vinegar, a bandfull of French Capers, a dozen Raiſins of the ſun, the ſtones being pickt out, fiue or ſix Dates broken in quarters, fiue or ſix O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liues ſliced, fiue or ſixe blades of Mace, a handfull of powder Sugar, ſtew all theſe vntill they be half ſtewed away: then diſh your Shoulder, and powre this ſawce on the top of the meate, throw on Salt, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Chicken Pie to be eaten hot.</head>
                        <p>TRuſſe four or fiue Chickens fit to be bakte, ſeaſon them with Nutmegge, Pepper, Salt, and Sugar, put them
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:36146:69"/>into a fit Coffin: then ſeaſon ſeuen or eight lumpes of Marrow, with Nutmeg, Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Salt and Sugar, rowle it in yolkes of hard Egges, it will kéepe them from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing: lay your marrow vpon the Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, and the yolkes of thrée or four hard Egges broken in quarters, fiue or ſixe blades of whole Mace, as many quartered Dates, a little Sugar, halfe a pound of ſwéet Butter: cloſe vp your Pie, and ſet it in an Ouen as hot as for Manchet, and in one houre it will be bakte, draw it forth, and waſh it with Roſewater and Butter, and ſtrew on floure, and Sugar, beaten to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſet it again into the Ouen a quarter of an houre, it will be like yce: then draw it forth, and put in a little Sacke, or Muſcadine, and ſo ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To roaſt a Neates tongue to be eaten hot.</head>
                        <p>BOyle a faire Neates tongue tender, blanch it and lard it on one ſide, prick in ſome Cloues: then cut out the meat at the great end; and mince it with a little dubbing ſuet, as much as an Egge, then ſeaſon it with a little Nutmeg, and Mace,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:36146:70"/>and Sugar, thrée or foure Dates minſt, a handfull of Currans, halfe a preſerued Orenge minſt ſmall, about halfe a graine of Muske: work vp your meat with the yolkes of two raw Egges, and ſtuffe it hard into the Tongue; then pinne ouer the end a péece of a Caule of Veale, or a skinny peece of Beefe ſuet, then put it on a ſmall ſpit, thorow both ends, ſet a Diſh vnder the meat to ſaue the grauy, baſte it with ſweet Butter, and put to the grauy a little Sacke, or Muſcadine and the yolk of an hard Egge minſt, and the coare of a Lemmon minſt: when your Neates Tongue is roaſted take it vp, and put it in a diſh fitting for it, and put a little Sugar into the ſawce, and powre it all ouer the Tongue, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Neates Tongue to be eaten hot.</head>
                        <p>BOyle a fair Neates Tongue tender: ſeaſon it as you read before in the roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted tongue: then lay in the tongue into a Coffin, made of the ſame faſhion. Lay on it fiue or ſix blades of whole Mace, three or foure quartered Dates, a little Orenge cut into ſlices, the coare of a Lemmon
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:36146:70"/>ſliced, half a pound of ſweet Butter, a little Sugar, cloſe vp your Pie, and put it into an Ouen, as hot as for Manchet: if you ſee it colour too faſt, then take down the Ouen lid: but if too ſlow, then lay a few coales in the Ouens mouth, in an houre and halfe it will be bakte: then take a little Sacke or Muſcadine, and the juyce of a Lemmon, half a graine of Muske, a little Sugar, the yolkes of two or three raw Egges, a little ſweete Butter: ſet this on a chafindiſh of coales, and ſtirre it, that the Egges curdle not, vntill the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be melted, then draw it out, and cut it vp, and put in your caudle, ſcrape on Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To roaſt a Pigge with a Pudding in his belly.</head>
                        <p>FLey a fat Pigge, and truſſe his head backward, looking ouer his backe, lay him in a very faire Diſh, for ſoyling: then temper as much ſtuffe for a Pudding, as you think wil fill his belly, you muſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per your pudding with grated bread, half a pound of dubbing ſuet minſt, a handfull of Currans, foure or fiue Dates minſt, Cloaues, Mace, Nutmegs, and Ginger,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:36146:71"/>beaten, of each alike, and a little Sugar, and a very little Salt, you muſt wet your pudding with two Egges, and a little Roſewater and ſwéet Creame, as much as will wet your pudding ſo ſtiffe, as that if you lay it vpon a Trencher, it will not runne abroad: then put it into the belly of the Pigge, and prick vp the belly cloſe, ſpit it, and roaſt it: and when it is almoſt roaſted, wring vpon it the juyce of a Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: and when you are ready to take it vp, take the yolkes of foure or fiue new-laid Egges, a handfull of feathers, waſh the Pigge with the yolkes of Egges, and while you are a waſhing the Pigge, let ſome other body bread it after you, before the Egges be hard: mingle amongſt your bread a little Ginger, Pepper, and Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg: let your ſawce be Vinegar, Butter, and Sugar, and the yolke of a hard Egge minſt: ſo ſerue it in vpon your ſawce hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Pigge to be eaten hot.</head>
                        <p>FLey a ſmall fat Pigge, cut it in quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or in ſmaller péeces, ſeaſon it with Pepper, Ginger, and Salt: lay it into a
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:36146:71"/>fit Coffin, ſtrip and mince ſmal a handfull of Parſley, ſixe ſprigs of Winter-Sauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſtrew it on the Meat in the Pie, and ſtrew vpon that the yolks of thrée or four hard Egges minſt, and lay vpon them fiue or ſixe blades of Mace, a handfull of cluſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Barberries, a handfull of Currans well waſht and pickt, a little Sugar, halfe a pound of ſweet Butter, or more: cloſe your Pye, and ſet it in an Ouen, as hot as for Manchet: and in two houres it will be Bakte: then draw it forth and put in half a pinte of Vinegar, and Sugar, being war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vpon the fire, poure it all ouer the meat, and put on the Pie-lid again: ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Another way to roaſt a Legge of Mutton.</head>
                        <p>LArde a faire large Legge of Mutton, a finger déepe with the kidney ſuet, cut long wiſe like ones finger: prick in ſome Cloues, and roaſt it with a quicke fire: when you think it halfe roaſted, cut off ſome of the vnderſide of the fleſh end, into thinne ſlices: then take halfe a pinte of great Oyſters, and the grauy of them,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:36146:72"/>three or foure blades of whole Mace, a péece of ſwéet Butter, as big as an Egge, a quarter of a pinte of Vinegar, a ſpoonfull of Sugar: put all theſe into your ſlices of Mutton, which you cut off the Legge, and ſtew them together in a Pipkin vntil the liquor be half conſumed: then diſh vp your Mutton being very well roaſted, and pour the ſawce vpon the top of it: ſtrew Salt about it, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a ſteake Pie of the ribs of Mutton, to be eaten hot.</head>
                        <p>CVt a necke of Mutton betwixt euery ribbe, beate euery ribbe with a Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer flatlings, it will make the Mutton to eate ſhort: then ſeaſon it with Pepper and Salt, and put it in a Coffin, lay on thrée or foure blades of whole Mace, halfe a pound of ſweete Butter, cloſe vp your Pie, and ſet it into an Ouen, as hot as for Manchet, in two houres it will be bakte: but in the meane time boyle a good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of good Parſley very tender, beate it as ſoft as the pulp of an Apple, put in a quarter of a pinte of Vinegar, and as
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:36146:72"/>much White-wine or Sack, but White-wine is the better, a little ſweet Butter, two ſpoonefuls of Sugar, put your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſley into this liquour, heate it but warm: then you may cut vp your Pie, and poure this ſawce all ouer the ſteakes: ſhake it well vpon your peele, to make the ſawce and the grauy mingle together: then lay on your lidde againe, ſcrape on fine Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To roaſt a Neck of Mutton.</head>
                        <p>CVt away the ſcragge end of a large neck of Mutton, and put a couple of pricks thorow the beſt end, roaſt it with a quicke fire, but ſcorch it not, baſte it with ſweet Butter, then wring in the juyce of halfe a Lemmon: when it is halfe roaſted, ſaue the grauy in a diſh, being put vnder the meate for the ſame purpoſe, and then baſte it againe with ſweete Butter, and wring in the juyce of the other halfe of the Lemmon: bread it with a little Manchet mingled with beaten Nutmeg &amp; Cloaues, put it into a warme Diſh, and put in the grauy that dropt from it: this is a ſawce both wholeſome, and toothſome.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="132" facs="tcp:36146:73"/>
                        <head>To make a Hartichoake-Pie to be eaten hot.</head>
                        <p>TAke the bottomes of foure well boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Hartichoakes, ſeaſon them with Nutmeg, Pepper, Salt, and Sugar, then lay them in a Coffin, in each corner one: then lay the Marrow of foure or fiue Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-bones (as whole as you can get them) in warme water to take away the red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, dry them, and ſeaſon them with Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Ginger, Sugar, and Salt, rowle them vp in the yolkes of raw Egges, and lay them vpon your Hartichoakes, and here and there the yolk of an hard Egge, ſome whole, ſome in halues, as your eye ſhall aduiſe you, ſtrew on them the reſt of the ſeaſoning: lay vpon them fiue or fixe Dates broken in quarters, fiue or ſixe blades of whole Mace and a little Sugar, put almoſt a pound of ſweet Butter on the top of all: cloſe your Pye, and ſet it into an Ouen as hot as for Manchet, in an houre or little more it will be bakte: if your Ouen be ouer hot, it will diſſolue your Marrow, or dry it vp: draw it forth when it hath ſtood an houre, put in a little Sacke or Muſcadine, wet it with Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:36146:73"/>and Butter, ſtrew on it a little floure and Sugar beaten together, and ſet it into the Ouen againe, in a qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ter of an houre it will be hard, and criſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> like yee: draw it forth &amp; ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To roaſt a Shoulder, or Hanch of Veniſon, or a Chine of Mutton.</head>
                        <p>TAke any of theſe meates, lard them with French larde, and pricke them thicke with Roſe-mary, roaſt them with a quicke fire, but burn them not, baſte them with ſwéet Butter: take halfe a pinte of Claret-wine, a little beaten Cinamon and Ginger, two ſpoone fulls of Sugar, fiue or ſixe whole Cloues, a branch of Roſemary, a little ſwéet Butter, a handfull of grated bread: let all theſe boyle together, vntill it be as thick as Water-grewell, then put in a little Roſe-water and Muske, it will make your Gallentine taſte very pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, put it in a fitting diſh: draw off your meate, and lay it into the diſh, ſtrew it with Salt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="134" facs="tcp:36146:74"/>
                        <head>To make Chewets of Veale.</head>
                        <p>PArboyle two pound of the leane fleſh of a Legge of Veale, ſo, as that it may be eaten: pare off the outſide and mince the meat ſo ſmall as grated bread, then mince ſixe pound of Beefe ſuet, as ſmall as the meat, but you muſt firſt pick out the kernels, and the skinnes, mingle them ſo together, as that you can ſee no meate in the ſuet: then mince a quarter of a pound of Dates ſmall, take a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pound of Biskets and Carra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, two pound of Currans cleane waſht and pickt, and dride in a fair cloath: ſeaſon your meate with a little Cloaues and Mace, Nutmegge, and twice ſo much Cinamon as any of the other, all by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, the fourth part of a pinte of da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maske Roſewater, almoſt half a pound of Sugar, then ſtirre vp your meat, that it be ſeaſoned in all places alike, the leaſt taſte of Salt that may be is enough: then raiſe ſuch Pies as you may put nine or ten of them in a diſh, faſhion them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what long, and raiſe them higher then an ordinary Pie, fill them as full as you can
<pb facs="tcp:36146:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                           <pb facs="tcp:36146:75"/>
                           <pb n="135" facs="tcp:36146:75"/>without disfaſhioning of them, with thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting out the ſides, cloſe them with very thinne liddes, bake them in an Ouen as hot as for other Pies, in halfe an houre they will be bakte: draw them out, and ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue them hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To roaſt a Capon with Oyſters, and Cheſtnuts.</head>
                        <p>BOyle and pill nine or tenne Cheſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts, put them hot into Claret-wine, parboyle as many great Oyſters, ſpit a Capon to be roaſted, put the Cheſtnuts and the Oyſters into the belly of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, and ſtop them in with ſwéet Butter, roaſt it with as hot a fire as you can, but burne it not: baſte it with ſweet Butter, ſo ſoone as it droppes, ſaue the grauie: parboyle twenty Cheſtnuts, and twice ſo many great Oyſters, take halfe a pinte of Claret-wine, and a péece of ſwéet Butter, &amp; a little groſſe Pepper, ſtew the Oyſters and parboyld Cheſtnuts in the Wine, with Butter, vntill it be halfe conſumed: then put the grauie of the Capon into your ſawce, and the ſawce into a faire Diſh: bread vp your Capon,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:36146:76"/>and lay it on the ſawce, ſprinckle Salt, and ſerue it in hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To bake a Quince or a Warden Pie, ſo as the fruit may be red, and the cruſt pale and tender.</head>
                        <p>PAre faire pear Quinces or Wardens, and ſet them into an earthen panne, with the crownes vpward, put to them a little Claret-wine, and a grain of Muske or more, according to the quantity of the fruit, put in a little Sugar, couer them cloſe with a ſhéet of Paſte, ſet them into a Bakers Ouen with wheaten bread, but not houſhold bread, for then they will be burnt and dry: when they haue ſtood thrée or foure houres in the Ouen, they will be very red and tender, then you may kéepe them a wéeke or more for uſe: when you haue occaſion to make your Pie, take Butter, and the yolkes of Egges, and make ſhort Paſte, &amp; raiſe a Coffin fit for your ſtuffe, one by another, put in whole Cloues, and a little whole Cinamon, poure in ſome ſirrup from their former baking, or if you want it, then put in Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret-wine,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:36146:76"/>and more Sugar, ſet them in an ouen as hot as for Pies, and in one hour they will be bakte, and your fruit orient red. Remember before your firſt baking, that you coare your Quinces.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To roaſt a Shoulder or a Fillet of Veale with farcing hearbes.</head>
                        <p>VVAſh your meate, and parboyle it a little, ſtriptwo handfull of Parſley, Winter Sauory a handfull, and ſome Tyme: mince theſe hearbes ſmall, put to them the yolkes of thrée or foure hard Egges minſt, Nutmeg, and Pepper, Currans a good handfull, worke all theſe with the yolke of a raw Egge: make holes as déep as your finger all ouer your meate, fill them with the Hearbes: roaſt it with a quicke fire, let the grauy of the Hearbes droppe on the Hearbes left, baſte your meat with ſwéet Butter: when it is almoſt roaſted, put the hearbs and grauy to a quarter of a pinte of White-wine Vinegar, and a good ſpoone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Sugar, let them boyle vntill you take vp the meate, and when it is in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>it
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:36146:77"/>diſh, powre the fawce all ouer the meate, and ſtrew it with Salt, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To fry Calves feet, or Trotters.</head>
                        <p>SHred a handfull of yong Parſley very ſmall, and beate it betwéene thrée or foure raw Egges, ſeaſon it with a little Nutmeg and Sugar, a corne of Pepper, and a little Salt: boyle your féet tender, and ſlit them in halues, rowle three of theſe halues into the aforeſaid Parſly and Egges: heate your frying panne with ſweet Butter, or ſuet, ſlide youre féet and Egges with the flat ſide downeward, when the Butter is hot: if you haue any Currans, put a handfull into your Egges and Parſley, they wil ask no more frying then an Egge: when the vnder ſide is yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, turne them euery one by it ſelfe, as you doe Egges, Diſh them vpon ſippets, with that ſide outward that you fryd firſt, boyle young Parſly tender, and beate it vntill it be like the pulp of a roaſted Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, put to it a quarter of a pinte of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, two ſpoonefuls of Sugar, a peece of ſwéet Butter, heat them well, and powre
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:36146:77"/>them on the féete, ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Buttred Loaves.</head>
                        <p>SEaſon a pottle of floure with Cloues, Mace, and a little Pepper, mingle it with Milke warme from the Cow, take halfe a pound of ſweete Butter melted, halfe a pinte of Ale-yeſt, two or three raw Egges, temper your floure with theſe things, to the temper of Manchet paſte, then make them vp in little Manchets about the bigneſſe of an Egge, flat them, cut them and pricke them, ſet them on a paper, and bake them like Manchet, let the Ouen-lidde be downe: but if ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be in the Ouen that requireth lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or more heats, then couer them with a paper, in an houre they will be thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoakt: then melt a pound of ſweet Butter, with ſome Roſe-water in it, draw forth your loaues, and pare away the cruſts, ſlit them thorow betwixt the top and the bottome, in two places, and they will be like three round toaſts: put them into the melted Butter, &amp; turn them ouer and ouer in the Butter, then take a warme Diſh, and put in the bottom
<pb facs="tcp:36146:78"/>péeces of the loaues, ſtrew on Sugar of a good thickneſſe, then ſet on the middle pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſerue them likewiſe: laſtly put on the tops, and ſcrape on Sugar on them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: ſo you may ſet on thrée, foure, fiue, ſixe, or more in a diſh. If you be not ready to ſend them in, then ſet them in the Ouens mouth, with a paper ouer them, to kéepe them from drying.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To fry ſheepes tongues, Deeres tongues, or Calves tongues.</head>
                        <p>BReake thrée or foure Egges with Nutmeg, Cinamon, Sugar, and Salt, put to them a handfull of Currans: pill the Tongues, and ſlice them in thinne ſlices, put them into your Egges: and when your Frying pan is hot with Butter, or ſweet lard, cut the coare of a Lemmon in ſquare péeces, like dice, and put it in to your Egges and tongues, but not before you be ready to put the meat into the pan, for then it will make them curdle: then frye them in ſpoonefulls like Egges on both ſides, the leaſt burning takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all the good taſt of al the other things: fry them, and diſh them vpon ſippets, or
<pb facs="tcp:36146:78"/>vpon thinne Manchet toaſts fride with ſwéet Butter. Let your ſawce be Sacke, or White-wine, ſweet Butter, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, heate it hot, and poure it on the top of your Tongues: ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Boyled Sallets.</head>
                        <p>SCrape boyld Carrets, being ready to eate, and they will be like the pulp of a roaſted Apple, ſeaſon them with a little Cinamon, Ginger, and Sugar, put in a handfull of Currans, a little Vinegar, a peece of ſwéet Butter, put them into a Diſh, but firſt put in another péece of but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that they burne not to the bottome: then ſtew your rootes in the Diſh a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an houre: if they beginne to be drie, put in more Butter: if they be too ſweet, put in a little more Vinegar. The ſame way you may make a Sallet of Béetes, Spinnage, or Lettice boyled: beat any of theſe tender, like the pulp of a roaſted Apple, and vſe them as before ſhewed.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="142" facs="tcp:36146:79"/>
                        <head>A bakte Pudding after the Italian faſhion.</head>
                        <p>PAre off the cruſts from a penny white loafe, cut it in ſquare péeces like dice, put to it halfe a pound of dubbing ſuet minſt ſmall, halfe a pound of Raiſins of the Sun, the ſtones taken out, two Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Sugar, fiue or ſixe ſliced Dates, a graine of Muske, fiue or ſixe lumpes of Marrow: ſeaſon theſe with Cloaues, Mace, Nutmeg, and Salt, but a very little Salt is ſufficient, beat a couple of Egges, with foure or fiue ſpoonefuls of Creame, powre it vpon your ſeaſoned bread, and ſtirre it very gently for breaking, ſo as the péeces may be but wet, but not ſo wet that you can ſée any moyſture in them: lay a Pome water in the bottome of the Diſh, or ſome other ſoft Apple pared, and ſliced thinne, put your Pudding alſo vpon the Apple, and ſo ſet the Diſh into an Ouen, as hot as for Manchet, or ſmall Pies, when you ſée it riſe yellow, take downe your Ouen lidde to coole your Ouen, it will be bakte in halfe an houre: if the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be too hot, it will be burnt, if it be too
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:36146:79"/>cold, it will be too heauy: when it is bakte draw it forth, and ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it hot to the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make Puffes.</head>
                        <p>SEt the beſt new Milke together, as a Chéeſe is made with Runnet, and when it is runne, take the Curds, and ſtraine the Whey cleane from them, then ſeaſon your Curds with a little Ginger, Cinamon, Sugar, and Nutmegge, put in a little Roſewater, Muske and one Egge, but the yolkes of two: temper it with as much fine flower as will make it leeth paſte, as leeth as you can worke it, then butter a white Paper, make them into flat balls, about the bigneſſe of a great table man, and ſet them into an Ouen as hot as for Manchet, vpon the buttered pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or rather the Ouen muſt be as hot as for ſmall Pies: a quarter of an houre af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you may take them out, and dipp them in Butter melted with Roſe-water, ſcrape on fine Sugar, and ſet them into the Ouen againe: beware of burning them: when you ſée time, draw them again
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:36146:80"/>and put as many of them in a Diſh as you thinke fit: they will ſhine, and be criſpe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Blancht Manchet, to be made in a Frying-pan.</head>
                        <p>BReake eight or nine Egges, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the whites of foure of them, beat them, with halfe a pinte of ſweet Creame: put to them halfe a penny Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet grated, and put to it two ounces of Sugar beaten, Nutmeg and Mace, a little Roſe-water: fry theſe with ſwéet Butter, euen as you would fry a Tanſey: but let it be a ſmall frying-pan, that it may bée the thicker, beware you burn it not: and when it is fride, waſh it ouer with a little Sack, and the juyce of a Lemmon: ſcrape on Sugar, and ſerue it in hot vpon a plate, euen as a Tanſey.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make Peaſcods, or Dolphins of Marrow, or of a roaſted kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of Veale.</head>
                        <p>SEaſon parboyld Marrow with Sugar, Cinamon, and Ginger, rowle it vp in
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:36146:80"/>the yolke of a raw Egge: then take a péece of ſhort paſte rowled very thin, then floure your Dolphin or Peaſcod mold, &amp; lay your péece of paſte vpon it, then fill the mould vpon the paſte with your Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or roaſt kidney minſt, and ſeaſoned with the aforeſaid ſeaſoning, and faire parboyld Currans, being wrought with the yolke of a raw Egge: when you haue filled your moulds with either of theſe meates vpon the paſte, round about cloſe by the meate, then lay another ſheet of paſte on the meate, and cloſe it downe with your finger to the wet paſte, then pinch off the paſte cloſe by the mould with your Thumbe, and then turne out your Dolphins or Peaſcods vpon a paper, then frye them with a good deale of ſwéet Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, but let your Suet be hot before you put them in, or elſe it will make your Paſte, heauy: when you haue fryde them on the one ſide, turne the other, but frie that ſide laſt that you ſerue vpward vnto the Table: then take them out of that hot Larde, and diſh them vpon a warme Diſh and plate, ſcrape on Sugar, and ſet it againſt the fire, or in a warme Ouen, that you may ſerue them hot, for if you let
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:36146:81"/>them lie ſtill in the Frying-pan, they will drinke vp the ſuet, and be both heauy, and of an ill taſte: take heed alſo in any wiſe that you turne them off, for they will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure no hot fire.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make a Livery Pudding.</head>
                        <p>BOyle a Hogges liuer very drie, when it is cold grate it, and take as much grated Manchet as Liuer, ſift them thorow a courſe Siue or Collinder, and ſeaſon it with Cloaues, Mace, Cinamon, and as much Nutmeg as of all the other, halfe a pound of Sugar, a pound and half of Currans, halfe a pirite of Roſe-water, two pound of Beefe Suet minſt ſmall, eight Egges, put away the whites of foure: temper your Bread and Liuer with theſe Egges, Roſe-water, and as much ſweet Cream as will make it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſtiffe: then cut the ſmall guts of a Hogge about a foot long, fill them about thrée quarters full of the aforeſaid ſtuffe, tie both ends together and boyl them in a kettle of faire water, with a pewter Diſh, vnder them, with the bottome vpward, &amp;
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:36146:81"/>it will kéepe your Puddings from brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: when the water ſeetheth put in your Puddings, let them boyle ſoftly a quarter of an houre, and take them vp: an ſo you may kéep them in a drie trug a weeke or more: when you ſpend them, you muſt broyle them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To make Rice Puddings.</head>
                        <p>BOyle halfe a pound of Rice with three pintes of Milke, a little bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Mace, boyl it vntill your Rice be dry, but neuer ſtirre it, but if you chaunce to ſtirre it, then you muſt ſtirre it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually or elſe it will burne: powre your Rice into a Collinder, or elſe into a ſtrainer, that the moiſture may runne cleane from it: then put to it ſixe Egges, and put away the whites of three, halfe a pound of Sugar, a quarter of a pinte of Roſe-water, a pound of Currans, a pound of Beefe ſuet ſhred ſmall, ſeaſon it with Nutmeg, Cinamon, and a little Salt, ſtirre all this together with a ſpoon thinne, drie the ſmalleſt guts of a Hog in a faire cloth being watered and ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fit for the Puddings, and fill them
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:36146:82"/>thrée quarters full, and tye both ends to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, let them boyle ſoftly a quarter of an hour or ſcarce ſo much, and let the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter boyle before you put them in, and doe as in the other Pudding laſt ſpoken of.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>The end of the Bookes of Cookery.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:82"/>
                  <p>A NEVV BOOKE OF CARVING AND SEVVING.</p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Marriot,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Dunſtans Churchyard in Fleetſtreet. 1641.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="book">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:83"/>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:36146:83"/>
                  <head>Tearmes of a Carver.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Reak that Déere, leach that Brawne, rear that Gooſe, lift that Swan, ſawce that Capon, ſpoil that Hen, fruſh that Chicken, vnbrace that Mallard: vnlace that Cony, diſmember that Herne, diſplay that Crane, disfigure that Peacock, vnjoynt that Bitturne, vntatch that Curlew, allay that Feſant, wing that Partrich, wing that Quaile, mince that Plouer, thie that Pigeon, border that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, thie that Woodcock, thie all manner of ſmall Birds.</p>
                  <p>Timber the Fire, tire that Egge, chine that Salmon, ſtring that Lampry, ſplat that Pike, ſawce that Plaice, ſawce that Tench, ſplay that Breme, ſide that Haddock, tuske that Barbell, culpon that
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:36146:84"/>Troute, finne that Cheuine, tranſen that Eele, tranch that Stugio, vndertranch that Porpas, tame that Crab, barbe that Lobſter.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The office of the Butler and Pantler, Yeoman of the Cellar and Ewry.</head>
                     <p>THou ſhalt be Butler and Pantler all the firſt year, and yée muſt haue thrée pantry Kniues, one Knife to ſquare Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher-loaues, another to be a Chipper, the third ſhall be ſharpe for to make ſmoothe Trenchers: then chip your Soueraignes bread hot, and all other bread let it be a day old, houſhould bread three dayes old, Trencher-bread foure dayes old, then look your Salt be white and drye, the powder made of Iuory two inches broad, &amp; three inches long: and looke that your Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler lidde touch not the Salt: then looke your table cloathes, towells and napkins be faire foulded in a cheſt or hanged vpon a pearch, thou looke your Table-kniues be faire poliſhed, and your ſpoones cleane, then looke you haue two Tarriors, a more and a leſſe, and wine cannels of boxe, made according, and a ſharp gimlet and fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cets:
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:36146:84"/>And when ye ſet a Pipe on broach, doe thus, ſet it foure fingers broad aboue the neather chine vpward a ſtaunt, &amp; then ſhall the lees neuer ariſe. Alſo look ye haue in all ſeaſons Butter, Cheeſe, Apples, Peares, Nuts, Plums, Grapes, Dates, Figs and Raiſins, Compoſt, green Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Chard, and Quince. Serue faſting, Butter, Plums, Damſons, Cherries, &amp; Grapes: After meate Peares, Nuts, Strawberries, Huttleberries and hard Cheeſe: Alſo Blandrels, or Pippins with Carrawaies in Confects: after Supper roaſted Apples and Peares, with blancht powder, &amp; hard Cheeſe: beware of Cow-creame and of Strawberries, Huttleber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Iuncat for Cheeſe will make your Soueraigne ſick, but let him eate hard Cheeſe.</p>
                     <p>Hard Cheeſe hath theſe operations: it will keepe the ſtomach open. Butter is wholeſome firſt and laſt, for it will doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all poyſons: Milke, Creame, and Iuncate they will cloſe the Maw, and ſo doth a poſſet, beware of greene Sallets, and raw fruits, for they will make your Soueraigne ſicke, therefore ſet not much
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:36146:85"/>by ſuch meates as will ſet your teeth on edge, therefore eate an Almond and hard Cheeſe. Alſo of diuers drinkes if their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſitiues haue diſpleaſed your Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, let him eat a raw Apple, and the fumoſitiues will ceaſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Meaſure is a merry meane, and if it be well uſed, Abſtinence is to bee praiſed when God therewith is pleaſed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Alſo take good heed of your wines eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry night with a candle, both redde Wine, and ſweet Wine, and looke they reboyle nor leake not, and waſh the pipe heads euery night with cold water, and looke yee haue a clenching iron, ads, and linnen cloathes if need be, and if they reboyle, ye ſhall know by the hiſſing, therefore keep an emptied Pipe with thelees of coloured Roſe, and draw the reboyled Wine to the lees, and it ſhall helpe it, and if the ſweete Wine pale, draw it into a Romney Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell for leeſing.</p>
                     <p>Alſo looke your compoſt be faire and clean, and your Ale fiue daies old ere men drinke it, then keep your houſe of office clean, and be courteous to anſwer to each perſon, and looke yee giue no perſon no paide drinke, for it will breed the ſcab.</p>
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:36146:85"/>
                     <p>And when yée lay the cloth, wipe the boord cleane with a cloth, then lay a cloth (a couch it is called) take your fellow the one end, and hold you the other end, then draw the cloth ſtraight, the bought on the vtter edge, take the vtter parts and hand it eauen, then take the third cloth and lay the bought on the inner edge, and lay eſtate with the vpper part halfe a foot broad, then couer the Cuphoord and thine Ewry, with the Towel of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, then take thy Towell about thy neck, and lay the one ſide of the Towell vpon thy left arme, and thereon lay your So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes Napkin, and lay on thine arme ſeauen Loaues of Bread, with thrée or foure Trencher Loaues, with the end of the Towel in the left hand, as the manner is, then take thy Salt-celler in thy left hand, and take the end of the Towell in your right hand to beare in Spoones and Kniues, then ſet your Salt on the right ſide where your Soueraigne ſhall ſit, and on the left ſide your Salt, ſet your Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, then lay your Kniues, and ſet your Bread one Loafe by anothers, and your Spoones, and your Napkin faire foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded beſide your Bread, then couer your
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:36146:86"/>bread and trenchers, ſpoones and Kniues, and at euery end of the Table, ſet a Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, with two trencher Loaues, and if yée will wray your Soueraignes Bread ſtately, yée muſt ſquare and proportion your Bread, and ſée that no Loafe bee more then another, and then ſhall yée make your wrapper mannerly: then take a Towell of reines, of two yards and a halfe, and take the Towell by the ends double, and lay it on the Table, then take the end of the bought, a handfull in your hand, wrap it hard, then lay the end ſo wrapped betwéene two Towels, vpon that end ſo wrapped. This being done, lay your bread bottome to bottome, ſixe or ſeauen loaues, then ſée you ſet your Bread mannerly in good forme, and when your Soueraignes Table is thus arrayed, couer all other boords with Salt, Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Cups: alſo ſée thine Ewry be arrayed with Baſons and Ewers, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hot and cold, and ſée ye haue Napkins, Cups, Spoones, and ſée your Pots for Wine and Ale be made cleane, and to the ſurnape make the curteſie with a cloth vnder a faire double napry: then take the Towels end next you, and the vtter end of
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:36146:86"/>the Cloth on the vttter ſide of the Table, and hold theſe thrée ends at once, and fould them at once, that a pleat paſſe not a foot broad, then lay it euen where it ſhould lie: and after meat waſh with that, that is at the right end of the Table, yee muſt guide it out, and the Marſhall muſt conuey it and looke to each cloath, the right ſide be outward, and draw it ſtraight: then muſt yee raiſe the vpper part of the Towell, and lay it without any groaning, and at euery end of the Towell yee muſt conuey halfe a yard that the Sewer may take eſtate reuerently, and let it be, &amp; when your Soueraigne hath waſhed, draw the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nape eauen, then beare the ſurnape to the middeſt of the boord, and take it vp before your Soueraigne, and beare it into the Ewry againe, and when your Soueraigne is ſet, looke your Towell be about your necke, then make your Soueraigne cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, then vncouer your Bread and lay it by the Salt, and lay your Napkin, Knife, and ſpoone afore him, then kneele on your knee till the purpaine paſſe eight Loaues, and looke yee ſet at the ends of the Table foure Loaues at a Meſſe, and ſee that euery perſon haue a Napkin and a Spoone, and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:36146:87"/>waite well to the Sewer how many Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes be couered, and ſo many cups couer yée, then ſerue yée forth the Table man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly, that euery man may ſpeak of your courteſie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Sewing of Fleſh.</head>
                     <p>THe Sewer muſt Sew, and from the boord conuey all manner of pottages, meates and ſawces, and euery day com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with the Cook, and vnderſtand and wit how many Diſhes ſhall be, and ſpeak with the Pantlers and Officers of the Spicerie for fruites that ſhall be eaten faſting. Then goe to the boord of Sew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſée ye haue Officers ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey, and ſeruants for to bear your Diſhes. Alſo if the Marſhall, Squires, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants of Armes be there, then ſerue forth your Soueraigne without blame.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Service.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt ſet yée forth Muſtard &amp; Brawn, Pottage, Béef, Mutton, ſtewed Phea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, Swan, Capon, Pig, Veniſon, Hake,
<pb facs="tcp:36146:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <pb facs="tcp:36146:88"/>
                        <pb n="159" facs="tcp:36146:88"/>Cuſtard, Leach, and Lombard, Fruter, vaunt, with a ſubtilty two pottages blanch manger and gelly. For ſtandard Veniſon, roaſt Kid, Fawne, and Come, Buſtard, Storke, Crane, Peacock with his taile, Herneſew, Bitturne, Woodcock, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trich, Plouer, Rabbets, great Birds, Larks, Doucets, Pampuffe, white Leach, Amber, Gelly, Creame of Almonds, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew, Brew, Snite, Quaile, Sparrow, Martinet, Pearch in Gelly, pety Peruis, Quince bakte, Leach Dewgard, Fruter, Fage, Blandrels or Pippins with Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in Confects, Wafers and Ipocras, they be agreeable. Now this feaſt done, voyd yee that Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Carving of fleſh.</head>
                     <p>THe Caruer muſt know the Caruing, and the faire handling of a Knife, and how he ſhall fetch all manner of Fowle: your Knife muſt be faire, and your hands muſt be cleane, and paſſe not two fingers and a Thumbe vpon your Knife. In the middeſt of your hand ſet the haft ſure, vnlaſſing the mincing with two Fingers and Thumbe, Caruing of Bread, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and voyding of Crums with two Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:36146:89"/>and a Thumbe: looke yee haue the care, ſet neuer on Fiſh, Fleſh, Beaſt nor Fowle, more then two fingers and a Thumbe, then take your loafe in your left hand, and hold your knife ſurely, enbrew not the Table cloth, but wipe vpon your Napkin, then take your Trencher-loaf in your left hand and with the edge of your Table-knife take vp the Trenchers as nigh the point as you may, then lay foure Trenchers to your Soueraigne one by an other, and lay thereon other foure Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, or elſe twaine, then take a Loafe in your left hand and pare the loafe round about, then cut the ouer cruſt to your So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, &amp; cut the neather cruſt and voyd the paring, and touch the Loaf no more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is ſo ſerued, then clenſe the table that the Sewer may ſerue your Soueraigne.</p>
                     <p>Yee muſt alſo know the fumoſities of Fiſh, Fleſh, and Foules, and all manner of Sawces according to their appetites, theſe be the fumoſities: Salt, ſoure, reſtie, fat, fryed, ſinewes, skinnes, hony, croupes, young feathers, heads, pigeons bones, and all manner of legges of beaſts and fowles to the other ſide, for theſe be fumoſities, lay them neuer to your Soueraigne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:36146:89"/>
                     <head>Service.</head>
                     <p>TAke your Knife in your hand and cut Brawne in the Diſh as it lyeth, and lay on your Soueraignes Trencher, and ſee there be Muſtard.</p>
                     <p>Veniſon with furmity is good for your Soueraigne, touch not the Veniſon with your hand, but with your Knife, cut it out into the furmity, doe in the ſame wiſe with Peaſon and Bacon, Beefe, Hen and Mutton: pare the Beefe, cut the Mutton and lay to your Soueraigne: beware of fumoſities, ſalt, ſinew, fat, reſty, and raw. In Sirrup, Pheſant, Partrich, Stocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doue, Chickens, in the left hand take them by the Pinion, and with the forepart of your Knife lift vp your wings, then mince it into the ſirrup, beware of skin, raw and ſinew: Gooſe, Teale, Mallard and Swan, raiſe the Legges, then the wings, lay the body in the midſt or in any other Platter, the wings in the middeſt, and the Legges after, lay the Brawne between the legges and the wings in the platter: Capon or Hen of Greece, lift the Legges, then the wings, and caſt on wine or ale, then mince
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:36146:90"/>the wing and giue your Soueraigne: Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, Partridge, Plouer, or Lapwing, raiſe the wings and after the legges, Wood-cocke, Bitturn, Egrit, Snite, Curlew and Herneſew, vnlace them, breake off the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and breake the neck, then raiſe the legges, and let the féet be on ſtill, then the wings. A Crane, raiſe the wings firſt, and beware of the trump in his breſt, Peacock Storke, Buſtard, and Shouillard, vnlace them as a Crane, and let the féet be on ſtil, Quaile, Sparrow, Larke, Martinet, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, Swallow and Thruſh, the legs firſt, then the wings: Fawne, Kid, and Lamb, lay the Kidney to your Soueraigne, then lift vp the Shoulder, and giue to your So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, a ribbe. Veniſon roaſt, cut it in the Diſh, and lay it to your Soueraigne: a Conny, lay him on the backe, cut away the vents betwéene the hinder legges, breake the carnell bone, then raiſe the ſides, then lay the Conny on the wombe, on each ſide the chine, the two ſides departed from the Chine, then lay the bulke, Chine, and ſides in the Diſh: alſo yee muſt mince foure Leſſes to one morſell of meate, that your Soueraigne may take it in the ſawce. All bakte meates that be hot-open them aboue
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:36146:90"/>the Coffin, and all that be cold open them in the midway. Cuſtard, cheek them inch ſquare, that your Soueraigne may eate Doucets, pare away the ſides and the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, beware of fumoſitiues, Fruter, vaunt, Fruters they ſay be good, better is Fruter Pouch, Apple Fruters be good hot, and all cold touch not. Tanſey, is good hot. Worts of grewell, of Beefe, or of Mutton is good, Gilly, Mortrus, Creame of Almonds, Blanch-Manger, Iuſſell and Charlet, Cabbage and vmbles of a Deere be good, and all other pottage beware of.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Sawces for all manner of Fowles.</head>
                     <p>MVſtard is good with Brawn, Beefe, chine of Bacon &amp; Mutton: Verjuyce good to boyl Chickens, and Capon: Swan with Chaldrons: ribs of beefe, with gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick: Muſtard, Pepper, Verjuyce, Ginger, ſawce of Lambe, Pig &amp; Fawne: Muſtard &amp; Sugar, to Feſant, Partrich and Conny: ſawce Gamlin, to Herneſew, Egript, Plo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and Crane, Brew and Curlew, Salt, Sugar, and water of Camet, Buſtard Shouillard, and Bitturne ſawce, Gamlin, Woodcocke, Lapwing, Larke, Quaile,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:36146:91"/>Martinet, Veniſon, and Snite, with white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalt: Sparrowes and Throſtles, with ſalt and Cinamon: thus with all meates, ſawce ſhall haue the operation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Feaſts and ſervice from Eaſter unto Whitſontide.</head>
                     <p>ON Eaſter day, and ſo forth to Penti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt after, the ſeruing of the Table, there ſhall be ſet Bread, Trenchers and ſpoones after the eſtimation of them that ſhall ſit there, and thus you ſhall ſerue your Soueraigne: lay Trenchers, and if he be of a lower degree or eſtate, lay fiue Trenchers, and if he be of a lower degree, four Trenchers, and of a lower degree, three Trenchers, then cut bread for your Soueraigne, after ye know his conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whether it be cut in the middeſt or pared, or elſe to be cut in ſmall peeces, alſo you muſt vnderſtand how the meat ſhall be ſerued before your Soueraigne, and namely on Eaſter day, after the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and ſeruice of that Country where ye were borne. Firſt on that day yee ſhall ſerue a Calfe ſodden, and ſodden Egges with greene ſawce, and ſet them
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:36146:91"/>before the moſt principall eſtate, and that Lord becauſe of his high eſtate ſhall part them all about him, then ſerue pottage, as Worts, Rootes, or Brewis, with Béefe, Mutton, or Veale, and Capons, to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured with Saffron, and baked meates, and the ſecond courſe. Iuſſell with Mamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and roaſted Endoured, and Pigeons, with Bakte meates, as, Tarts, Chewets, and Flaunes, and other, after the diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Cookes, and at Supper time diuers ſawces of Mutton or Veale in broth, after the ordinance of the Steward, and then Chickens with Bacon, Veale, roaſt Pigeons, or tamed, and Kid roaſt with the head, &amp; the purtenance of Lamb, and Pigs féete with Vinegar and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſley thereon, and Tanſey fryed, and other bakte meates: yée ſhall vnderſtand this manner of Seruice, dureth to Penticoſt, ſaue fiſh dayes.</p>
                     <p>Alſo take héed how yée ſhall array theſe things before your Soueraigne. Firſt yée ſhall ſée there be Gréen ſawce of ſorrell or of Vines, that is, hold a ſawce for the firſt courſe and yée ſhall beginne to raiſe the Capon.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <pb n="166" facs="tcp:36146:92"/>
                     <head>A generall Table of direction for the order of Carving up of Fowle, to direct them which know not, and are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to learne.</head>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Lift that Swan.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He manner of cutting vpoſ a Swan, muſt be to ſlit her right down in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the breaſt, &amp; ſo clean thorow the back, from the neck to the rumpe, ſo part her in two halfes, but you muſt do it clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and handſomely, that you break not, nor tear the meat, then lay two halfes in a fair Charger, with the ſlit ſides downeward, throw ſalt about it, and ſet it again on the Table. Let your ſawce be chaldron for a Swan, and ſerue it in ſawcers.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <pb n="167" facs="tcp:36146:92"/>
                        <head>Reare the Gooſe.</head>
                        <p>YOu muſt breake a Gooſe vp contrary to this faſhion. Take a Gooſe being roaſted, and take off both the Legges faire like a ſhoulder of Lambe, take them quite from the body, then cut off the belly péece round, cloſe to the lower end of the breſt: then lace her downe with your knife cleane thorow the breſt, on each ſide your Thumbs breadth from the bone in the middle of the breaſt. Then take off the Pinion of each ſide, and the fleſh which you firſt laced with your knife, raiſe it vp cleane from the bone, and take it cleane from the carkaſſe with the Pinion. Then cut vp the bone which lyeth before in the breaſt, which you commonly call the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thought, the skin and the fleſh being vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. Then cut from the breaſt bone ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſlice of fleſh cleane thorow, and take it cleane from the bone: then turne your carkaſſe, and cut it aſunder, the backe bone aboue the loyne bones, then take the Rumpe end of the Back-bone, and lay it in a faire Diſh, with the skinnie ſide
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:36146:93"/>upward, lay at the fore-end of it the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-throught, with the skinne-ſide vpward, and before that the apron of the Gooſe: then lay your Pinions on each ſide con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, ſet your legges on each ſide contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry behinde them, that the bone end of the legges may ſtand vp croſſe in the middle of the Diſh, and the wing Pinions may come on the outſide of them. Put vnder the Wing Pinions on each ſide the long ſlices of fleſh which you cut from the breaſt-bone, and let the ends meet vnder the legge-bones, and let the other ends lie cut in the Diſh betwixt the Leg, and the Pinion: then poure in your ſawce into the Diſh vnder your meate, then throw on Salt, and ſet it on the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>To cut up a Turkey or Buſtard.</head>
                        <p>YOu muſt raiſe vp the Leg very faire, and open the joynt with the point of of your Knife, but take not off the Legge: Then lace downe the breaſt with your Knife on both ſides, and open the breaſt Pinion with the Knife, but take not the Pinion off, then raiſe vp the Merry-throught betwixt the breaſt-bone and the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:36146:93"/>toppe of the Merry-thought, then lace downe the fleſh on both ſides of the breaſt-bone, then raiſe vp the fleſh called the brawne, and turne it outward vpon both ſides, but breake it not, nor cut it not off, then cut off the wing Pinion, at the joynt next to the body, and ſticke on each ſide the Pinion, in the place where ye turned out the brawne, but cut off the ſharpe end of the Pinion and take the middle péece, and that will fit juſt in the place.</p>
                        <p>You may cut vp a Capon or Pheaſant the ſame way: but of your Capon cut not off the Pinion, but in the place where you put the Pinion of the Turky, you muſt put the Gizard of your Capon, on each ſide halfe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Diſmember that Herne.</head>
                        <p>YOu muſt take off both the legges, lace it downe to the breaſt with your knife on both ſides, and raiſe vp the fleſh, and take it cleane off with the Pinion. Then you muſt ſtick the head in the breaſt, and ſet the Pinion on the contrary ſide of the carkaſſe: and the legge on the other ſide of the carkaſſe, ſo that the bone ends may
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:36146:94"/>méete croſſe ouer the carkaſſe, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wing croſſe ouer vpon the top of the carkaſſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Vnbrace the Mallard.</head>
                        <p>RAiſe vp the Pinion and the Legge, but take them not off, and raiſe the Merrie-thought from the breaſt, and lace it downe on each ſide of the breaſt with your knife, bending to and fro like waues.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Vnlace that Conny.</head>
                        <p>TUrne the backe downeward, and cut the belly flaps cleane off from the Kidney, but take héed you cut not the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, nor the fleſh. Then put in the point of your Knife betwéene the Kidnies: and looſen the fleſh from the bone on each ſide of the bone, then turne vp the back of the Rabbet, and cut it croſſe betwéene the wings, then lace it downe cloſe by the bone, with your Knife on both ſides, then open the fleſh of the Rabbet, from the bone with the point of your Knife againſt the Kidnie: and pull the Legge open ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with your hand, but plucke it not off
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:36146:94"/>then thruſt in your Knife betwixt the ribs and the Kidney, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lit it out, then lay the legges cloſe together.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>Of the Carving of all manner of Fowles.</head>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Sawce that Capon.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake vp a Capon, and lift vp the right legge and right wing, and ſo array forth, and lay him in the platter as he ſhould flie, and ſerue your Soueraigne, and know well that Capons, or Chickens be arraied after one ſawce, the Chickens ſhall be ſawced with gréene ſawce or Verjuyce.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Allay that Feſant.</head>
                        <p>Take a Feſant, raiſe his legges and his wings, as it were a Hen, and no ſawce but only Salt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Wing that Partridge.</head>
                        <p>Take a partrich, and raiſe his legs and his wings as a Henne, if yée mince him, ſawce him with Wine, Powder of Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:36146:95"/>and ſalt, then ſet him vpon a Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh of coales to warme, and ſerue it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Wing that Quaile.</head>
                        <p>Take a Quaile and raiſe his legges and his wings as a Hen, and no ſawce but Salt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Diſplay that Crane.</head>
                        <p>Take a Crane and vnfold his legges, and cut of his wings by the joynts, then take vp his wings and his legges, and ſawce them with powder of Ginger, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, Vinegar and Salt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Diſmember that Heron.</head>
                        <p>Take a Heron and raiſe his legges and his wings as a crane, and ſawce him with Vinegar, Muſtard, Powder of Ginger and Salt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Vnjoynt that Bitturne.</head>
                        <p>Take a Bitturne and raiſe his legges and his wings as a Heron, and no ſawce but Salt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Breake that Egript.</head>
                        <p>Take an Egript and raiſe his legges and his wings as a Heron, and no ſawce but Salt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Vntach that Curlew.</head>
                        <p>Take a Curlew and raiſe his legges
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:36146:95"/>and his wings as a Henne, and no ſawce but Salt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Vntach that Brew.</head>
                        <p>Take a Brew and raiſehis legges and his wings in the ſame manner, and no ſawce but onely Salt, and ſerue it to your Soueraigne.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Vnlace that Conny.</head>
                        <p>Take a Conny and lay him on the back, and cut away the vents, then raiſe the wings and the ſides, and lay bulke, chine, and ſides together: Sawce, Vinegar and Powder of Ginger.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Breake that Sarcell.</head>
                        <p>Take a Sarcell or Teale, and raiſe his wings and his legges, and no ſawce but onely Salt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Mince that Plover.</head>
                        <p>Take a Plouer and raiſe his legges and wings as a Hen, and no ſawce but onely Salt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>A Snite.</head>
                        <p>Take a Snite and raiſe his wings, his legs and his ſhoulders, as a Plouer, and no ſawce but Salt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Thie that Woodcock.</head>
                        <p>Take a Woodcock and raiſe his legges as a Hen, this done dight him the braine.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <pb n="174" facs="tcp:36146:96"/>
                     <head>From the Feaſt of Whitſontide unto Midſummer.</head>
                     <p>IN the ſecond Courſe for the meates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd yee ſhall take for your ſawees, Ale, Wine, Vinegar, and powders after meate, but Ginger and canell from Penti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt to the Feaſt of S. Iohn Baptiſt.</p>
                     <p>The firſt courſe ſhall be Béefe and Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton with ſodden Capons, or roaſted, and if Capon be ſodden, array him in the manner aforeſaid, &amp; when he is roaſted, thou muſt caſt on Salt, with Wine or with Ale, then take the Capon by the legges, and caſt on the ſawce, and breake him out, and lay him in a Diſh as he ſhould flie, firſt yée ſhall cut the right legge and the right ſhoulder, and betwéene the foure members lay the brawne of the Capon with the croupe in the end betweene the legs, as it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for to be joyned together, and other bakte meates after. And in the ſecond courſe, pottage ſhall be Iuſſell Charlet or Mertrus, with yong Geeſe, Veale, Porke, Piaeons, or Chickens roaſted with Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puffe, Fritters, and other bakte meates after the ordinance of the Tooke. Alſo
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:36146:96"/>the Gooſe ought to be cut member to mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, beginning at the right legge, and ſo forth vnder the right wing, and not vpon the ioynt aboue, and it ought to be eaten with gréene Garlike, or with Sorrell, or tender Vines or Verjuyce in Summer ſeaſon after the pleaſure of your Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne: alſo yée ſhall vnderſtand that all manner of Fowles that haue whole féet, ſhould be raiſed vnder the wing and not aboue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>From the Feaſt of Saint John the Baptiſt unto Michaelmas.</head>
                     <p>IN the firſt courſe: Pottage, Worts, Gruell and Furmenty, with Veniſon, and Mortrus, and peſtles of Porke, with green ſawce, roaſted Capon, ſwan with Chawdron. In the ſecond courſe, pottage after the ordinance of the Cookes, with ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted Mutton, Veal, Pork, Chickens or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doured Pigeons, Herneſewes, Fritters or bakte meates, and take heed of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, he ſhall be arrayed in the manner of a Capon, but it ſhall be done drye without any moyſture, and he ſhall be eaten with ſalt, and powder of Ginger, and the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:36146:97"/>Herneſew ſhall be arrayed in the ſame manner without any moyſture, and hee ſhould be eaten with Salt, and Powder, alſo ye ſhall vnderſtand that all manner of Fowles hauing open clawes, as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, ſhall be tired and arrayed, as a Capon and ſuch other.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>From the Feaſt of Saint Michaell unto the Feaſt of Chriſtmas.</head>
                     <p>IN the firſt courſe pottage, Beefe, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Bacon, peſtles of Porke, or with Gooſe, Capon, Mallard, Swan or Feſant, as it is before ſaid, with Tarts or Bakte-meates, or Chines of Porke. In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond courſe, Pottage, Mortrus or Conies or Sew: then roaſt fleſh, Mutton, Porke, Veale, Pullets, Chickens, Pigeons, Teales, Wigions, Mallards, Partrich, Woodcocke, Plouer, Bitturne, Curlew, Herneſew, Veniſon roaſt, great Birds, Suite, Feldfares, Thruſhes, Fritters, Chewits, Beefe with ſawce, Geloper, roaſt, with ſawce pogill, and other baked meates as is aforeſaid, and if yee carue before your Lordor your Lady any ſodden fleſh, carue away the skinne aboue, then Carue reaſonably of the fleſh for your
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:36146:97"/>Lord and Lady, and ſpecially for Ladies, for they will ſoone be angry, for their thoughts be ſoone changed, &amp; ſome Lords will be ſoone pleaſed, and ſome not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as they bée of complexion. The Gooſe and ſwan may be cut as yee doe other Fowles that haue whole féete, or elſe as your Lord or your Lady will haue it.</p>
                     <p>Alſo a ſwan with a Chadron, Capon, or Feſant, ought to be arrayed, as it is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, but the skin muſt be had away, and when they haue beene carued before your Lord or your Lady, for generally the skin of all manner whole footed Fowles, that haue their liuing on the water, their skins be wholeſome and cleane, for by cleanneſſe of water and fiſh is their liuing, and if they eate any ſtinking thing, it is made ſo clean with the water that all the corruption is clean gone away from it.</p>
                     <p>And the skinne of a Capon, Henne, or Chicken be not ſo cleane, for they eate ſoule things in the ſtreets, and therefore the skinnes be not ſo wholeſome, for it is not their kinde to enter into the Riuer to make their meat boyd of the filth. Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lard, Gooſe, or Swan, they eate vpon the land foule meate, but auon after the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:36146:98"/>kinde they goe to the riuer, and there they clenſe them of their foule ſtinke. A Feſant as it is aforeſaid, but the skin is not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, then take the heads of all field birds, &amp; wood birds, as Feſant, Peacock, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trich, Woodcock, Curlew, for they eate in their degrée foule things, as wormes, toades, and other ſuch.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>The ſecond Part of the Sewing of Fiſh.</head>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>The firſt courſe.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O goe to the Sewing of fiſh muſcalade, Menewes in Sew, of Porpos or of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, bakte Herring with Sugar, Gréene fiſh Pike, Lamprey, Salens, Porpos, roaſted, bakte Gurnard, and Lamprey bakte.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>The ſecond courſe.</head>
                        <p>Gelly white and red, Dates, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, Conger, Salmon, Dorey, Brit, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>but, Halibut for ſtandard, Baſe, Trout,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:36146:98"/>Mullet, Cheuin, Sole, Eeles and Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prey roaſt, Tench in Gelly.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>The third courſe.</head>
                        <p>Freſh Sturgion, Breame, Pearch in Gelly, a Ioule of Salmon, Sturgion, Welkes, Apples, and Peares, roaſted with Sugar Candy. Figs of Malike and Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins, Dates capt with minced Ginger, Waters and Ipocras they be agreeable, this Feaſt being done, voyd ye the Table.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Of the Carving of Fiſh.</head>
                        <p>THe Caruer of Fiſh, muſt ſée to peaſon and furmenty, the tayle and the liuer, ye muſt looke if there be a ſalt Porpos or Sole, Turrentine, and do after the form of Veniſon, baked Herring, and lay it whole vpon your Soueraignes Trencher, white Herring in a Diſh, open it by the backe, picke out the bones and the row, and ſee there be Muſtard. Of ſalt-fiſh, gréene-fiſh, ſalt ſalmon, and Conger, pare away the skinne: Salt-fiſh, Stockfiſh, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Mackrell, and Hake with Butter, take away the bones and the skinnes: a Pike, lay the wombe vpon his Trencher, with Pike ſawce enough, a ſalt Lamprey,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:36146:99"/>gobon it in ſeuen or eight péeces, and lay it to your Soueraigne: a playce, put out the Water, then croſſe him with your knife, caſt on Salt, Wine, or Ale. Gur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, Rochet, Breme, Cheuin, Baſe, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, Roch, Pearch, Sole, Mackrell, Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Hadocke, and Codling, raiſe them by the backe, and picke out the bones and clenſe the refet in the belly: Cary, Bream Sole and Trout, back and belly together: Salmon, Conger, Sturgion, Turbuthir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol, Thornback. Houndfiſh, and Halibut, cut them in the Diſhes, the Porpos about, Tench, in his ſawce, cut two Eeles and Lampreys roaſt, pull off the skin, pick out the bones, put thereto Vinegar and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: a Crab, break him aſunder in a diſh, and make the ſhell cleane, and put in the ſtuffe againe, temper it with Vinegar and powder them, couer it with bread, and fend it into the kitchen to heat, then ſet it to your Soueraigne, and lay them in a Diſh: a Creuis, dight him thus, part him aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſlit the belly, and take out the fiſh, pare away the red skin and mince it thin, put Vinegar in the Diſh, and ſet it on the Table without heating: a Ioule of ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, cut it in thinne morſels, and lay
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:36146:99"/>it round about the Diſh.</p>
                        <p>Freſh Lamprey bakte, open the paſtie, then take white bread, and cut it thinne, and lay it in a Diſh, and with a ſpoone take out Galentine, and lay it vpon the bread with Red Wine and powder of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, then cut a Gobon of the Lamprey, and mince the Gobon thinne, and lay it in the Galentine, then ſet it vpon the fire to heate. Freſh herring with ſalt and wine, Shrimps well picked, Flounder, Gud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, Menewes, and Muſſels, Eeles, and Lampreyes: Spr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ts is good in ſew, Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culade in woorts, Oyſters in ſew, Oyſters in grauy, Menewes in porpas, Salmon in foele Belly white and red, Creame of Almonds, Dates in Confects, Peares and Quinces in ſirrup, with parſley rootes. Mortus of Houndfiſh raiſe ſtanding.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>Of the ſawces of all Fiſh.</head>
                        <p>MUſtard is good for ſalt Herring, ſalt fiſh, ſalt Conger, ſalmon, ſparling, ſalt Eele, and Ling: Vinegar is good with ſalt porpos, Turrentine, Salt Sturgion, Salt Thrilpole, and ſalt whale, Lamprey with Galentine, Verjuyce: to roach, Dace
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:36146:100"/>Breme, Molet, Dace, Flounders, Salt Crab and Cheuine with Powder of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: to Thornbacke, Herring, Houndfiſh, Haddock, Whiting, and Cod, Vinegar, Powder of Cinamon and Ginger, green ſawce is good with Green-fiſh and Hali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>but, Cottell and freſh Turbut: put not your greene ſawce away, for it is good with Muſtard.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="directions">
                        <head>The Chamberlaines Office.</head>
                        <p>THe Chamberlaine muſt be diligent &amp; cleanely in his office, with his head combed, and ſee to his Soueraign, that he be not negligent of himſelfe, and ſee that he haue a cleane ſhirt, breech, peticote and doublet, then bruſh his hoſen within and without, and ſee his ſhoone and his ſlippers be clean, and at morne when your Soueraigne will ariſe, warme his ſhirt by the fire, and ſee ye haue a foot ſheet made in this manner. Firſt ſet a chaire by the fire with a cuſhion, another vnder his féet, then ſpred a ſhirt vnder a chair &amp; ſee there be ready a Kerchife, and a Combe, then warme his petticoat, his Doublet and his ſtomacher, and then put on his doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let and his ſtomacher, and then put on
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:36146:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>his hoſen and ſhoone, or flippers, then ſtrike vp his hoſen mannerly, and tie them vp, then button his Doublet hole by hole, &amp; lay a cloath vpon his necke and head, then looke ye haue a Baſon and Ewer with warm water, &amp; a towel to waſh his hands, then knéele vpon your knee, aske your Soueraigne what robe he will weare, and bring him ſuch as he commandeth, and put it vpon him, and take your leaue manner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and goe to the Church or Chappell to your Soueraignes cloſet, and ſee there be Carpets, and Cuſhions, and lay down his Bookes of Prayers, then draw the Curtaines, and take your leaue goodly, and goe to your Soueraignes Chamber, and caſt all the cloathes off the bed, and beate the Feather-bed, and the Bolſter, but looke ye waſte no Feathers, then the blankets, and ſee the ſheetes be faire and ſweete, or elſe looke yee haue clean ſheetes, then lay the head ſheetes and the pillowes, then take vp the Towell and the Baſon, and lay Carpets about the bed or in Windowes and Cuphoord layde with cuſhions: alſo looke there be a good fire burning bright, and ſee it the houſe of eaſement be ſwéet and cleane, and
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:36146:101" rendition="simple:additions"/>therpriuy boord couered with gréene cloth and a Cuſhion, then ſee there be blanket doune, or Cotton for your Soucraigne, and looke yee haue a Baſon and Ewer with water, and Towell for your Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, then take off his gowne, and bring him a manttle to keep him from cold, then bring him to the fire and take off his ſhoon and his Hoſen, then take a faire Kerchiefe of reines and combe his head, and put on his Rerchiefe and his Bonet: then ſpread downe his bed, lay the head ſhéete and the Pillowes, and when your Soueraigne is in bed, draw the Curtaines, and ſee there be morter or ware of perchours rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, then driue out dogge or Cat, and looke there be Baſons and Vrinall ſet néer your Soueraigne, then take your leaue maner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that your Soueraigne may take his reſt merrily.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the knowledge which is required of the Marſhall and the Vſher.</head>
                     <p>THe Marſhall and the Vſher muſt know all the Eſtates of the Land, and the high Eſtates of a King with the blood Royall.</p>
                     <pb n="185" facs="tcp:36146:101"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>The Eſtate of a King.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of a Kings ſonne, a Prince.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of a Duke.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of a Marqueſſe.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of an Earle.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of a Biſhop.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of a Vicount.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of a Baron.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of the thrée chiefe Iudges and the Maior of London.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of a Knight Bachelor.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of a Knight, Deane, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of the Maſter of the Rolles.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of other Iuſtices, and Barons of Checker.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of the Maior of Calice.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of a Doctor of Dininity.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of the Doctor of both the Lawes.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of him that hath beene Maior of London, and Sergeant of the Law.</item>
                        <item>The Eſtate of a Maſter of the Chancery, and other Worſhipfull Preachers and Clarkes that be graduable, and all other orders of chaſte perſons and Prieſts, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Merchants, and Gentlemen, all theſe may ſit at the Squires Table.</item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="186" facs="tcp:36146:102"/>
                     <p>A Duke may not kéepe the hall but each Eſtate by themſelues in Chamber or in Panilion, that neither ſée other: Marques, Earles, Biſhops and Vicounts, all theſe may ſit at a meſſe: a Baron and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor of London, and thrée chiefe Iudges, and the Speaker of the Parliaments, all theſe may ſit two or thrée at a meſſe: and all other ſtates may ſit three or foure at a meſſe: alſo the Marſhall muſt vnderſtand and know the blood Royall, for ſome Lord is of the blood Royall, and of ſmall liuelihood, and ſome Knight is wedded vnto a Lady of Royall blood, ſhe ſhall kéepe the Eſtate of her Lords blood, and therefore the Reyall blood ſhall haue the Reuerence, as I haue ſhewed you before: alſo a Marſhall muſt take heed of the birth, and next of the line of the blood Royall: Alſo he muſt take heed of the Kings Officers, of the Chancellor, Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Chamberlaine, Treaſurer, and Comptroller.</p>
                     <p>Alſo, the Marſhall muſt take héed vnto ſtrangers, and put them to worſhip and reuerence, for if they haue good cheere it is your Soueraignes honour. Alſo a Marſhall muſt take héed, if the King ſend
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:36146:102"/>your Soueraigne any meſſage, and if hee ſend a Knight, receiue him as a Baron, and if he ſend a Yeoman receiue him as a Squire, and if he ſend a Groome, receiue him as a Yeoman. Alſo it is no rebuke to a Knight, to ſet a groome of the Kings at his Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <head>A true and approved Receit, for the right making of the beſt Ipocras.</head>
                     <p>TAke of Grains halfe a dragm, take of Cinamon <hi>4.</hi> ounces, of Ginger, two ounces, of Nutmegges halfe an ounce, of Cloues and Mace of either a quarter of an ounce, bruiſe theſe well in a Mortar, and infuſe them in a gallon of white wine <hi>4.</hi> or <hi>5.</hi> dayes, the veſſell being cloſe ſtopt, then put to it a pound of ſugar, and a half, when the ſugar is diſſolued, put to it balf a pinte of Roſe-water, and as much milke; let it ſtand a night, and then let it run thorow in Ipocras Bagge, then may you put it into a fine new Rundlet if you purpoſe is péepe it, or if you ſpend it preſently, you may put it into certaine pots for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <pb n="188" facs="tcp:36146:103"/>
                     <head>An excellent and much approved receit, for a long Conſumption.</head>
                     <p>TAke <hi>8.10.</hi> or <hi>11.</hi> white Snayles, and breake away their ſhells from them, then put them into a bowle of water for twelue houres, to clenſe themſelues from their ſlime, then take them from that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and put them into an other bowle of running water for twelue howers more, then take them out, and put them into halfe a pinte of White Wine, and keepe them in it twelue houres, then take a quart of Red Cowes Milke; and put the Snayles out of the Wine into the Milk, and boyle the quart of Milke with the Snayles put into it, vntill it be boyld to a pinte, then put into it one ounce of Canded Sugar, and ſo giue the ſick party the ſame to drinke euery morning, and at foure of the clocke in the afternoone, but you muſt not let the ſick party eate or drinke any thing elſe for the ſpace of two houre s af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they haue taken this Receit, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt, this being duely made and taken accordingly, will with Gods help<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> recouer the party being very weak and
<pb facs="tcp:36146:103"/>farre ſpent in this long lingering ſickneſſe, and of my knowledge hath béene often ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, and is found an excellent Receit to cure the ſame diſeaſe.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div n="1" type="table_of_contents">
                  <head>A Table of the firſt book.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>A Bill of ſervice for an extraordinary Feaſt <hi>for Summer ſeaſon: fiftie diſhes to a Meſſe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>THe firſt courſe. Fol. 3.</item>
                     <item>The ſecond courſe for the ſame Meſſe. Fol. 4</item>
                     <item>The third courſe for the ſame Meſſe. Fol. 5</item>
                     <item>Another direction for a bill of fare for winter ſeaſon, which alſo ſerveth to ſet forth your meat in order. Fol. 5</item>
                     <item>The ſecond courſe for the ſame Meſſe. Fol. 6</item>
                     <item>The firſt courſe for a ſmall common Service of Meat, to direct them which are unperfect, to bring them to further knowledge of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Service. Fol. 7</item>
                     <item>A ſecond courſe to the ſame Meſſe Fol. 8</item>
                     <item>A Table of direction for a bill of Fare for Fiſh
<pb facs="tcp:36146:104"/>dayes, and Faſting dayes, Emberweeks, or Lent.</item>
                     <item>The firſt courſe for the ſame dyet. Fol 19</item>
                     <item>The ſecond courſe for the ſame dyet. Fol 10</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Boylde-Meates.</head>
                     <item>TO boyle a Capon Larded with Lemmons, on the French faſhion. Fol 11</item>
                     <item>To ſowce a Pigge. Fol 11</item>
                     <item>To ſowce Oyſters. Fol 12</item>
                     <item>To ſowce a Pike, Carpe or Breame. Fol 13</item>
                     <item>To boyle Flounders, or Gudgeons on the French faſhion. Fol 14</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Gurnet on the French faſhion. Fol 14</item>
                     <item>To boyle a legge of Mutton on the French fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. Fol 15</item>
                     <item>To haſh a legge of Mutton on the French fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. Fol 15</item>
                     <item>To roaſt a Legge of Mutton on the French fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. Fol 16</item>
                     <item>To roaſt a Neates-tongue on the French fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. Fol 16</item>
                     <item>To boyle Pigeons with Rice, on the French faſhion. Fol 17</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Rabbet with Hearbes on the French faſhion. Fol 17</item>
                     <item>To boyle Chickens in whitebroth. Fol 18</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Teale, or widgeon, on the French faſhion. Fol 29</item>
                     <item>To ſmoore an old Coney, Duck, or Mallard on
<pb facs="tcp:36146:104"/>the French faſhion. Fol 19</item>
                     <item>Another way to boyle Chickens. or Pigeons with Gooſe-berries or Grapes. Fol 20</item>
                     <item>To boyle a chine of Mutton or Veale, in ſharp broth on the French faſhion. Fol 21</item>
                     <item>To boyle Larkes or Sparrowes. Fol 21</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Baked-Meates.</head>
                     <item>A Made diſh of Coney Livers. Fol 22</item>
                     <item>A made diſh of ſweet breads. Fol 22</item>
                     <item>A made diſh of Sheeps tongues. Fol 23</item>
                     <item>A Florentine of a Coney, the wing of a Capon, or a Kidney of Veale. Fol 23</item>
                     <item>A Chewet of Stockfiſh Fol 24</item>
                     <item>A Frydayes Pye, without either fleſh or fiſh.</item>
                     <item>A quarter tart of pippins. Fol 25</item>
                     <item>A Gooſeberry tart Fol 26</item>
                     <item>A Cherrytart. Fol 26</item>
                     <item>To make an Oyſter-pye. Fol 26</item>
                     <item>A made diſh of Muſcels and Cockles. Fol 27</item>
                     <item>To bake a Neates-tongue to be eaten hot. Fol 27</item>
                     <item>A delicate Chewet. Fol 28</item>
                     <item>To make an Vmble pye, or for want of Vmbles, to doe it with a Lambes head and Purtenance. Fol 28</item>
                     <item>To bake a Calves Chaldron. Fol 29</item>
                     <item>To bake a Carpe. Fol 29</item>
                     <item>To bake a Tench with a pudding in her belly. Fol 30</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:36146:105"/>
                     <item>To bake Eeles. Fol 31</item>
                     <item>To bake Chickens with Grapes. Fol 31</item>
                     <item>To bake a ſteake pye with a french pudding in the pye. Fol 31</item>
                     <item>To make a good quince pye. Fol 32</item>
                     <item>To make a pippin pye. Fol 33</item>
                     <item>To bake a Pigge. Fol 33</item>
                     <item>To bake Fallow Deere in the beſt manner. Fol 33</item>
                     <item>To bake red Deere. Fol 34</item>
                     <item>To bake a wilde boare. Fol 34</item>
                     <item>To bake a Swanne. Fol 35</item>
                     <item>To bake a Turkey or Capon. Fol 35</item>
                     <item>To bake a Hare on the French faſhion. Fol 35</item>
                     <item>To bake a wilde Gooſe or Mallard. Fol 36</item>
                     <item>To bake a Curlew or Herneſhaw. Fol 36</item>
                     <item>To bake Woodcooks or Blackbirds. Fol 37</item>
                     <item>To bake Larks or Sparrowes. Fol 37</item>
                     <item>Fritters on the Court faſhion. Fol 37</item>
                     <item>To make Pancakes ſo criſpe that you may ſet them upright. Fol <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8</item>
                     <item>A Sallet of Roſe buds and Clove Gilly flowers. Fol 38</item>
                     <item>To keepe greene Cucumbers all the yeare. Fol 38</item>
                     <item>To keepe broome Capers. Fol 38</item>
                     <item>Purſlaine ſtalkes. Fol 39</item>
                     <item>To make Caper-rowles of Raddiſh Cods. Fol 39</item>
                     <item>Divers Sallets boyled, Fol 39</item>
                     <item>Buds of Hops. Fol 40</item>
                     <item>A Sallet of Mallowes. Fol 40</item>
                     <item>A Sallet of Burdoek-roots. Fol 40</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:36146:105"/>
                     <item>To make blancht Manchet in a Prying panne. Fol. 41</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Puddings.</head>
                     <item>A Farced Pudding. Fol. 42</item>
                     <item>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udding of Veale. Fol. 43</item>
                     <item>A Fregeſey of Egges. Fol. 44</item>
                     <item>A Cambridge Pudding. Fol. 44</item>
                     <item>A Swan or Gooſe pudding. Fol. 45</item>
                     <item>A Leveridge, or Hogs pudding, Fol. 45</item>
                     <item>A Chiveridge pudding. Fol. 46</item>
                     <item>A Rice pudding. Fol. 46</item>
                     <item>A Florentine of Veale. Fol. 46</item>
                     <item>A Marrow toaſt. Fol. 47</item>
                     <item>Another in a Fryingpan Fol. 48</item>
                     <item>A pudding ſtewed between two diſhes. Fol. 48</item>
                     <item>To make French puffes with green Hearbes. Fol. 49</item>
                     <item>Dropt Raiſins Fol. 50</item>
                     <item>A fond Pudding. Fol. 50</item>
                     <item>To make uffes on the Engliſh faſhion. Fol. 51</item>
                     <item>To make a pudding in a fryingpan. Fol. 52</item>
                     <item>To make Apple puffes. Fol. 52</item>
                     <item>To make Kickſhawes. Fol. 53</item>
                     <item>To make ſome Kickſhawes in paſte to fry or bake in what forme you pleaſe. Fol. 54</item>
                     <item>To make an Italian pudding. Fol. 55</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Rack of Veal on the French faſhion. Fol. 56</item>
                     <item>To farce a Leg of Lamb on the French faſhion. Fol. 56</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:36146:106"/>
                     <item>To haſh Deere, Sheepe, or Calves tongues on the French faſhion. Fol. 57</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Engliſh Cookery.</head>
                     <item>TO boyle a Capon. Fol. 58</item>
                     <item>To garniſh your Diſhes. Fol. 59</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Capon another way. Fol. 59</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Capon in Rice. Fol. 60</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Capon with Oyſters, and pickled Lemmon. Fol. 61</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Capon with Pippins. Fol. 62</item>
                     <item>To boyle Chickens in Whitebroth. Fol. 63</item>
                     <item>To boyle Chickens in Soope. Fol. 63</item>
                     <item>To boyle the common way. Fol. 64</item>
                     <item>To boyle Chickens with Lettice, the beſt way. Fol. 65</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Rabbet. Fol. 66</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Rabbet with Grapes and Gooſeber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Fol. 66</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Rabbet with Claret wine. Fol. 66</item>
                     <item>To boyle a wilde Duck. Fol. 67</item>
                     <item>To boyle a tame Duck, or Widgin. Fol. 67</item>
                     <item>To boyle Pigeons. Fol. 68</item>
                     <item>To boyle Pigeons with Capers or Sampyre. Fol. 68</item>
                     <item>To boyle Sawceges. Fol. 69</item>
                     <item>To boyle Gooſe Giblets, Swannes Giblets. Fol. 69</item>
                     <item>Giblets with Hearbs and Roots. Fol. 70</item>
                     <item>To ſmoore a Racke, or ribbes of Mutton. Fol. 70</item>
                     <item>For the fillets of a Veale, ſmoored in a frying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panne. Fol. 71</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:36146:106"/>
                     <item>A Diſh of ſteakes of Mutton, ſmoored in a frying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan. Fol. 71</item>
                     <item>To ſmoore a Chicken. Fol. 72</item>
                     <item>To fry Muſcles, Pery-Winckles, or Oyſters to ſerve with a Duck, or ſingle by themſelvs Fol. 72.</item>
                     <item>To marble Smelts, Soales, Flounders, plaice, &amp;c. Fol. 73</item>
                     <item>To Conger Eeles in Collars, like Brawne. Fol. 73</item>
                     <item>To ſowce a Pigge in collars. Fol. 74</item>
                     <item>To ſowce a breaſt of Veale. Fol. 75</item>
                     <item>To haſh a ſhoulder of Mutton, or a leg of Lamb. Fol. 75</item>
                     <item>A leg of Lambe farſt with Hearbs. Fol. 76</item>
                     <item>To ſmoore Calves feet. Fol. 77</item>
                     <item>Another way. Fol. 77</item>
                     <item>To haſh Neates-tongues. Fol. 78</item>
                     <item>The ſame with Cheſt-nuts. Fol. 78</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Certaine Gellies.</head>
                     <item>CHriſtall Gelly. Fol. 79</item>
                     <item>To make Gelly of Pippins of the colour of Amber. Fol. 80</item>
                     <item>To make a Gelly of pippins, as orient red as Rubie. Fol. 81</item>
                     <item>To make white leach of Almonds. As alſo after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to make it either yellow, greene, or red. Fol. 81</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:107"/>
                  <head>A Table of the ſecond book.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>TO boyle a Capon larded with Lemmons, on the French faſhion. Fol. 87</item>
                     <item>To boyle Chickens. Fol. 88</item>
                     <item>An other way to boyle Chickens, or a Capon in White broth. Fol. 89</item>
                     <item>Another way to boyle Chickens for one that is ſick, and to provoke ſleep. Fol. 90</item>
                     <item>Another way to boyle them on Sorrelſops, for him that hath a weak ſtomack. Fol. 91</item>
                     <item>To boyle a partridge. Fol. 91</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Legge of Mutton on the French faſhion Fol. 93</item>
                     <item>To farce a legge of Mutton. Fol. 94</item>
                     <item>To farce a legge of Lambe. Fol. 95</item>
                     <item>To ſtew Trouts. Fol. 96</item>
                     <item>To make a farſt pudding. Fol. 97</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Pike. Fol. 98</item>
                     <item>To farce a Legge of Mutton on the French fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. Fol. 99</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Carpe or Breame. Fol. 101</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Wild Duck, Widgin, or a Teale on the French faſhion. Fol. 102</item>
                     <item>Another way to boyle ſmaller Carpes or Breames. Fol. 103</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:36146:107"/>
                     <item>Another way to boyl a Leg of Mutton or Lamb. Fol. 104</item>
                     <item>To boyle Ecles. Fol. 105</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Rabbet. Fol. 105</item>
                     <item>To boyle Lamprels. Fol. 106</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Neck, or a Loyne, or a Chine of Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, or to boyle a Neck, or Legge, a Fillet or a Knuckle of Veale, or to boyle a Leg or Loyn of Lamb. Fol. 107</item>
                     <item>To ſtew Smelts or Flounders. Fol. 108</item>
                     <item>To boyle Pigeons on the French faſhion. Fol. 109</item>
                     <item>Another way to boyle a Pike. Fol. 109</item>
                     <item>To boyle Olives of Veale. Fol. 111</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Mullet, or a Pike with Oyſters. Fol. 112</item>
                     <item>To boyle a tame Duck. Fol. 123</item>
                     <item>To make a raſher of Mutton, or of cold Lambe Fol. 113</item>
                     <item>To boyle a Knuckle of Veale, or a necke of Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. Fol. 114</item>
                     <item>To ſtew the ribbes of a neck of Veal in ſteakes. Fol. 115</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Bakte Meates, and Kick-ſhawes.</head>
                     <item>TO make a grand Sallet. Fol. 116</item>
                     <item>To ſo wee a Pigge. Fol. 117</item>
                     <item>To make puf-paſte. Fol. 118</item>
                     <item>To roaſt a Leg of Mutton, or a Cowes Vdder. Fol. 121</item>
                     <item>To make an Olive Pye to be eaten hot. Fol. 122</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:36146:108"/>
                     <item>To roaſt a ſhoulder of Mutton to ſerve for ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dinner or ſupper. Fol. 124</item>
                     <item>To bake a Chicken-pie to be eaten hot. Fol. 124</item>
                     <item>To roaſt a Neates tongue to be eaten hot. Fol. 125</item>
                     <item>To bake a Neates tongue to be eaten hot. Fol. 126</item>
                     <item>To bake a pigge with a pudding in his belly. Fol. 127</item>
                     <item>To bake a Pigge to be eaten hot. Fol. 128</item>
                     <item>Another way to roaſt a Legge of Mutton. Fol. 129</item>
                     <item>To bake a ſteake pie of the ribbes of Mutton, to be eaten hot. Fol. 130</item>
                     <item>To roaſt a Neck of Mutton. Fol. 131</item>
                     <item>To make a Hartichoak pie to be eaten hot. Fol. 132</item>
                     <item>To roaſt a Shoulder, or Hanch of Veniſon, or a Chine of Mutton. Fol. 133</item>
                     <item>To make Chewets of Veale. Fol. 134</item>
                     <item>To roaſt a Capon with Oyſters and Cheſtnuts Fol. 135</item>
                     <item>To bake a Quince, or a Warden Pie, ſo as the fruit may be red, and the cruſt pale and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Fol. 136</item>
                     <item>To roaſt a ſhoulder or a fillet of Veale with far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing hearbes. Fol. 137</item>
                     <item>To fry Calves feet, or Trotters. Fol. 138</item>
                     <item>Buttered Loaves. Fol. 138</item>
                     <item>To fry Sheepes tongues, Deeres tongues, or Calves tongues. Fol. 140</item>
                     <item>Boyld Sallets Fol. 141</item>
                     <item>A bakte pudding after the Italian faſhion. Fol. 142</item>
                     <item>To make puffes. Fol. 143</item>
                     <item>Blanch manchet to be made in a Frying pan. Fol. 144</item>
                     <item>To make Peaſcods, or Dolphins of Marrow, or
<pb facs="tcp:36146:108"/>of a roaſted Kidney of Veale. Fol. 144</item>
                     <item>To make a Livery pudding. Fol. 146</item>
                     <item>To make Rice puddings. Fol. 147</item>
                  </list>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Table to the Booke of Carving, and Sewing.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>TErmes for Carving. Fol. 151</item>
                        <item>The Office of the Butler and Pantler,</item>
                        <item>Yeoman of the Celler and Ewery. Fol. 152</item>
                        <item>The Sewing of Fleſh. Fol. 158</item>
                        <item>The Service of Fleſh. Fol. 158</item>
                        <item>The Carving of Fleſh. Fol. 159</item>
                        <item>Sawces for all manner of Fowles. Fol. 163</item>
                        <item>The carving of all manner of Fowle. Fol. 166</item>
                        <item>Service for the foure quarters of the yeere. Fol. 174</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Sewing of Fiſh, firſt, ſecond, and third Courſe. <hi>178</hi>
                        </head>
                        <item>CArving of Fiſh. Fol. 179</item>
                        <item>Sawces of all Fiſh. Fol. 181</item>
                        <item>Chamberlaines office. Fol. 182</item>
                        <item>The knowledge which ought to be in a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall, and Viher. Fol. 184</item>
                        <item>An excellent Receipt for to make the beſt Ipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras. Fol. 187</item>
                        <item>An approved Receit for a Conſumption though the party be far ſpent. Fol. 188</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:109"/>
               </div>
               <div type="illustration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:109"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Officit hic menti Dans pinguia fercula ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="illustration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36146:110" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>cuts and prices of meat</figDesc>
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE FAMILY GUIDE.</hi> shewing from an exact calculation, <hi>The Medium Price of Meat,</hi> and the relative value of each Joint. 1794</head>
                        <p>
                           <list>
                              <head>Hind Quarter</head>
                              <item>1. Sir-Loin 5<abbr>d</abbr> ½</item>
                              <item>2. Rump 5<abbr>d</abbr> ½</item>
                              <item>3. Aitch-Bone 4.<abbr>d</abbr>
                              </item>
                              <item>4. Buttock 4<abbr>d</abbr> ½</item>
                              <item>5. Mouse D.<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 3.<abbr>d</abbr>
                              </item>
                              <item>6. Veiny-Piece 4.<abbr>d</abbr>
                              </item>
                              <item>7. Thick-Flank 4.<abbr>d</abbr>
                              </item>
                              <item>8. Thin D.<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 4.<abbr>d</abbr>
                              </item>
                              <item>9. Leg 1<abbr>d</abbr> ½</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>Fore Quarter</head>
                              <item>10. Fore Rib, 5 Ribs 5<abbr>d</abbr> ½</item>
                              <item>11. Middle D.<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 4 <abbr>d.<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                                 </abbr> 3<abbr>d</abbr> ½</item>
                              <item>12. Chuck — 3 <abbr>d.<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                                 </abbr> 3<abbr>d</abbr> ½</item>
                              <item>13. Shol<hi rend="sup">r</hi> or Leg Mutt.* piece 3<abbr>d</abbr> ½</item>
                              <item>14. Brisket 4.<abbr>d</abbr>
                              </item>
                              <item>15. Clod 3.<abbr>d</abbr>
                              </item>
                              <item>16. Neck or Sticking Piece 2.<abbr>d</abbr>
                              </item>
                              <item>17. Shin 1<abbr>d</abbr> ½</item>
                              <item>18. Cheek</item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>LONDON</hi>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
